<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exposition of the divine standard of prayer, styl'd the Lord's Prayer of the preface, conclnsion [sic], and of every petition of it, as of the prayer of the kingdom of Messiah, the Lord Jesus Christ / by T. Beverley.</title>
            <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 234 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27600</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2141</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37096</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16207856</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16207856</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105089</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27600)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105089)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1087:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exposition of the divine standard of prayer, styl'd the Lord's Prayer of the preface, conclnsion [sic], and of every petition of it, as of the prayer of the kingdom of Messiah, the Lord Jesus Christ / by T. Beverley.</title>
                  <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 68 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Salusbury ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105089:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105089:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> AN EXPOSITION OF THE Divine Standard of Prayer, STYL'D THE <hi>Lord's Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the <hi>Preface, Concluſion,</hi> and of Every <hi>Petition</hi> of it; As of the <hi>PRAYER</hi> of the <hi>KINGDOM</hi> of <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>T. BEVERLEY.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>LUKE XI. 1.</bibl>
               <p>Lord, <hi>[Meſſiah]</hi> Teach us to Pray, as <hi>John [the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner]</hi> Taught his Diſciples.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>John Salusbury,</hi> at the <hi>Riſing Sun</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi> 1692.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:105089:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:105089:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The PREFACE</hi> to the Expoſition upon the <hi>Prayer, Jeſus Christ</hi> hath <hi>Taught</hi> us in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> as the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THIS <hi>Prayer, Taught by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> which is of due Right, the <hi>Admiration</hi> and <hi>Veneration</hi> of all <hi>Seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> and <hi>Underſtanding Chriſtians;</hi> hath yet been very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle underſtood in the Excellency of its <hi>Spirit,</hi> and High In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.</p>
            <p>I confeſs my ſelf to have been much in the Dark concerning it, till ihis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Earneſt Application of my Thoughts to it, and much diſtracted in my Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment about it: But I am now ſatisfied, even to Humble Aſtoniſhment at the Divine VViſdom of it, underſtanding it as the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom;</hi> which hath given me Reſolution in great Doubts concerning it, as I ſhall now hriefly preſent, and more fully Treat in the following Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It ſeem'd very perplexing to me, whether this prayer was intendeded as a <hi>Form of Prayer, or as a Pattern of Prayer;</hi> of this I have given a full Reſolution in the following Diſcourſe, That it is a Prayer comprehending All <hi>Prayer,</hi> that is according to the <hi>word of God;</hi> It is a Treaſury, or <hi>Sea of Prayer,</hi> from which all Flows, and into which all Returnes, if duly Expounded according to the whole <hi>word of God;</hi> and the <hi>word of God,</hi> as it directs in <hi>Prayer,</hi> is referr'd to it. And becauſe, The <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt</hi> is in all things the <hi>Central Point,</hi> where all the <hi>Lines of Prayer</hi> meet That <hi>Kingdom</hi> muſt needs be alſo the <hi>Center</hi> of this <hi>Prayer</hi> and the higheſt Intention of it, and of all contained in it; Thus, as to the Matter of this Prayer; And then, as to the <hi>Form</hi> of it, It is a <hi>Pattern,</hi> or <hi>Exemplar</hi> of that Plain, Spiritual, Continued, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>naffected manner of <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> And No Other ought to be preſcribed. But as a meer <hi>Form,</hi> there appears no obligation to it; either by precept, or <hi>Scripture Example,</hi> as is to be ſhown: And further, It being ſo Brief, and ſo Full of Senſe, what Thoughts can take in that ſenſe, keeping Time with the Repetition of it; And yet an excited underſtanding, and Enflamed Affections are no more barred from it, than from other expreſſions of Scripture; But They had need be both much exalted, when we uſe this Prayer in the whole Form, that we may not take it in vain: It being never intended for a Refuge of Cold or Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Formalities.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It ſeemed very Strange to me to find this <hi>Prayer</hi> to have ſo many <hi>Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> Taken from the <hi>Jewiſh Formules,</hi> or little Forms of <hi>Petition</hi> ſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally
<pb facs="tcp:105089:3"/> Allowed by All Converſant to their Writings, to have been in uſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them. This Enclined me to Think, It was a <hi>Prayer,</hi> given only for the <hi>Time then being,</hi> to the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> till the Deſcent of the <hi>Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> upon them. But Obſerving it to be the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom, given by the Meſſiah;</hi> I Find it very agreeable to the Sublimation of what was Found among the <hi>Jews;</hi> as of their <hi>Baptiſmal waſhings</hi> into the Inſtitution of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> and the <hi>Cup of Bleſſing</hi> into that of the <hi>Lords Supper;</hi> So the <hi>Prayer</hi> uſual among them for the <hi>Kingdom of Meſſiah,</hi> and the Bleſſed <hi>Priviledges</hi> of that State, are exalted by <hi>Chriſt</hi> into this <hi>Prayer;</hi> To ſhew the Intereſt the <hi>Jews</hi> had in this Great <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and the <hi>Ancient Promiſes</hi> of it all along the <hi>Propheſies;</hi> and ſo moſt Fittly is a <hi>Prayer Compoſed</hi> out of their <hi>Petitions</hi> for this <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. I could not, but be under much ſcruple, and trouble, to Find, that the <hi>Prayer of our Great Mediator</hi> ſhould not bear his <hi>Name;</hi> in which we are to <hi>Pray to the Father;</hi> nor carry any Expreſs Mention of <hi>His Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption,</hi> nor of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> the <hi>Giving</hi> of which was the Great, and Blrſſed Conſequence of <hi>His Aſſencion:</hi> But by conſidering, as I have done in the following Diſcourſe, I find nothing more Effectuall to Moove <hi>Chrſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> off from <hi>Reſting</hi> in and even <hi>Idolizing</hi> this <hi>Prayer</hi> as a <hi>Form,</hi> or to carry them to <hi>Pray</hi> according to it in ſo <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Admirable manner,</hi> but to ſearch the whole <hi>Goſpel</hi> to find the <hi>Divine Senſes</hi> of this <hi>Prayer,</hi> and not with out underſtanding it to be Satisfied in the ſo often <hi>Repetitions</hi> of it, ſo cotrary to the very End of its <hi>Inſtitution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Doubts being thus Remoov'd; I find a very <hi>Glorious</hi> and <hi>Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Harmony</hi> in the <hi>Petitions,</hi> with that <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> as it ſhall Appear in its Full Dimenſions of <hi>Happineſs,</hi> and <hi>Bleſſedneſs;</hi> And therefore, altho, all the Preſent <hi>Holy,</hi> and proper <hi>Senſes</hi> of each <hi>Petition</hi> are no way wav'd or diſparag'd hy this Diſcourſs, but earneſtly Recommended; Yet it is Proved, that ſtill the Higheſt Elevation of this <hi>Prayer,</hi> and of every <hi>Petition</hi> in it is the <hi>Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and therein we are to <hi>Pray</hi> in the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> for that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> without which we can never <hi>Pray</hi> this <hi>Prayer</hi> aright, nor <hi>Read</hi> it; as our Saviour Commands us; or declare of His Servants, that they do ſo, <hi>viz. Expound</hi> it, when they <hi>Pray Aright</hi> out of the <hi>Word of God</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For it is all along in this Diſcourſe, Endeavored to be Maniffeſted, thus we never <hi>Pray Aright</hi> according to the <hi>word of God,</hi> but we <hi>Pray</hi> as from the Springs flowing out of this Ocean of <hi>Prayer;</hi> and our <hi>Prayer</hi> Fals into it; So that we ought, and are Commanded to <hi>Read</hi> out of It, when we <hi>Pray.</hi> And it is Pronounced in our behalf, that we do ſo <hi>Pray,</hi> out of it and into it, when ſoever we ſo <hi>Pray,</hi> according to the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> tho we do not at all Repeat the <hi>Words,</hi> and the <hi>Interceſſion</hi> of our Great <hi>Mediator,</hi> and the Vertue of His <hi>Mediatory Prayer</hi> is allways Falling upon His Servants in ſo Praying. I Therefore Magnify this <hi>Prayer,</hi> in this Expoſition, and moſt Humbly, and Earneſtly Recommend it with All <hi>Prayer,</hi> and <hi>Suppication,</hi> for the Right underſtandihg and <hi>Holy</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:105089:3"/>
            <head>The DEDICATION To the Archbiſhop of CANTERBURY.</head>
            <p>THE following <hi>Expoſition</hi> is moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly Preſented, with all Regards of <hi>Reverence</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> which the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſages</hi> of this Nation have Affix'd to ſo Great a Character and Station; and to the Perſonage in it, with ſincereſt Veneration of the Exemplary Piety, Holineſs of <hi>Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> Largeneſs of Mind and Underſtanding, Sagaciouſneſs of Reaſon, and Truly Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Equanimity, Condeſcention, and Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Catholickneſs of Spirit, ſo Illuſtrious in Him before all the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> at this Time; and according to the full Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of the Offerer; who therefore Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeches the Acceptance of Himſelf, and of what is Preſented.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing ſuch a Station is a large Province of doing Good; and that a Servant of God ought to improve it as ſo; There is nothing can be more Earneſtly or Humbly Deſired, then that this <hi>Expoſition</hi> of ſo Grand a Portion or part of Scripture, may, if it ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced
<pb facs="tcp:105089:4"/> of Falſhood, or Contrariety to the Glory, Wiſdom, Truth and Holineſs of the Giver, be Redargued in the ſame manner, It is endeavour'd to be Argued; not with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to circumſtantial Miſtakes, or Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſights, from which nothing in the preſent ſtate is Free, and without any perſonal References to the Expoſitor (who before hand lays himſelf Proſtrate) which can neither add nor take away from <hi>ſubstantial Truths:</hi> For ſo is the Apoſtolick Precept to an <hi>Evangelick Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> ſeated in <hi>Authority</hi> to do it; to <hi>Reprove</hi> by <hi>Elenchizing</hi> or <hi>Argumentation;</hi> when the merit of the caſe requires it; But if on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide what is <hi>written</hi> be <hi>upright,</hi> and <hi>words of Truth;</hi> ſuch a Perſon will, I doubt not, take care that He that hath ſo <hi>Laboured in the word and Doctrine</hi> may receive the <hi>double Honour al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loted by Chriſt;</hi> Theſe are obligations on Him, that is entruſted with a <hi>Goſpel Oeconomy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Concernment is very great, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Expoſition</hi> of the <hi>Prayer</hi> ſo univerſally Styled <hi>The Lord's Prayer;</hi> Both becauſe the Prayer is an ineſtimable Treaſure, and even Treaſury to all <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> and that in its very
<pb facs="tcp:105089:4"/> Repetition, it is made ſo eſſential to the Form of Publick Worſhip in this (as it owns it ſelf) <hi>National Church,</hi> and <hi>by Law Eſtabliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Expoſition</hi> is alſo Levelled to the Higheſt Point of <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> If it be; as it is declared; ſo ſupreme a Truth of the Goſpel, as the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> peculiar to Him as the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> as the <hi>great Son of Man is;</hi> who hath it <hi>written on his Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stim,</hi> and <hi>on his Thigh, King of Kings, Lord of Lords;</hi> Not only as He hath unchangeably a Kingdom, as the <hi>eternal Word,</hi> or as He now hath <hi>All Power in Heaven, and Earth.</hi> But in a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble glorious <hi>Kingdom,</hi> the <hi>Kingdom of the Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Years;</hi> that great Feſtival <hi>of Tabernacles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8. 15.</note> that ſhall be celebrated with everlaſting Joy, with <hi>Lawrels, Olives</hi> and <hi>Palms,</hi> with all the Glory, Verdure and Flouriſh of <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> when the Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of the higheſt Heaven ſhall be, as it were, left for that Time; the <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Throne of God</hi> and of the <hi>Lamb</hi> ſhall <hi>come down</hi> with the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> into the <hi>New Heaven</hi> above, and into the <hi>New Earth</hi> beneath, <hi>as in Heaven and on Earth,</hi> according to this <hi>Prayer.</hi> This <hi>Tabernacle-ſtate</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 13.</note> 
               <hi>of God</hi> with, and <hi>comming down</hi> to be <hi>with men,</hi> Not They with him; gives ſtyle to this <hi>Feaſt of</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:105089:5"/> 
               <hi>Tabernacles,</hi> ſo renowned by the <hi>Prophet Zecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> c. 14. Becauſe it is not the everlaſting Pallace, but the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> of a <hi>thouſand Years;</hi> at the end of which, as a Kingdom <hi>Deliver'd up,</hi> It is drawn up again to God All in All, and All Tabernacle-State ceaſes; And ſeeing now, as is moſt <hi>constantly Affirmed,</hi> This <hi>Kingdom,</hi> according to an exact Calculation of <hi>Scripture-time,</hi> ſhall be in its Succeſſion, and to prepare for its Glory within five Summers; and that as in the <hi>Sermon upon the Witneſſes Riſing,</hi> herewith Printed; There ſhall be the Avant-Courriers of that Succeſſion, all along theſe very Five Years: This ſolemn Appeal, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Greatneſs and Dignity of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects Treated of, is Preſented to ſuch an <hi>Angel,</hi> in the Church of Ghriſt as is Tuly Hoped, in whom the <hi>National Epiſcopacy</hi> and <hi>Pastoral Office</hi> draws to a Point, and Unit, and ſo is Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to All in Him, By</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Their most Humble Servant in the Prophecy of Jeſus Christ, <hi>T. BEVERLEY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105089:5"/>
            <head>AN EXPOSITION Of the <hi>PRAYER</hi> we <hi>Generally Stile, The Lord's Prayer.</hi> According to the <hi>Evangeliſts, Matthew,</hi> and <hi>Luke,</hi> Mat. 6. 9. Luke 11. 1. SHEWING, That according to its True Elevation, It is the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom,</hi> viz. of the <hi>Thouſand Years Kingdom of Christ,</hi> in the <hi>New Heaven,</hi> or <hi>Jeruſalem above;</hi> and in the <hi>New Earth,</hi> or <hi>Jeruſalem below.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I Have treated much of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> and endeavour'd t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> demonſtrate it from a great Concert of <hi>Scriptures.</hi> Now This <hi>Prayer</hi> is a moſt deſervedly Celebrated Portion of <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and even Summary of <hi>Scripture;</hi> eſpecially with relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>Prayer,</hi> it being a <hi>Prayer</hi> taught by Chriſt to his <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> when he was here upon Earth; and in them to all Succeſſions of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> until his <hi>Kingdom comes.</hi> Therefore It muſt be preſum'd to draw within it ſelf whatever is matter of Deſire, and ſo of <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> throughout the <hi>Scripture.</hi> Seeing then this <hi>Kingdom</hi> muſt needs be the moſt Earneſt and Paſſionate Deſire, and <hi>Prayer</hi> of the Servants of Chriſt; It would be a deep Prejudice againſt the Doctrine of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105089:6"/> 
               <hi>Kingdom,</hi> if it could not be found within this <hi>Prayer.</hi> But on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, If it ſhall be found, that all the Lines of the Prayer meet in it, as in a Center; ſo that it muſt be, according to its Trne Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, the <hi>Prayer</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> It will certainly much incline to the Belief of ſuch a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> Thoſe, who have not hitherto receiv'd it into their Faith, Hope, and Expectation.</p>
            <p>It is therefore moſt expedient, I ſhould by the Aſſiſtance of the Spirit, undertake an Expoſition of this <hi>Prayer;</hi> ſince I (on ſo great Reaſon) eſteem it to be the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom,</hi> and therein mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, It is ſuch; and that, as ſuch, it ought to be <hi>Prayed</hi> by all the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Chriſt, according to ſuch meaſures of <hi>Praying</hi> it, as ſhall be given, until that very <hi>Kingdom come;</hi> and more eſpecially by us, who live ſo near the Approaches of it, as we may by the <hi>Holy Books understand</hi> we do; and therefore ſhould more earneſtly <hi>pray</hi> for it, (as <hi>Daniel,</hi> of old, for <hi>Jeruſalem)</hi> by this <hi>very Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let it be no Prejudice then, I beſeech you, to Any, who ſhall read this Expoſition; that I add another Interpretation of this <hi>Prayer,</hi> as the <hi>Prayer</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> to all thoſe Interpretations that you may have heretofore receiv'd, and may be now in your Families: For I acknowledge thoſe Interpretations, or Expoſitions, to be of very great, not only Excellency, and Uſe, but alſo Neceſſity: I am ſo far from drawing you off from them, that I receive them with greateſt Veneration and Reverence, and declare of them ſo to others</p>
            <p>But think it not ſtrange, that he who <hi>ſpake, as never Man ſpake;</hi> and therefore moſt Juſtly it ought to be believ'd of him, that when he <hi>Taught to pray,</hi> he ſo <hi>Taught,</hi> as <hi>never Man,</hi> beſides himſelf <hi>Taught to pray:</hi> Think it not ſtrange, I ſay, that he Compriz'd in this <hi>Prayer</hi> Things beyond the ordinary Apprehenſion, beyond the Surface of Things: For he hath ſo fram'd this <hi>Prayer,</hi> that it begins at the Foundation of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> the <hi>Spirituality</hi> of it in the <hi>Works of Grace</hi> here; and it riſes to the Top of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> in the <hi>Glory</hi> of an <hi>Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Appearance;</hi> and ſo guides the Prayers of his Servants by it, in relation to their State in Grace here, and even to their whole State in this World, in Subordination to it, as to riſe in their Deſires to that higher State of <hi>Bodies</hi> of the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> in <hi>Glory;</hi> wherein they ſhall Appear before the <hi>Throne of God, and of the Lamb,</hi> in the <hi>New Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem above;</hi> and alſo to have regard in their P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayers, according to this <hi>Prayer,</hi> to the <hi>New Creation of God,</hi> in a <hi>New Earth,</hi> a State of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution</hi> to all the <hi>Creatures,</hi> as in a <hi>New Jeruſalem below:</hi> And even through all This, our Lord hath in this <hi>Prayer</hi> peirc'd and ſoar'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond, even into the <hi>Kingdom of Eternity,</hi> when <hi>God ſhall be All in All.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:105089:6"/>
            <p> Now as to the Firſt, the State of the <hi>Kingdom of Grace,</hi> which is now; and alſo with relation to the <hi>Kingdom of Eternity,</hi> which ſhall be at the <hi>utmoſt, hereafter,</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom Deliver'd</hi> up; I preſume to add nothing to the General Expoſitions, already ſo full, but ſhall only endeavour to draw the Lines of the Diſcourſe in parallel to the <hi>Epiphania,</hi> or Luſtre of the <hi>Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> in his <hi>Glorious Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I only premiſe in the General, That I reſt upon the Guard of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence over this <hi>Elect</hi> Portion of <hi>Scripture;</hi> And that it hath ſo watch'd over it, as to ſurprize and prevent any Change of it; So that we have whatever the Divine Spirit Dictated to the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> concerning it, and juſt as it Dictated to each <hi>Evangeliſt:</hi> I therefore matter no Difference of <hi>Copies;</hi> but as this <hi>Prayer</hi> is giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n by Two <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> and at Two ſeveral Times, and on Two ſeveral Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, or Accounts; ſo God hath preſerv'd the <hi>Prayer</hi> in each <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt,</hi> as we find it; and ſo I proceed to Diſcourſe upon it.</p>
            <p>I begin with this <hi>Prayer,</hi> therefore, as we find it in the <hi>Evangeliſt Matthew,</hi> where it is plac'd in the midſt of the <hi>Sermon on the Mount;</hi> in which our Lord, gathering together the great Heads of the <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuality</hi> of the <hi>Doctrine of Chriſtianity,</hi> relating to <hi>Practice</hi> and <hi>Action,</hi> neceſſarily falls upon that high Point of <hi>Prayer:</hi> Firſt, He Regulates the End and Intention of <hi>Prayer,</hi> as having to do with God only in ſecret, and baniſhes from it all Phariſaic Oſtentation, and Deſire to be ſeen of Men; and from thence he ſlides into the manner, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delling of <hi>Prayer,</hi> and bars the <hi>Heathen</hi> way of <hi>Praying,</hi> from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king an Invaſion into the <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> as it ſeems it had done on the <hi>Jews;</hi> upon whom the <hi>Gentiles Times</hi> of Servitude under the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> now ſate heavy; and their Principles had too much <hi>Leav'ned</hi> many of the <hi>Jews:</hi> Our Lord therefore Cautions his Diſciples againſt the <hi>Leaven of Herod,</hi> implying the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> and againſt the <hi>Leaven of the Phariſees,</hi> implying the Corrupted <hi>Judaiſm,</hi> Mark 8. 15.</p>
            <p>And undoubtedly in this very <hi>Prayer,</hi> our Lord Remonſtrated to All After-Ages of Chriſtians againſt that Falſe <hi>Judaiſm,</hi> and the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiliſm</hi> of the <hi>Antichriſtian Apoſtacy,</hi> in this very matter of <hi>Prayer;</hi> which yet in his <hi>Divine Spirit,</hi> He Fore-ſaw would come upon it, under the <hi>working</hi> of the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> and the <hi>Revelation</hi> of the <hi>Man of Sin:</hi> And the <hi>Apocalyptick Prophecy</hi> foretells it under thoſe very Names, <hi>Jews;</hi> who <hi>Lyed,</hi> in <hi>ſaying, They were Jews,</hi> and <hi>were not;</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who Crouded into the <hi>Outer Court,</hi> and <hi>Took away this Daily Sacrifice</hi> of <hi>Spiritual Evangelical Prayer,</hi> and brought in <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Superſtition</hi> in rhe room of it.</p>
            <p>When therefore our Great <hi>High Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Prophet</hi> Commanded to <hi>Pray after this manner,</hi> giving only the Summary of <hi>Prayer,</hi> that muſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105089:7"/> needs intend Enlargement, according to every Head; and in this Plain and Unaffected Method, and intire Compoſure of Prayer, without interruptions, or breakings off; without <hi>Repetitions,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intermixed <hi>Reſponſals,</hi> or <hi>Suffrages;</hi> He hath for ever Damned All thoſe preſcribed, impoſed <hi>Liturgies,</hi> and <hi>Litanies,</hi> that conſiſt of theſe; and particularly the ſo often <hi>Repetitions</hi> of this <hi>Prayer,</hi> which is exceedingly injur'd, and affrouted thereby, the very avowed inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it being againſt all Affected <hi>Repetitions,</hi> and ſo of it ſelf eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially. Accordingly, the <hi>Firſt,</hi> and <hi>pureſt Times</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity pray'd</hi> after this Plain, Unaffected Manner of <hi>Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it is not to be thought, It was any part of our <hi>Lord's</hi> meaning to abridge the pouring out <hi>Prayer</hi> unto God, when the Soul is full of Affection, and flows out into Expreſſion, as abundant; even as Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>continued a whole Night in Prayer,</hi> and hath left to his Church up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Record, that much larger <hi>Prayer,</hi> as it were, ſome Sample of his <hi>Great Interceſſion,</hi> John 17. Nor does he lay his Prohibition upon the <hi>Repetition</hi> of the very ſame Words, when the Spirit within, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting earneſtly upon the ſame Thing, Naturally chuſes again, and again, the very ſame Words; Fot he himſelf <hi>Thrice</hi> uſed the ſame Words concerning the Removal of the <hi>Cup from him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now with this <hi>Prayer,</hi> as given in this <hi>Sermon on the Mount,</hi> hath our Lord interwoven many great Principles of Chriſtianity, as he makes plain, by enlarging upon them; as that of <hi>Forgiveneſs of Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes,</hi> according to that; <hi>That we ſhould forgive,</hi> even as we deſire to be <hi>Forgiven;</hi> of <hi>ſeeking the Kingdom of God,</hi> and the <hi>Righteouſneſs of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in the <hi>Firſt</hi> place; according to that, <hi>Thy Kingdom come;</hi> of truſting Providence with the Things of <hi>To Morrow;</hi> according to that, <hi>Give us this Day;</hi> and of not truſting to the <hi>ſaying, Lord, Lord,</hi> without doing the <hi>Will of our Father,</hi> according to that, <hi>Thy Will be done;</hi> Of All which the Exppſitors of this <hi>Prayer</hi> in general have excellently treated.</p>
            <p>Let it be then allowed, and acknowledg'd, that the Sum of the Account of our <hi>Lord's</hi> giving this <hi>Prayer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> as in the <hi>Sermon on the Mount,</hi> is, To give a <hi>Prayer</hi> Commenſurate with the whole <hi>Doctrine of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity,</hi> to all his Diſciples; And his commanding Them to <hi>pray after this manner,</hi> included a Command to obtain an Acquaintance with the Spiritual Senſe and Meaning of this <hi>Prayer,</hi> which they are to learn from the whole <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Goſpel of the Kingdom.</hi> For it cannot be expected, the Great Concernmenss of Chriſtianity this <hi>Prayer</hi> refers unto, as they fall within <hi>Prayer</hi> in general, ſhould be found ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitly within this Summary of <hi>Prayer</hi> for them; That Chriſtians therefore may be able to <hi>pray after this manner,</hi> or according to the mighty Importances of this Prayer, the Variety of their own States,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105089:7"/> and all the Occaſions thereof, and according to the various Motions of their own Spirits, the whole <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Goſpel of the Kingdom</hi> muſt <hi>dwell Richly</hi> in them; that they may all ſteer by the Compaſs of this <hi>Prayer;</hi> as Men upon the Sea ſhape various Courſes, and yet all ſail by one Compaſs, that never varies; So ſhould we in <hi>Prayer,</hi> by this <hi>Prayer,</hi> underſtood according to the whole <hi>Doctrine of Chriſt,</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and no otherwiſe to be underſtood.</p>
            <p>And as to the Manner, That there ſhould be no Preſcribing after Chriſt; For what <hi>can the Man do,</hi> that <hi>comes after him?</hi> who would yet preſcribe no otherwiſe, than thus in brief, and in this plain, ſincere way, without Artifice, without Doublings this way, and that way; and yet by ſuch an All-Comprehending Wiſdom; that no Man can <hi>pray</hi> according to the Word of God, but he muſt <hi>pray</hi> according to this <hi>Prayer;</hi> For it is as the Sea to <hi>Prayer,</hi> All the Rivulets of Prayer come out <hi>of the Word of God,</hi> gathered into this <hi>Prayer,</hi> and hither <hi>they return again;</hi> whence they <hi>come out,</hi> thither they <hi>return.</hi> None can <hi>pray</hi> according to the <hi>Word of God,</hi> but however inſenſible we are of it, as of <hi>Waters coming from the Sea,</hi> it is a Derivation from <hi>this Prayer.</hi> Nor can any <hi>pray</hi> according to this <hi>Word,</hi> but they muſt <hi>pray</hi> into this <hi>Prayer;</hi> All <hi>returns again,</hi> All ſinks into it, Falls within its Compaſs and Comprehenſion, whether the Words are us'd or not; and yet this <hi>Prayer</hi> will never be <hi>full;</hi> it will never be pray'd enough, till this <hi>Kingdom comes;</hi> Nor can it ever be exhauſted, nor the full Senſe of it drawn out, till that <hi>Kingdom come,</hi> although <hi>All Saints pray</hi> out of it, as into it. Now therefore by way of Recollection, I conclude, this <hi>Prayer,</hi> as given in the <hi>Evangeliſt Matthew,</hi> is eſpecially given with regard to the whole Doctrine of Chriſtianity; and ſo to be us'd in a Free Expatiation, according to the whole <hi>Goſpel.</hi> But then I affirm the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> is one of the greateſt Points of the Goſpel; and that other contrary Preſcriptions of <hi>Prayer,</hi> and with Repetitions and Interruptions eſpecially, are forbidden, as, not <hi>after that manner,</hi> and great Tranſgreſſions againſt the <hi>Simplicity, that is in Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus far I have remark'd upon this <hi>Prayer,</hi> as given in the <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt Matthew;</hi> I am now to conſider it, as it is given the Second Time by Chriſt. Recorded by the <hi>Evangeliſt Luke:</hi> For that it was ſo given a Second Time, will appear: And it is the more deeply to be apprehended, and weigh'd, becauſe it was given the Second Time upon the ſolemn D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſire of the <hi>Diſciples</hi> to be <hi>Taught to pray,</hi> as <hi>John Taught his Diſciples.</hi> Now Chriſt <hi>Teaching to pray,</hi> as <hi>John, the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner, Taught to pray,</hi> (who, though <hi>before Chriſt,</hi> yet <hi>was after him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>)</hi> muſt needs <hi>Teach to pray,</hi> as the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> as the <hi>Great Prieſt, Prophet,</hi> and <hi>King,</hi> who was to <hi>come into the World.</hi> The Diſciples were there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105089:8"/> undoubtedly moved by a <hi>Divine Inſtinct,</hi> to deſire to be <hi>Taught to pray</hi> by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as the <hi>Great Master,</hi> in the ſame <hi>manner</hi> that <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Fore-runner Taught his Diſciples.</hi> For the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> ſo <hi>Teaching to pray,</hi> cannot but be ſuppos'd to comprize in his <hi>Prayer</hi> the great <hi>Intereſts</hi> his <hi>Diſciples</hi> and <hi>Servants</hi> have in his <hi>Meſſiahſhip;</hi> which is much to be obſerv'd to guide us into the higheſt Senſes of it, and above what our Lord might be ſuppos'd to aim at, as in the general Doctrine of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity,</hi> and as in the <hi>Evangeliſt Matthew;</hi> though that alſo could not be but Tranſcendently High, as to Chriſtianity in general.</p>
            <p>But let us firſt obſerve the more Remote and Outward Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the giving of this <hi>Prayer</hi> in the <hi>Evangeliſt Luke.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="circumstance">
               <p n="1">1. As it was given upon the ſo ſolemn Deſire of the <hi>Diſciples</hi> to be <hi>Taught to pray;</hi> and <hi>our Lord</hi> giving the <hi>Prayer</hi> in theſe <hi>Words; When ye pray, ſay;</hi> it may ſeem to puſh home to the conſtant uſe of theſe Words when we pray. But in Anſwer to it, there are theſe Three Things to be obſerved, which are plain <hi>Matters of Fact.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. That this Prayer is moſt compleat in <hi>Matthew,</hi> where it is firſt given; and it is to be compleated in <hi>Luke,</hi> by being compar'd with it ſelf, as given in <hi>Matthew.</hi> For the <hi>Doxological</hi> Concluſion, or Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> the <hi>Power,</hi> and the <hi>Glory for euer and ever,</hi> with the <hi>Amen,</hi> the Seal of all, is to be found only in <hi>Matthew;</hi> both which the <hi>Jews</hi> generally us'd in their <hi>Prayers,</hi> even as <hi>Chriſtians</hi> do. If then the whole and intire Pattern muſt be deriv'd from <hi>Matthew,</hi> even ſo muſt the Juſt Elevation of the Command for the uſing it, be taken from thence alſo, where it is moſt compleat. Now there the Command for the uſing it is expreſly given thus; <hi>After this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner pray;</hi> ſhewing it to be a <hi>Pattern,</hi> which muſt be <hi>meaſur'd</hi> by all <hi>Scripture;</hi> ſo few Words being elſe inſufficient (as hath been made out) to direct us to <hi>pray</hi> after that <hi>manner.</hi> So thoſe Words in <hi>Luke, When ye pray, ſay,</hi> muſt be expounded by thoſe in <hi>Matthew, When ye pray, ſay after this manner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It is certain by the Courſe of the <hi>Goſpel-Hiſtory,</hi> That the <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> as given in <hi>Luke,</hi> was another diſtinct Giving of it, from that in <hi>Matthew,</hi> and was the laſt Giving it; and ſome conſiderable Time after the <hi>Sermon in the Mount;</hi> from whence it is evident, That where the Form is moſt compleat, and had been before given; the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did not yet underſtand themſelves oblig'd to the <hi>Repetition</hi> of the <hi>Words,</hi> or ſtrictly determin'd to the <hi>Form;</hi> For if they had continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally us'd it, as a <hi>Form,</hi> they could not have been forgetful, That Chriſt had already <hi>Taught them to pray;</hi> or they muſt have charg'd his <hi>Form of Prayer</hi> directly with Inſufficiency; even there where it is moſt a <hi>Form;</hi> and in that <hi>Sermon,</hi> where they were the moſt Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, or proper <hi>Auditors;</hi> For he <hi>laoked on his Diſciples</hi> when he begun
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105089:8"/> his <hi>Sermon;</hi> which much aſſures, had it been ſuch a <hi>Form,</hi> they could not have forgotten it, as ſo preſcrib'd. Our <hi>Lord</hi> therefore, to ſhew he had enfolded all the Intereſts of his <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and of his <hi>Kingdom</hi> in the <hi>Prayer</hi> he had before <hi>Taught;</hi> returns them upon the ſame <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> by giving it them a-new, in ſo great Parts of it; that they could not but thereby remember it, and make up whatever was wanting in the laſt giving of it, by his firſt giving it; and therefore they, and All Chriſtians after them, are to ſearch further, and deeper into it; And that is one Great Senſe of, <hi>when ye pray, ſay;</hi> or, as the Word alſo ſignifies, <hi>Read;</hi> that is, Enlarge with Underſtanding upon the Heads of <hi>Prayer</hi> I have given you before. There All <hi>Prayer</hi> is to be found; there is to be found what I, as the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> am peculiarly to <hi>Teach my Diſciples;</hi> beyond what <hi>John,</hi> the <hi>preparer of my way before me,</hi> was to <hi>Teach his Diſciples; Read</hi> therefore with <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> that <hi>manner of Prayer</hi> I have already <hi>Taught you.</hi> You ask to be <hi>Taught, Read what I have Taught you; Read,</hi> and <hi>underſtand</hi> what you <hi>Read:</hi> Thus <hi>Reading the words of the Book of the Prophecy</hi> of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> is <hi>Reading with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> and <hi>Expoſition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. It is moſt evident, our <hi>Saviour</hi> was not Rigid about the <hi>Form</hi> of <hi>VVords;</hi> for he changes the Words in Two <hi>Petitions,</hi> yet not alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Senſe, <hi>viz.</hi> in that <hi>Petition; Give us our Daily Bread.</hi> In <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> it is <hi>This Day;</hi> or, as he ſaid, <hi>To Day;</hi> In <hi>Luke,</hi> that which is <hi>for,</hi> or <hi>according to the Day;</hi> ſo in that <hi>Petition; Forgive us our Debts,</hi> in <hi>Matthew;</hi> our <hi>Sins,</hi> in <hi>Luke;</hi> In <hi>Matthew, As we forgive our Debtors;</hi> in <hi>Luke, For we forgive every one indebted to us.</hi> And in the ſame <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſt Luke, Our Lord,</hi> at that <hi>Petition, Deliver us from Evil,</hi> breaks off without the <hi>Praiſe-Aſcribing Concluſion,</hi> which we find in <hi>Matthew;</hi> or the <hi>Amen,</hi> the fore-named <hi>Seal</hi> of All.</p>
               <p>Now from All theſe Things, which are plain Matters of Fact laid together, it is moſt evident; the Senſe of thoſe Words, <hi>when ye pray, ſay,</hi> does not oblige us to the Words, but to the whole Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of their <hi>Evangelick Senſe</hi> and <hi>Importance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Give leave to add here, as in the moſt ſeaſonable Place with Relation to this Prayer; as it is found both in the <hi>Evangaliſt Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> and <hi>Luke;</hi> That neither in Them nor in the whole <hi>New Teſtament</hi> is this <hi>Prayer</hi> any where ſtyled the <hi>Lords Prayer;</hi> as the <hi>Breaking of Bread</hi> is ſtyled the <hi>Lords Supper;</hi> and the <hi>Firſt Day</hi> the <hi>Lords Day,</hi> nor yet any way Referred to, as ſuch. To ſhew, the<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Form</hi> of Words is no Inſtituton of Chriſts, to be uſed in <hi>ſolemn Worſhip,</hi> as the <hi>Lords Day,</hi> and <hi>Lords Supper</hi> are; not to be divided one from another, Joyned ſo by that ſingular Word, not again uſed in the whole <hi>New Teſtament.</hi> 1 Cor. 11. 20. Rev. 1. 10. as, viz. <hi>Lordly,</hi> or <hi>Belonging to the Lord,</hi> that is, by Peculiarity or Speciallity.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105089:9"/> This is very much to be weighed, as ſhewing, the very Prayer, as in the Form, does not Tye us.</p>
               <div type="objection_and_answer">
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                     </label> To all, that I have ſaid upon the <hi>Prayer,</hi> as in the <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt Luke,</hi> it may be ojected: whether the Prayer Tye us to a Form or not, It ſeems wonderful, the Diſciples ſhould forget Chriſt had taught them to Pray before, as in <hi>Matthew,</hi> and that, even as the <hi>Great Prophet</hi> in that <hi>Sermon</hi> on the <hi>Mount.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> Undoubtedly this Inadvertency, and Forgetfulneſs, as in other Caſes, was permitted by God; that they might in this ſolemn manner deſire the <hi>Lord</hi> to <hi>Teach</hi> them more ſolemnly, as <hi>Meſſiah;</hi> as <hi>John</hi> the Fore-Runner of <hi>Meſſiah, Taught his Diſciples;</hi> and that Chriſt giving the ſame <hi>Prayer</hi> again, might ſhew, how cloſe His <hi>Meſſiahſhip</hi> and the whole <hi>Doctrine of Chriſtianity</hi> are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, and that all Run together unto His <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="circumstance">
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond Circumſtance of this <hi>Prayer,</hi> as it is given in the <hi>Evangeliſt Luke,</hi> is the Conſideration of the Diſcourſes relating to <hi>Prayer</hi> after the giving this <hi>Prayer,</hi> that our Lord looks unto; and they are theſe Two.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Earneſtneſs, and Importunity, that we ought to uſe in <hi>Prayer;</hi> and that muſt relate to this <hi>Prayer</hi> in all the Parts, or Branches of <hi>Pray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r,</hi> to which it directs us, and even Leads us by the Hand into; we ought to be ſo earneſt, as not to receive a Denial from God; And this Earneſtneſs He after, in this very <hi>Goſpel of Luke,</hi> particularly guides to, is unto his own <hi>Coming;</hi> when he will <hi>Avenge his own Elect;</hi> Aſſuring us, even while he does indeed <hi>Bear long,</hi> yet he will <hi>Avenge ſpeedily:</hi> And that herein he hath Reſpect to his own <hi>Coming,</hi> he plainly ſhews; For he adds, <hi>And yet when the Son of man cometh,</hi> ſhall he find Faith on the Earth? <hi>c.</hi> 18. 1, 7, 8.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The other Point of <hi>Prayer our Lord</hi> diſcourſes with Relation to this <hi>Prayer,</hi> is, That when his Servants are ſincere in their Deſires, God will give them the <hi>Beſt Things,</hi> though they may not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the <hi>Heighth and Depth,</hi> the <hi>Breadth and Length</hi> of the <hi>Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,</hi> and Senſes of the <hi>Word of God,</hi> with Relation to <hi>Prayer;</hi> and particularly as gather'd into this <hi>Prayer;</hi> For God will underſtand for his <hi>Children</hi> the <hi>Beſt Things,</hi> even as a moſt compaſſionate Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; if his Children ask things that are good in their kind, he does not give things different, nor Below, much leſs contrary; but better and Above. And this may thus relate to this <hi>Prayer;</hi> the whole Stream of it runs into the Channel of Trueſt <hi>good Things;</hi> They therefore, whom the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> moves to <hi>pray</hi> it, ſhall not be anſwered with any thing of a worſe or lower kind, but with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105089:9"/> the <hi>Spirit,</hi> the <hi>Supream,</hi> and <hi>All-Comprehending Good.</hi> And this He will give, and ſtill give, till it comes to the Height of His <hi>Kingdom,</hi> according to <hi>Eſay.</hi> 59. <hi>laſt;</hi> For ſo his <hi>Spirit makes Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion with groanings not to be uttered;</hi> And <hi>God underſtands His own Spirit,</hi> as is after, further to be Inſiſted upon; and he underſtands it, not only by our words, no nor by our more formed appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions, but by deep <hi>Search of our Hearts,</hi> and the moſt retired Operations of his <hi>Spirit</hi> within our <hi>Hearts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to this great purpoſe, our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſpeaks in thoſe words alſo in <hi>Matthew; Be ye not like the Heathen</hi> in <hi>much ſpeaking;</hi> For your <hi>Faiher knoweth, what things you have need of, before you ask Him;</hi> ſhewing; That Prayer is not to be manag'd, as if we would In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, or change God, but to affect our own Hearts; and to put them into an order for receiving from God by his Grace in Chriſt, Spiritual Underſtanding, Holy Affection, Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Dependence, Earneſt Deſire, and Zeal for his Glory, and Kingdom; and a State here preparatory for it. That way of <hi>Prayer,</hi> that either by meer often <hi>Repetition,</hi> by cuſtomarineſs, by not <hi>having the Spirit,</hi> and Power of the Word of God in it, is Unſerviceable to the Great Ends, is not after the manner of the <hi>Lord's Teaching to Pray,</hi> nor received into it: And what ever precribed way of <hi>Prayer</hi> it is, that more or leſs brings in a Rote of <hi>much Speaking</hi> only, and takes off from the Exerciſe of this <hi>Spiritual underſtanding,</hi> and Affection, hath ſutable degrees of that <hi>Great</hi> Guilt, of bringing <hi>Gentiliſm into the Temple of God,</hi> and <hi>taking away the daly Sacrifice of</hi> Prayer.</p>
               <div type="objection_and_answer">
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                     </label> But it may be ſtill ſaid, the Lords putting His <hi>Prayer</hi> ſo much into a <hi>Form,</hi> argues, He intended it ſhould be ſo uſed, elſe why did he put it into a <hi>Form?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> That He did not intend it as a Riged <hi>Form,</hi> I have ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly argued; yet He put it into a <hi>Form,</hi> eſpecialy in <hi>Matthew,</hi> that it might ſtand the more Conſpicuous, and Full in all parts, as a Pattern; and might ever in Relation to His King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom be in conſtant Uſe, as to the ſubſtantial Importance of it; and by an Admirable Foreſight of the way of uſing this Prayer by the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> World, condemns the Ignorance, the Unbelief, the Oppoſſition to the <hi>Dactrine</hi> of <hi>His Kingdom,</hi> even out of the <hi>own Mouths</hi> of the generallity of <hi>Christians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now I come having ſpoken this in preparation, to <hi>Teach you the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of this</hi> Prayer <hi>of the Kingdom,</hi> as <hi>David Taught the Children of Iſrael the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Bow</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">2 Sam. 1. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>; For Spirits of Saints Inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105089:10"/> and Armed with the <hi>Spioit</hi> of this <hi>Prayer,</hi> and the Divine Senſes of it, without any over Ceremoniouſneſs about the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition of the Words, are as the <hi>Charriots, and Horſemen of</hi> Iſrael; eſpecially, They, who are thus inſtructed in it, As it is the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And herein, I have ſaid, I propoſe this to you, to give you the <hi>Key</hi> of <hi>this Prayer,</hi> as it is the <hi>Prayer of the Glorious Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> and ſeeing I have declared, I do no way prejudice the Expoſitions Calculated for general uſe, tho I take the Elevation of this Prayer according to this <hi>Kingdom;</hi> let none thefore be angry at it, leaſt they fall under the Reproof of <hi>taking away the Key of this Prayer; They would not Enter in themſelves;</hi> and <hi>Thoſe,</hi> who <hi>are Entring in, they hinder,</hi> as our <hi>Lord,</hi> Cenſuring the great <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies</hi> and <hi>Maſters of the Jewiſh Law,</hi> ſpeaks concerning <hi>the Key of Knowledg, Luke</hi> 11. 52.</p>
                  <p>I will therefore firſt lay down ſeveral Arguments, that the true Elevation of this Prayer in its Expoſition muſt be, as it is the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom;</hi> and accordingly, I will Aime to give it, when I have firſt Eſtabliſhed this main Poſition by theſe Proofs of it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="arguments">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>1</label> The firſt Argument I draw from the expreſs and plain Words of the <hi>Prayer; Thy Will be done as in Heaven,</hi> and <hi>upon Earth.</hi> Now taking the Words according to the plain Sence of them, and as we generally underſtand them; it is evident, this <hi>Prayer</hi> Teaches us to riſe to the utmoſt of our deſires, that the <hi>Will of God may be done;</hi> And ſeeing there can be no higher Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of its being done, then the doing of it, <hi>as it is done in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> we therefore pray it may be <hi>done on Earth, as it is in Heauen;</hi> now the ſame Holineſs, Zeal and Spirituallity or Heavenly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign muſt move us to pray, that the <hi>Name</hi> of God ſhould be <hi>Sanctified</hi> to the ſame height, that we pray <hi>His Will ſhould be done</hi> unto; And that utmoſt is, that it may be <hi>on Earth,</hi> as it is in <hi>Heaven Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if we are <hi>Taught to pray,</hi> that the <hi>Will of God may be done on Earth as it is in Heaven,</hi> and by <hi>Analogy</hi> and proportion, that his <hi>Name</hi> may be <hi>Sanctified</hi> on <hi>Earth</hi> as it is in <hi>Heaven;</hi> our <hi>Lord</hi> hath by Admirable Wiſdom ſet the <hi>Kingdom of God</hi> between theſe Two <hi>Petitions,</hi> even the <hi>Petition</hi> that <hi>His Kingdom may come;</hi> between thoſe Two <hi>Petitions,</hi> that undeniably ought to be prayed to the height, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Name Sanstified, as in Heaven, ſo on Earth;</hi> and the <hi>Will done as in Heaven, and ſo on Earth;</hi> that what otherwiſe we might doubt of, whether <hi>His Kingdom</hi> ought to be <hi>prayed</hi> to <hi>come on Earth,</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:105089:10"/> as it is in <hi>Heaven,</hi> (Becauſe we are ready to think that its only to be in <hi>Heaven)</hi> might be aſcertain'd to us: That we ought to <hi>pray</hi> for the <hi>Kingdom coming,</hi> even on <hi>Earth,</hi> as it is in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and that we ſhould not be able to wrench out, what is ſo Rivetted into the midſt. And the very <hi>Analogy</hi> and <hi>Proportion</hi> of Heavenly Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Glory of God equally looks to all, if there be a poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, They may All be; now to ſhew that They may All be, even the <hi>Kingdom coming on Earth, as in Heaven;</hi> as well as the <hi>Name Sanctified on Earth, as in Heaven;</hi> and the <hi>Will done on Earth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as in Heaven</hi> of which we make no doubt, we ought ſo to <hi>pray;</hi> the <hi>Prayer</hi> hath ſo placed that the moſt to be doubted of in the middle, that we may <hi>pray</hi> for all together and alike.</p>
               <p>Again, there is ſuch a concatenation of the things, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be divided; For the <hi>Will of God</hi> is, that <hi>His Name</hi> ſhould be <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſally Sanctified,</hi> as innumerable Scriptures teſtify: If then <hi>His Will be done on Earth,</hi> as <hi>in Heaven; His Name muſt be Sactified on Earth, as it is in Heaven;</hi> ſeeing that it is ſo Supream a manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of His <hi>Will,</hi> that His <hi>Will</hi> cannot <hi>be done,</hi> if that be not <hi>done;</hi> and if <hi>His Will be ſo done on Earth, as in Heaven, His Kingdom</hi> muſt ſo <hi>come:</hi> For what is a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> but that he who hath the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> ſhould have <hi>His Name</hi> Higheſt, moſt Celebrated, Honoured and Ador'd; which is the <hi>Sanctifing the Name of God;</hi> when it is ſet at Infinite heights, and diſtances above <hi>all other Names,</hi> and this in Chriſt who hath a <hi>Name</hi> above <hi>all other Names;</hi> to the <hi>glory of God the Father;</hi> and that he ſhould have <hi>His Will</hi> obeyed; when ever therefore the <hi>Will of God is obeyed the Name of God is ſo Sanctified on Earth as it is in Heaven; His Kingdom muſt needs come on Earth, as it is in Heaven;</hi> and ſo <hi>His Kingdom will come,</hi> when ever that is; thus when one is, the other is alſo; when one is not, the other cannot be; the things are perfectly convertible, and turn on the ſame Poles; when one is, all are together with it; and if ſo much, as one be not, It is certain, neither of the other can be.</p>
               <p>But that we may know both the Time, when each of the other may be, and ſhall be; and that we may alſo know the Grand Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, or mighty Inſtrument, when each of the other ſhall be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected: The <hi>Kingdom coming</hi> is <hi>ſet</hi> in the midſt of each; when the <hi>Kingdom comes,</hi> the other Two ſhall be; For that <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly effect and bring the other Two to paſs: <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Name ſhall be ſo ſanctified,</hi> and the <hi>VVill ſo done.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But theſe things are impoſſible to come to paſs, according to the Experience of ſo many Thouſand Years, that the World hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready; had or to be hoped for, or expected, without <hi>Bowing the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, Rending the Heavens;</hi> the <hi>Heavens coming down,</hi> as it were to the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105089:11"/> Earth, in ſuch Glorious Manifeſtations, as the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> is deſcrib'd to appear in.</p>
               <p>And if theſe ſo Fundamental Points of Glory and Happineſs in that <hi>Kingdom</hi> be eſtabliſhed, how great will be the Conſequences? There ſhall certainly be the conſtant <hi>Table of the Kingdom</hi> in the <hi>Bread of Life,</hi> and the moſt abundant Sufficiency of All Things; the State of <hi>Reconciliation</hi> betwixt God and Man, betwixt Man and Man, betwixt Man and the <hi>whole Creation,</hi> betwixt the lower <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> and themſelves, and throughout the whole Frame of the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of God; <hi>All things in Heaven and Earth</hi> being <hi>Reconciled in him, even in him;</hi> and then moſt certainly there will be no more <hi>Leading into Temptation,</hi> but a perfect <hi>Deliverance from Evil:</hi> For the Cauſe of all the Indigencies of that Life, that is to be ſupported by that <hi>Epiou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſious,</hi> or <hi>Superſubſtantial Bread,</hi> according to the <hi>Day;</hi> of all the <hi>Anger of God,</hi> and the Mutual Enmities in the World; and of the Curſe upon the Creation, is, That <hi>the Will of God is not done on Earth as it is in Heaven,</hi> and <hi>his Name ſanctified;</hi> and becauſe the preſent State is not the State of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> But then ſhall it be Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd with <hi>Hallelujahs,</hi> That the <hi>Kingdom, and the Power, and the Glory is his</hi> throughout <hi>Eternity of Ages;</hi> Seal'd with an Unchangable and everlaſting <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now I would appeal to any one, whether our <hi>Lord Teaching his Diſciples</hi> then, and ſucceſſively in All Ages, to <hi>pray,</hi> that the <hi>Will of God</hi> may be <hi>done on Earth,</hi> as <hi>it is in Heaven;</hi> and that All Things that muſt in Neceſſary Conſequence fall out together, ſhould come to paſs alſo, whenever <hi>his Will</hi> is ſo <hi>done;</hi> whether, I ſay, <hi>our Lord</hi> would <hi>Teach</hi> ſo to <hi>pray,</hi> if he had not known it was the <hi>Will of God</hi> Things ſhould be ſo; or if there were not a <hi>promiſe of God</hi> for ſuch a <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> wherein All theſe Things ſhould be ſo, as a Ground of <hi>Faith</hi> they ſhould be ſo; And becauſe God hath ſo <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd,</hi> and <hi>reſolv'd</hi> they ſhould be ſo; and that he will yet be <hi>enquir'd</hi> of by the <hi>Prayer</hi> of his Servants to <hi>do it for them:</hi> Therefore hath our Lord Jeſus Chriſt <hi>taught us</hi> ſo to <hi>enquire by Prayer</hi> in, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this Great <hi>Rule of Prayer</hi> he hath given.</p>
               <p>There are Three Things the Word of God hath made neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to our Receiving any Mercy, in the Nature and Order of a Mercy.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That we ſhould <hi>pray</hi> unto, and <hi>enquire</hi> of God for it.</item>
                  <item>2. That the Thing we <hi>pray</hi> for, ſhould be within the Decree, and Determination of God, it ſhould be; and ſo according to his <hi>Will.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:105089:11"/>
                  <item> 3. That it ſhould be <hi>ask'd in Faith,</hi> or upon a <hi>Promiſe,</hi> declaring to us that <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Determination</hi> of God.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Now in theſe Great Points Chriſt hath taken a certain Care:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That there ſhould be <hi>Prayer</hi> for thoſe things, by giving this <hi>Prayer</hi> for them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Seeing he gave this <hi>Prayer</hi> by an <hi>Infallible Spirit, knowing the Mind of God,</hi> it is certainly ſquared according to the <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of God.</hi> As therefore this <hi>Prayer</hi> is every way prepared for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heard, ſo Jeſus Chriſt moſt certainly ſends out his <hi>Spirit</hi> to all his Servanrs, to give Faith, and to move holy Deſire, according to this <hi>Prayer,</hi> that God may be <hi>cried to Day and Night,</hi> agreeably with it. And when his Saints may be ſhort, in either the Underſtanding it, or in the Faith, or Deſire, that it ſhould be <hi>Pray'd</hi> with; the <hi>Spirit makes Interceſſion</hi> according to the <hi>will of God,</hi> with <hi>Groans that cannot be <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ttered;</hi> wherein God underſtands the <hi>Mind</hi> of his <hi>Spirit,</hi> becauſe it makes <hi>Interceſſion</hi> according to <hi>his will;</hi> ſo this <hi>Prayer</hi> muſt be a certain Prediction, that all theſe things ſhall be ſo; For God cannot Fail of his <hi>will,</hi> and <hi>promiſe;</hi> Chriſt cannot Fail of having <hi>Taught</hi> to <hi>Pray</hi> according to <hi>this will</hi> and <hi>promiſe</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> nor can Chriſt Fail to give his <hi>Spirit</hi> to his Servants to Excite them to <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Holy Deſire,</hi> according to this <hi>Prayer;</hi> From all which it unconteſtably Follows, That this <hi>Prayer</hi> muſt be a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Prediction, That the <hi>will of God ſhall be done on Earth, as it is in Heaven;</hi> and the whole Concatenation of Things be according to it; and therefore that the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> muſt <hi>come on Earth, as it is in Heaven;</hi> ſo that this <hi>Prayer</hi> muſt be a <hi>Prayer</hi> for the Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Appearance</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Kingdom,</hi> according to the higheſt Eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Senſe of the <hi>Prayer;</hi> and ſo the Prayer to be Expound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For what is more Viſible, than that this hath not yet been, nor is like to be in the Preſent State upon Earth; but even to Horror and Amazement, the contrary hath been ever ſince the general Profeſſion of Chriſtianity by Nations; and in all the Proſpect we can have of Things, Humanly ſpeaking, it will continue ſo; There muſt be therefore a peculiar State Created for the Anſwer of this Petition; and what can that be, but that <hi>New Earth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to promiſe,</hi> wherein <hi>Righteouſneſs ſhall Dwell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> even at, and in the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt.</hi> And ſo this <hi>Prayer muſt be the Prayer of the Kingdom, enquiring of God</hi> for the Accompliſhment of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</p>
               <p>I can therefore by no means allow the Abatement of the Force of this <hi>Petition;</hi> upon a compare of it with ſuch Expreſſions, <hi>be ye Holy, as I am Holy; be ye Perfect, as your Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her in Heaven is Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect;</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:105089:12"/> or by comparing it with the <hi>Apoſtle</hi>'s vehement Emotion, of <hi>forgetting things that are behind, and preſſing forward for the mark of the price of the High Calling of God in Jeſus Chriſt; if by any means he might attain the Reſurrection of the Dead,</hi> or the State of Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this Life; if we ſhould ſo Expound it.</p>
               <p>Now to Interpret theſe Expreſſions, either as gracious Deſires, though not Anſwer'd in this World, or as ſetting up to our ſelves the higheſt and moſt perfect Mark to Shoot at, though we cannot reach it in this World; or that ſuch Expreſſions of being, <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Perfect, as God is,</hi> ſhew that excellent Kind, and Alloy of Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, though we cannot riſe up to the Perfection of Degrees; and then to ſuppoſe this Senſe to be all the Senſe of this <hi>Petition,</hi> and that it cannot be fully and compleately Anſwer'd, till we come to Heaven, this Explication, I affirm, cannot agree.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe all theſe gracious, both Endeavours and Deſigns, have a Time and and a State of coming to their Complement, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, even to a Perfection of Degrees, ſo far as Created Nature is Capable of ſuch a Perfection; and therefore neither thoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands nor Deſires are in vain; though they do not obtain their deſired Effect in this State; Becauſe there is a State on purpoſe for that Perfection; But for the <hi>doing the will of God on Earth, as it is in Heaven,</hi> that can never come to its Perfection, except there be a State on ſome very <hi>Earth,</hi> where it may come into its Perfection; For there is ſo Direct and Perpendicular a Fixing the Petition up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome <hi>Earth;</hi> That it muſt come to its Perfection on ſuch <hi>Earth,</hi> or not at All: Seeing then there are ſuch Promiſes to the <hi>Earth, That Knowledg ſhall cover it, as the Waters do the Sea; That Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs ſhall dwell in it; That the Sinners ſhall be Conſumed out of it; That the Meek ſhall Inherit it,</hi> and then ſuch a <hi>Prayer Taught</hi> by Chriſt for the <hi>Doing the Will of God on Earth,</hi> and according to ſo great an Exemplar, as <hi>in Heaven.</hi> There muſt be a Perfection of it on <hi>Earth,</hi> or elſe this <hi>Petition</hi> cannot be Heard; For Perſonal Qualifications follow Perſons, and may be Perfected in their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, how ever they change their Place: But Local Priviledges adhere to the place; and except <hi>Earth</hi> it ſelf were carried up to <hi>Heaven,</hi> there cannot be a Perfecting of what is proper to the Holy State of <hi>Earth,</hi> but it muſt be on <hi>Earth;</hi> For elſe there muſt be a Confounding <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It is duly to be obſerv'd, and it is very plain, it is ſo; that <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> are Parallell'd as two places, one where the <hi>Will of God</hi> is done; and the other, where it is <hi>prayed, It may be done.</hi> The words are therefore moſt exactly Framed to expreſs a Parallel.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105089:12"/> It is therefore Prayed, That as the places ſtand in Parallel one to another, ſo that the State of the <hi>Will of God done in one,</hi> may be made Parallel by the <hi>doing the Will of God</hi> in the other; And as the <hi>doing the Will of God</hi> is the Glory of the one Place, ſo that it may be alſo <hi>the Glory of the other;</hi> and therefore, except that <hi>Glory</hi> Fill the <hi>Earth,</hi> according to ſo many <hi>Promiſes</hi> foremention'd, as it now Fills the Heaven, this <hi>Petition</hi> cannot be heard.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Kingdom comming</hi> is, as it were, the Key of the <hi>Sanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Name of God,</hi> and the <hi>doing the Will of God.</hi> Now the very words, <hi>Thy Kingdom come,</hi> do enough Explain; It is a State on Earth that is deſir'd, and ſhew both the Time and the High Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy, which will then be at work for the <hi>Sanctifying the Name of God,</hi> and for the <hi>doing the will of God,</hi> as in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>on Earth;</hi> as is further to be made out in the Explaining that <hi>Petition;</hi> And It does aſſure us, the Intention of the Petition is not, that there may be only ſuch a <hi>doing the Will of God,</hi> as was before <hi>Jeſus Chriſt came in the Fleſh,</hi> and ſince <hi>Chriſt came;</hi> univerſal among the Saints, <hi>viz.</hi> with that Sincerity, and in that doing it, that is of the ſame kind with that in <hi>Heaven;</hi> ſuch indeed there hath been; but alas, It hath been but in ſo very low degrees, as bear no Proportion; ſo that, except there be a new State of things, ſuch a <hi>doing the Will of God</hi> can never ariſe to any Perfection, ſeeing it hath not done it in 1600 years; and we can have no Reaſon, except ſuch a <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom Come,</hi> to expect it in 1600; or 16000 more, if <hi>Time</hi> could ſo long continue; All which makes it beyond all doubt, that this <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition</hi> can never be Fulfill'd, but by ſuch a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> as ſhall bring <hi>Heaven and Earth</hi> to ſuch a Parallel.</p>
               <p>And therefore, as ſhall be ſhewn in the Explaining the <hi>Petition it ſelf;</hi> The <hi>Prayer</hi> is moſt ſtrictly, and yet moſt Intentionally for an exact Paralelliſm, between the new Heaven, and the new Earth; as ſhall be in the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> and wherein <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> ſhall <hi>Dwell</hi> alike; It is therefore a <hi>Prayer,</hi> not only for the <hi>doing the will of God on Earth, but alſo in Heaven; viz</hi> In that <hi>New Heaven;</hi> and that ſuch an <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> may be in a Parallel one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, according to the <hi>Promiſe;</hi> ſo that the <hi>Prayer,</hi> if we ſpeak ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely of the matter, is not directly, that the will of <hi>God</hi> may be done in this <hi>Earth,</hi> as it is now done in the <hi>Third Heaven</hi> above us; where <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Holy Spirits</hi> of <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> are; But that there may be ſuch a Parallel <hi>New Heaven</hi> and <hi>New Earth;</hi> although it is moſt True, the preſent <hi>Sanctification</hi> of the <hi>Name Kingdom,</hi> and <hi>will of God</hi> done in the <hi>Higheſt Heavens,</hi> is the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Exemplar of all; And therefore the <hi>New Jeruſalem comes down from God out of Heaven,</hi> into that <hi>New Heaven</hi> of the <hi>Air,</hi> and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105089:13"/> ſo there is a parallel on <hi>the New Earth</hi> betwixt that <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and <hi>New Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this is of great concernment that we underſtand it aright, on theſe two Accounts.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Becauſe the preſent <hi>Heaven of the Air</hi> hath not the <hi>Will of God done in it</hi> now, any more, than in this <hi>Earth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Becauſe in full Senſe, <hi>The will of God ſhall not be done in the</hi> New Earth; <hi>as it is now in the higheſt Heaven,</hi> by way of Parallel.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. Becaoſe the preſent <hi>Heaven,</hi> or <hi>Air,</hi> is by Scripture made the Habitation and Reſidence of <hi>Spiritual Wickedneſſes;</hi> for they are <hi>Spiritual Wickedneſſes</hi> in <hi>Heavenlies;</hi> That muſt be <hi>in Heavenly places;</hi> for they are, nor can be in any other Senſe in <hi>Heavenlies;</hi> nor can they be in any other <hi>Heavenly place,</hi> but the <hi>Air;</hi> The <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> of the <hi>Divine preſence</hi> can be no Reſidence for <hi>Bad Spirits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sathan</hi> with his <hi>Armies</hi> and <hi>Hosts of Bad Spirits</hi> is call'd the <hi>Prince of the Power</hi> of the <hi>Air;</hi> that is, he hath, under Divine Permiſſion, a Reſidence in the <hi>Air,</hi> and when ever God hath uſe for his <hi>Satha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick Miniſtery,</hi> he hath undoubtedly great Command there: So there is now a Parallel betwixt the <hi>Will of God</hi> not done by thoſe <hi>Spiritual Wickedneſſes</hi> in the <hi>Air,</hi> or the <hi>Heavenlies,</hi> and the not <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Will of God</hi> by the <hi>Seed</hi> of the <hi>Wicked One</hi> on <hi>Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But when the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt ſhall Come,</hi> theſe <hi>Wicked Spirits</hi> ſhall be under an Obligation to Diſlodg from their <hi>Heavenlies;</hi> and whether there is not a Force upon them by the <hi>Fire of that Day,</hi> I will not Diſpute; But it is moſt certain, they are <hi>Lay'd hold of, Bound</hi> and <hi>Chain'd,</hi> and <hi>Lock'd up</hi> in the <hi>Bottomleſs Pit,</hi> and cannot come out to <hi>Deceive the Nations</hi> for thoſe 1000 years of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus it may be very well underſtood, there may be a Prayer for a Paralleliſm betwixt the <hi>New Heaven</hi> and the <hi>New Earth,</hi> in doing the <hi>Will of God;</hi> Taught us by Jeſus Chriſt; as in the <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and in the <hi>New Earth;</hi> to be effected, and <hi>brought to paſs by his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> And this is the moſt true and proper Senſe of this <hi>Petition,</hi> as in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>upon Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Will of God</hi> ſhall not be done at all in the <hi>New Earth</hi> as it is now in the <hi>Higheſt of Heaven</hi> by way of Parallel, for though it is True, the <hi>Will of God</hi> done now in the <hi>Higheſt Heaven</hi> by <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints,</hi> is the firſt <hi>Exemplar;</hi> yet it is not the Parallel to which it Anſwers; but the <hi>New Heaven</hi> is the Parallel; And the Reaſon is this, The <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints doing the Will of God,</hi> are out of <hi>Bodies,</hi> and in a ſtate of <hi>Spirits,</hi> and ſo cannot be an Agreeable Parallel;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105089:13"/> (Jeſus Chriſt is ſo Tranſcendent, He in his own Perſon can be <hi>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> parallel);</hi> But betwixt <hi>Holy Spirits,</hi> and <hi>Spirits</hi> in ſo mean and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a State, there are ſo great Odds, there can be <hi>no parallel;</hi> But betwixt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as the <hi>Head,</hi> and his <hi>Saints of the Firſt Reſurrection</hi> in <hi>Incorruptible Bodies,</hi> in <hi>the New Heaven,</hi> and the <hi>Saints,</hi> the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,</hi> the <hi>Remaining</hi> on the <hi>New Earth,</hi> in <hi>Changed Bodies,</hi> that ſhall <hi>not die;</hi> there ſhall be, though not a <hi>perfect Equality,</hi> yet ſo great a <hi>Likeneſs</hi> in the <hi>doing the Will of God;</hi> as in the <hi>New Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> by one, and in the <hi>New Earth</hi> by the other; as ſhall fill out the Paralelliſm to great Glory of <hi>doing the Will of God,</hi> as in <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>upon Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus, whether we take this <hi>Petition</hi> in the more General Senſe, and as it is Univerſally Expounded, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Will of God</hi> may be <hi>done on Earth,</hi> as it is now in the <hi>Higheſt Heaven:</hi> Or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we take it in the more True<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Near, Strict Senſe, wherein there is ſo great Evidence, our Lord defign'd it; it is very evident it is a <hi>Petition,</hi> that muſt be Anſwer'd in ſome State <hi>on Earth,</hi> and not in the <hi>Heaven of Eternity</hi> only, in Perfection; and here only in ſome Degrees, or Likeneſs of Kind, in Regard of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity.</p>
               <p>And further, it is moſt evident, upon a New Argument, there is a <hi>parallel</hi> betwixt the <hi>Heaven</hi> and the <hi>Earth</hi> in this <hi>Prayer.</hi> It is not ſaid therefore, <hi>on Earih</hi> as in <hi>Heaven,</hi> but as in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth.</hi> But ſuch a <hi>parallel</hi> cannot be in either the <hi>Bodies of Saints</hi> now on <hi>Earth,</hi> ſo unfit for the <hi>doing the Will of God;</hi> nor in an <hi>Earth</hi> ſo under the <hi>Curſe,</hi> as This is, that yields nothing but <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars and Thorns,</hi> except at leaſt upon the Expence of the <hi>Sweat of the Brows,</hi> and with the greateſt <hi>Vanity and Vexation of Spirit:</hi> There muſt be therefore the <hi>New Earth,</hi> that the <hi>Coming Kingdom of God by Jeſus Chriſt</hi> brings with it.</p>
               <p>Having now diſpatch'd this firſt and greateſt Argument, That <hi>this Prayer</hi> is indeed the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom;</hi> I come to a <hi>Second Argument.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>2</label> That into which All the <hi>Prophecies</hi> iſſue, as All the <hi>Promiſes</hi> determine themſelves (particularly that of the <hi>New Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> and the <hi>New Earth);</hi> and wherein the <hi>Myſtery of God is Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd,</hi> cannot be left out of that <hi>Prayer,</hi> which the Great <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, High Priest,</hi> and <hi>Apoſtle of our Profeſſion, Taught</hi> to his <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it were ſo, either the Things ſpoken of muſt be ſmall, or the <hi>Prayer</hi> muſt be ſmall: But neither of theſe can be ſuppos'd; Not the Firſt, becauſe they are the Reſult and Iſſue of all the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105089:14"/> wonderful <hi>Counſels</hi> and <hi>Works of God in the World.</hi> Not the latter, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the great Comprehenſive <hi>Prayer,</hi> the whole <hi>Element of Prayer.</hi> So that when we <hi>pray</hi> aright, and according to the <hi>Word of God,</hi> we do <hi>ſay</hi> (as the words may very well bear, whenever you do pray, you do ſay, not ſo much <hi>Imperatively</hi> as <hi>Indicatively),</hi> whenever the <hi>Spirit of Adoption</hi> crys in us <hi>Abba Father,</hi> we do preſently ſay, <hi>Our Father.</hi> When the <hi>Spirit of Prayer</hi> moves upon any of the Stores of <hi>Prayer</hi> in the <hi>Word of God,</hi> we immediately fall into this <hi>Prayer.</hi> If ever therefore Any of Thoſe ſo very Great, and Viſible, and Conſpicuous Things in the <hi>Word of God,</hi> that concern the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt,</hi> either in Relation to our ſelves, or the <hi>Church of Chriſt</hi> in general, come into our <hi>Prayers</hi> (and how can it be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, if we do indeed <hi>pray?)</hi> Then either we muſt <hi>pray</hi> out of, and beyond this <hi>Prayer,</hi> which muſt needs be impoſſible, if this be ſo <hi>Comprehenſive a Prayer</hi> as we All allow it to be; or elſe this <hi>Kingdom</hi> muſt be ſo conſpicuous in this <hi>Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Since then on one ſide, we Find the <hi>Word of God</hi> ſo full of the Great <hi>Expreſſions</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> that we muſt either <hi>pray</hi> for the Things therein declar'd by <hi>Prophecy</hi> and <hi>Promiſe,</hi> or we muſt leave ſuch <hi>Huge Tracts</hi> of the <hi>Word of God</hi> out of <hi>our Prayers;</hi> And ſeeing on the other ſide, in this <hi>Prayer,</hi> which we acknowledge ſo <hi>Comprehenſive</hi> a <hi>Prayer,</hi> we find the ſo Expreſs Words, <hi>Thy Kingdom come;</hi> and a paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel State of <hi>Doing the Will of God,</hi> as <hi>in Heaven,</hi> and <hi>upon Earth;</hi> beſides all the other ſo <hi>Correspondent Relations;</hi> how can we but be aſſur'd <hi>This Prayer</hi> is the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom</hi> in its higheſt Elevation? and that it can be no other; and that ſeeing it is ſo, it muſt prevail for the <hi>Coming of the Kingdom</hi> in its proper Time, ſeeing, as we have Fully Reaſon'd, it cannot but be heard.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argam. </seg>3</label> That which is ſo much the <hi>Will of God;</hi> that it ſhould be; that He hath infus'd a <hi>Natural Emotion</hi> into the very <hi>Creation,</hi> towards it; and that it, as with a Lifted-up Head of Expectation and Deſire, ſues for: That certainly is comprehended in this <hi>Prayer:</hi> For it cannot be once ſuppos'd, that Jeſus Chriſt <hi>Teaching his Servants</hi> and <hi>Saints to pray,</hi> ſhould not give them, in a Spiritual and Intellectual way, what is given to the <hi>Lower Creat;on,</hi> as by <hi>Inſtinct;</hi> becauſe it is ſo Neceſſary: Now that <hi>Reſtitution of All Things,</hi> That <hi>Glorious Manifeſtation of the Sons of God,</hi> That <hi>Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> of the <hi>Creatures</hi> from their <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwilling Subjection to Vanity,</hi> they now <hi>Groan and Travail under;</hi> yet under <hi>Hope</hi> of <hi>bringing forth</hi> a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tSate. All this the Creatures, with <hi>Earneſt Expectation wait for,</hi> with <hi>lifted-up Heads,</hi> They, as it were beg for. How then can it be, but that ſo Great a Point of the <hi>Divine Will,</hi> ſhould have ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fair Lines of it in this <hi>Prayer?</hi> And ſeeing our <hi>Lord</hi> directs us
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105089:14"/> in this <hi>Prayer,</hi> to look up to God as a <hi>Father;</hi> The <hi>Liberty,</hi> even the <hi>Glorious Liberty of his Sons,</hi> muſt needs be a principal part of it; And where can there be ſo Reaſonable a <hi>placing</hi> of it, as in that Great <hi>Petition, Thy Kingdom come:</hi> For where ſhould the <hi>Sons of God</hi> have a <hi>Liberty of Glory,</hi> but in his <hi>Kingdom.</hi> This is ſo undeniably certain and Evident, that I inſiſt no further upon it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>4</label> When the Apoſtle ſpeaks of this very <hi>Glorious Liberty</hi> of the <hi>Children of God,</hi> and the <hi>Manifeſtation of the Sons of God,</hi> by it, and in it; who <hi>cry</hi> unto him, <hi>Abba Father;</hi> He does Affirm, we have the <hi>Firſt Fruits of the Spirit,</hi> and <hi>groan within our ſelves; waiting for the Adoption;</hi> that is, the <hi>Manifeſtation</hi> of the <hi>Sons of God;</hi> and That is, <hi>the Redemption of our Bodies.</hi> He further manifeſts, This cannot be a <hi>Preſent State:</hi> 1. Becauſe the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> had <hi>only the Firſt Fruits</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> compar'd with that <hi>Great Harveſt</hi> of the <hi>pouring out of the Spirit</hi> that ſhall be at that Time; and withal, the <hi>Vouchſafement of the Spirit to all Chriſtians in general</hi> now, is a <hi>Firſt Fruits,</hi> an <hi>Anointing,</hi> a <hi>Seale,</hi> and an <hi>Earneſt</hi> to All that <hi>Glory.</hi> 2. He ſhews, It is a <hi>Future State;</hi> becauſe it is <hi>in Hope;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot be <hi>in preſent:</hi> For then <hi>Hope</hi> and <hi>Sight</hi> would be <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded.</hi> Then he goes forward, and Affirms; Seeing this <hi>Hope</hi> cannot but be Full of <hi>Deſires,</hi> and thoſe <hi>Deſires</hi> will be <hi>breaking out into Prayers.</hi> That therefore the <hi>Spirit helps our Infirmities,</hi> in that great Point wherein we <hi>know not what to pray for as we ought: But the Spirit makes Interceſſion, with Groanings, that cannot be uttered.</hi> And <hi>he that ſearcheth the Heart, knoweth the Mind of the Spirit. For he maketh Interceſſion fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Saints, according to the Will of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From all theſe Things Duely laid together, ariſe many Great Points to our purpoſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Glorious Liberty of the Sons of God,</hi> at the Time of their <hi>Manifeſtrtion,</hi> and the <hi>Reſtitution of the Creation,</hi> cannot but be a principal Point of <hi>Prayer:</hi> For, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>We groan within our ſelves, waiting for the Adoption,</hi> &amp;c. And ſo he falls into the Diſcourſe of <hi>Prayer</hi> for it, with <hi>Groans that cannot be uttered.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſo often referring to <hi>God,</hi> as a <hi>Father;</hi> by the <hi>Spirit of Adoption, crying, Abba Father;</hi> by the ſo often mention of the <hi>Sons of God;</hi> by the <hi>Adoption;</hi> leads us, even by a ſtretch'd-out Hand, to that <hi>Prayer,</hi> wherein the very firſt word is, <hi>Our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> If therefore we are led by the <hi>Conſideration</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> as a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> to the <hi>Prayer</hi> that Teaches us to ſay <hi>Our Father,</hi> we are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly led alſo to the Great Points of <hi>Adoption; viz.</hi> the <hi>Manifeſtation</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:105089:15"/> 
                  <hi>of,</hi> and the <hi>Glorious Liberty of the Sons of God;</hi> which muſt be prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Points of that <hi>Prayer;</hi> wherein we call God <hi>Father,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Adoption</hi> is proper to <hi>Sons,</hi> even as the <hi>Manifeſtation of,</hi> and the <hi>Glorious Liberty of the Sons of God</hi> is; and therefore they muſt be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timately Related, both of them, to <hi>God,</hi> as <hi>a Father;</hi> Becauſe <hi>Sons</hi> and <hi>Father</hi> are ſo ſtrictly and inſeparately <hi>Cor-related.</hi> The <hi>Kingdom of God then coming, as in Heaven,</hi> and <hi>on Earth,</hi> muſt be the Center, wherein All theſe Lines meet: For at that <hi>Kingdom</hi> is the <hi>Redemption of our Bodies;</hi> that is, the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> as All <hi>Scripture</hi> Agrees.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Apoſtle</hi> plainly ſignifies, <hi>We do know</hi> what we are to pray for; and yet we <hi>do not know what to pray far as we ought.</hi> That is, we <hi>do know,</hi> as to the Matter of <hi>Prayer;</hi> but we do not know in clear <hi>Apprehenſion:</hi> And that therefore the Great Tranſaction in this <hi>Prayer,</hi> is between the <hi>Spirit of God in our Hearts, making Interceſſion,</hi> with <hi>Groans not to be uttered,</hi> in what we do <hi>pray for,</hi> but know not to <hi>pray for as we ought,</hi> and God <hi>ſearching the Heart,</hi> and <hi>knowing the Mind of the Spirit,</hi> wherein our Apprehenſions are not Form'd and Explain'd, who yet hears us; becauſe that <hi>Interceſſion</hi> is <hi>according to the Will of God,</hi> and the <hi>Rule</hi> of this <hi>Prayer,</hi> although our <hi>Apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> are not Expreſs.</p>
               <p>Now what more exact State of the Caſe can there be, with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the Generality of Chriſtians <hi>praying this Prayer?</hi> They do by this <hi>Prayer know what to pray for;</hi> for they know to <hi>pray,</hi> that the <hi>Kingdom of God may come:</hi> But they <hi>know not</hi> the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the very Thing of that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> as <hi>they ought.</hi> They have not the True Explain'd Apprehenſions of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> according to the Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Nature of it. This we know is the General Caſe of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: The <hi>Spirit</hi> therefore here <hi>helps out;</hi> it gives unform'd Deſires, <hi>Groans not uttered;</hi> that leave a Savour, a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an inward Senſe of this. And God knowing that Senſe, the <hi>Spirit</hi> leaves im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed, to be according <hi>to his Will,</hi> and according to this <hi>Rule or Prayer by Chriſt;</hi> That it is for that <hi>Glorious Manifeſtation of the Sons of God,</hi> and the <hi>Reſtitution of all Things, Hears</hi> according to that Rule, and that Senſe, according to the Rule imprinted and left by the <hi>Spirit.</hi> And thus All <hi>Chriſtians pray,</hi> and are <hi>heard</hi> for this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> beyond Themſelves knowing it: For this <hi>Prayer</hi> giving them the words, <hi>Thy Kingdom come,</hi> The <hi>Spirit</hi> beyond Themſelves give the <hi>Groans;</hi> And God Graciouſſy gives the <hi>Ear</hi> to his <hi>Sons <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ords,</hi> and to the Senſe of his <hi>Spirit's Groans;</hi> becauſe they are Both according to his <hi>Will.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:105089:15"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>5</label> The <hi>Prayer,</hi> which <hi>Our Lord</hi> gave, as <hi>The Meſſiah,</hi> as <hi>The Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>The King of Iſrael,</hi> cannot but be a <hi>Prayer for his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom:</hi> For His <hi>Kingdom</hi> is ſo Great a <hi>Truth,</hi> that he ſaid, <hi>For this end was I born, and for this end came I into the World, to bear witneſs to the Truth, And every one that is of the Truth, Heareth his Voice</hi> in this Great Point: For this was the very Point Chriſt was upon, when he uſed theſe Words; even in Rejoynder to that Demand of <hi>Pilate? Art thou a King then?</hi> And this was the <hi>Good Confeſſion</hi> he <hi>witneſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Pontius Pilate,</hi> as by Compare of <hi>John</hi> 18. 37. and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 13. may be ſeen: And therefore upon the very mention of that <hi>Good Confeſſion of Chriſt,</hi> the Apoſtle goes on to the Fuller Diſcourſe of, and Diſplay of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now then, if the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> was ſo Principal a Point of the <hi>Witneſs of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> for which he <hi>came into the World;</hi> certainly when he Gave a <hi>Prayer to his Servants,</hi> as the Great <hi>Standard of Prayer;</hi> and that he makes peculiar mention of <hi>the coming of that Kingdom,</hi> which, as hath been every way ſhown, cannot be the <hi>Kingdom of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity,</hi> but a preparation to it; and that <hi>Kingdom</hi> into which it is <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered up.</hi> This <hi>Prayer</hi> muſt be the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> For Chriſt <hi>Taught it</hi> in his Great Capacity of <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> as <hi>John Taught</hi> it in his Capacity, as the <hi>Fore-runner of Meſſiah.</hi> It could not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be, but that in this <hi>Prayer</hi> Chriſt <hi>Lifted up a Banner,</hi> and an <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign,</hi> and a <hi>Standard</hi> to <hi>be displayed, becauſe of this Truth;</hi> to which All his Servants ſhould be gathered in their Deſires.</p>
               <p>I do not therefore at all wonder, that the Principal, or All the <hi>Petitions,</hi> might be collected, from the uſual <hi>Petitions</hi> among the <hi>Jews;</hi> and thus <hi>Canonized,</hi> and <hi>made Sacred</hi> by Chriſt; becauſe the <hi>Jews</hi> had the more <hi>particular promiſes of this Kingdom,</hi> the more particular Notices and Notions of it, as may eaſily appear by the whole Stream of the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> and many Evidences of their Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of it in the <hi>New;</hi> However, they had much debaſed, and ſtraitned thoſe Notions: <hi>Our Lord</hi> therefore to ſhew, <hi>He was that King of Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>His was that Kingdom they expected,</hi> Compoſed their looſe and ſcattered <hi>Petitions</hi> for it, into this <hi>Excellent Frame,</hi> and under ſo Divine a Sanction, as the <hi>Prayer he Taught:</hi> And it ſtands therefore as a Monument for Them, and for All the <hi>Gentile Churches,</hi> of his <hi>Kingdom;</hi> and to draw All thereby to himſelf, as their <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>That King,</hi> that is <hi>to come into the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>6</label> Jeſus Chriſt is the <hi>One Mediator,</hi> and <hi>Interceſſor</hi> between <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> preſenting, and making Acceptable to God the <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> of his <hi>Saints;</hi> and <hi>Giving much Incenſe with them.</hi> And This is his peculiar <hi>Prieſthood, after the Order of Melchizedeck:</hi> For as ſuch,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105089:16"/> ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle, He Lives for ever to make Interceſſion for All Thoſe, that come to God by him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now in this <hi>Prieſthood of Interceſſion,</hi> Two Things muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily meet; His <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and his <hi>Prayer:</hi> His <hi>Kingdom,</hi> becauſe his <hi>Melchizedekian Prieſthood</hi> hath an immediate Reference to his <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Righteouſneſs,</hi> and of <hi>Peace,</hi> that is, his <hi>Glorious Kingdom,</hi> wherein his <hi>own Glory,</hi> as the <hi>Head,</hi> the <hi>Glory</hi> of his <hi>Church,</hi> as the <hi>Body,</hi> lye together enfolded, and are to come to perfection. And in that Prieſthood, he is a Saviour to Perfection, or to the very <hi>End.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, That which is the principal Point of his <hi>Redemption,</hi> is the principal Point of his <hi>Interceſſion.</hi> Now to make us <hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>Prieſts to God,</hi> and <hi>to his Father<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> that we may <hi>Reign on,</hi> and <hi>over the Earth,</hi> is the principal Point of his <hi>Redemption,</hi> and ſo Celebrated in the New Song, <hi>Revel.</hi> 5. and therefore of his <hi>Interceſſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, That which is the <hi>High Expectation</hi> of Chriſt, at the <hi>Right Hand of God,</hi> muſt needs fall in with his <hi>Interceſſion</hi> on the <hi>Right Hand of God.</hi> Now He is <hi>ſet down on the Right Hand of God, expecting</hi> that his <hi>Enemies</hi> ſhould be <hi>made his Footſtool;</hi> and that is in his <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> as it appears at his <hi>Comming,</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> teaches us, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 21. Therefore he intercedes for it; For his <hi>Expectation</hi> is grounded on his <hi>Interceſſion and Redemption.</hi> Heb. 10. 13. 2 Tim. 4. 1.</p>
               <p>And as his <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Interceſſion</hi> thus meet, ſo muſt his <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion</hi> meet alſo with, and be <hi>undivided</hi> from the <hi>Prayer</hi> he Taught. For no poſſible ſuppoſal can there be, that Chriſt ſhould <hi>Intercede</hi> upon the <hi>Prayers of his Saints,</hi> but that their <hi>Prayers</hi> muſt be comprehended in that Pattern and Rule of <hi>Prayer</hi> he gave: For he would not Give a <hi>Prayer</hi> he would not <hi>Intercede upon,</hi> and that that ſhould not be the Square and Summary of all the <hi>Prayers</hi> he would <hi>Intercede upon.</hi> It muſt needs therefore be, that the <hi>Kingdom coming</hi> the <hi>Prayer</hi> inſiſts upon, muſt needs be the <hi>Melchizedeckian Kingdom;</hi> the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> when his <hi>Redeemed,</hi> as <hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>Prieſts Reign</hi> upon, and <hi>over the Earth;</hi> and when his <hi>Enemies</hi> are made his <hi>Footſtool.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That <hi>Prayer</hi> therefore, <hi>John</hi> 17. which is the Pattern of Chriſt's <hi>Interceſſory Prayer,</hi> and which none <hi>can pray</hi> but himſelf, in the whole Frame of it; and was not therefore <hi>Taught</hi> by him to his <hi>Church</hi> to the End, They ſhould ſo <hi>pray</hi> it as he did. That <hi>Prayer</hi> is for this <hi>Kingdom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> in which <hi>Kingdom, God in Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt in his Saints,</hi> ſhall be ſo viſibly <hi>made perfect in One;</hi> that the <hi>World,</hi> which will not <hi>now Believe,</hi> ſhall, againſt their Wills, <hi>Know and Believe,</hi> and <hi>Believe and Know;</hi> as the <hi>Devils know,</hi> and <hi>Believe,</hi> and <hi>Tremble;</hi> that God ſent <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>hath loved his Saints as he loved him,</hi> Ver. 21. 23. This cannot be in this World, where this Glory is ſcorned
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105089:16"/> and defied, and neither <hi>Believ'd nor Known.</hi> It cannot be after the <hi>Enemies</hi> of Chriſt are <hi>put quite down under his Feet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> into the Lake,</hi> and he <hi>Renders</hi> up the <hi>Kingdom</hi> into <hi>an immediate Enjoyment of God All in All;</hi> For then this Illuſtrious Appearance is ended, both as to his own, and his Saints ſo Viſible Glory in Humane Nature; and alſo the Diſhonour of his Enemies: And Nothing Remains, but the <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding God All in All;</hi> or the <hi>Eternal Miſery of Separation from his Favour,</hi> or wailing under his <hi>Diſpleaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>7</label> If each part of this <hi>Prayer, viz.</hi> The Addreſs to God, as <hi>Our Father;</hi> each <hi>Petition,</hi> and the <hi>Doxology</hi> or <hi>Concluſion,</hi> Aſcribing to God. That <hi>Thine is the Kingdom,</hi> &amp;c. may with Admirable A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, both in Expreſſion and Senſe, be concerted with Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <hi>Scriptures</hi> Relating to the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and <hi>Glory of Chriſt,</hi> and of his <hi>Saints,</hi> as in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>on Earth;</hi> Then with how much Right may This <hi>Prayer</hi> be call'd, and Expounded into the <hi>Prayer</hi> of <hi>the Kingdom!</hi> This Concert therefore of this <hi>Prayer,</hi> and thoſe <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> I will endeavour to make in the following <hi>Expoſition.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection_and_answers">
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> But againſt all this Diſcourſe, this mighty Objection may be Levyed; How can this <hi>Prayer</hi> be look'd upon as the <hi>Prayer</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> or ſo Great a Standard of <hi>Prayer,</hi> or Comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſory of it; that hath not the leaſt mention of the Great <hi>Prince Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ah,</hi> or of his <hi>Redemption,</hi> which is both the Fundamental Point of <hi>Prayer,</hi> and of <hi>the Kingdom?</hi> How can this poſſibly be Reconcil'd with All that hath been ſaid of this <hi>Prayer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are Two Great Anſwers to be given to this, and ſuch as will excedingly Eſtabliſh it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> There can be no more certain, and Demonſtrative Argument, That <hi>This Prayer</hi> was never intended by Chriſt, as a <hi>Form,</hi> or that we ſhould place a Devotion in the Repetition of it; For then could it have wanted the <hi>Name of Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Mediation of Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Redemption</hi> of Chriſt, or the Expreſs Mention of <hi>the Spirit,</hi> which is that Supream Good Thing; being <hi>One</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>with Chriſt,</hi> which <hi>proceeds</hi> from the <hi>Father,</hi> and <hi>Takes of Chriſts,</hi> and <hi>Gives it to us;</hi> which we ſhould, according to our <hi>Lord's</hi> Doctrine of <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> in ſo near Neighbourhood to this <hi>Prayer,</hi> be ſo moſt earneſtly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate for?</p>
               <p>But now if <hi>This Prayer</hi> be ſuch a <hi>Standard of Prayer,</hi> as is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood and apprehended in the whole Latitude of the <hi>Word of God;</hi> All leads to Chriſt, and to the <hi>Eternal Spirit,</hi> to the <hi>Redemption, Blood,</hi> and <hi>Mediation of Christ,</hi> as the Foundation of All.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:105089:17"/>
               <p> And it was an End worthy of ſuch an Omiſſion of the Expreſs <hi>Name of Chriſt,</hi> and of <hi>the Spirit,</hi> to keep us from Reſting in this <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> as a <hi>Form,</hi> and to caſt us upon the whole <hi>Word of God,</hi> that we might <hi>pray after that manner,</hi> and that we might <hi>Read,</hi> or <hi>Expound</hi> that <hi>Prayer</hi> by it, whenever we <hi>pray.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>2</label> This <hi>Prayer</hi> is Full of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> No Word of it, but is Full of it, and cannot be <hi>underſtood,</hi> but with the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the <hi>Kingdom.</hi> Now the <hi>Kingdom</hi> being the <hi>Kingdom of Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah,</hi> of the <hi>Redeemer,</hi> and the <hi>Petitions</hi> being ſo adjuſted to that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Kingd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m of Meſſiah,</hi> and of his <hi>Redemption;</hi> The <hi>Petitions</hi> cannot be underſtood but with the <hi>Knowledge of Chriſt,</hi> and of <hi>his Name,</hi> and of his <hi>Redemption.</hi> So that though there be no Expreſs Mention of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> nor of his <hi>Redemption,</hi> yet by ſearching the Senſe and Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of each <hi>Petition,</hi> according to the <hi>Word of God,</hi> we muſt needs find it all there.</p>
               <p>And ſo proportionably, it may be ſaid, with Relation to the <hi>Spirit of God.</hi> The <hi>Kingdom</hi> is a <hi>Kingdom of the Spirit poured out,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Eſay</hi> 59. Laſt. Every <hi>Petition</hi> therefore muſt needs be full of the <hi>Spirit, of the Promiſe</hi> of that <hi>poured out;</hi> even as it is Full of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> when it is ſearch'd and underſtood, according to the whole <hi>Word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>3</label> The <hi>Prayers</hi> that we find in the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> after this <hi>Prayer</hi> given, cannot but be Expreſſive of this <hi>Prayer,</hi> and drawn out of it; elſe Chriſt did not <hi>Teach to pray</hi> in <hi>This Prayer;</hi> For to <hi>Teach</hi> his <hi>Diſciples to pray,</hi> and they not to <hi>pray</hi> according to it, muſt be either an Inſufficiency in the Manner of <hi>Chriſt's Teaching to pray,</hi> or elſe a Great Diſobedience, or at leaſt Neglect, for his Servants not to <hi>pray</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that <hi>Prayer.</hi> Now it is moſt evident, The <hi>Prayer of Chriſt,</hi> in his <hi>Mediation,</hi> John 17. although it be indeed Tranſcendent to our <hi>praying,</hi> as to thoſe things proper only, and peculiar to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his <hi>Mediatorſhip</hi> in it; Yet it is inſtructive to us, how to <hi>draw near to God in Christ,</hi> and to form our Approaches through him; And All the <hi>Prayers</hi> we find in the <hi>Apostles,</hi> muſt have the Lines, and <hi>Spirit of this Prayer</hi> in Them; elſe Chriſt <hi>Taught</hi> not to <hi>pray,</hi> when he <hi>Taught to pray;</hi> or he <hi>Taught to pray</hi> to no purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Now All Thoſe <hi>Prayers</hi> being <hi>Full</hi> of Chriſt, and <hi>Full</hi> of the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> we hereby know certainly, This <hi>Prayer</hi> muſt needs be ſo alſo in the Bottom of it, and therefore muſt be Explicated according to All thoſe <hi>Prayers;</hi> and we are ſent by it to Them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection_and_answers">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:105089:17"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> To all that hath been ſaid of this <hi>Prayer,</hi> That it is the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom,</hi> and that there is in it a <hi>paralelliſm</hi> between the <hi>New Heaven and the New Earth,</hi> in <hi>doing the Will of God;</hi> There may be this Objection made, A <hi>Kingdom of God and of Chriſt</hi> is eminently directed to in this <hi>Prayer,</hi> and alſo <hi>a parallel State betwixt Heaven and Earth:</hi> But All This is to be underſtood of the <hi>Kingdom of Eternity,</hi> which <hi>Kingdom of Eternity</hi> ſhall have <hi>a New Heaven and a New Earth.</hi> And it is a <hi>Kingdom</hi> that ſhall never <hi>end,</hi> and it is called <hi>Eternal Life:</hi> This therefore lifts up a <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> much above that of a <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And whereas the <hi>Son</hi> is ſaid <hi>to deliver up a Kingdom,</hi> it is only to be underſtood of that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> wherein he is in a State of continual <hi>Acquiſition,</hi> wherein he is <hi>Riding out Conquering and to Conquer,</hi> and <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing Enemies;</hi> That is the <hi>Kingdom</hi> He indeed ſhall <hi>deliver up to God,</hi> and Receives at the ſame Time the <hi>Kingdom of Fruition and Enjoyment,</hi> which endures indeed <hi>for ever and ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> muſt therefore be caſt back into ſome ſpace moſt fit for them within that <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> that is in a <hi>State of Acquiſition.</hi> And what fitter Time is there, than when the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Empire</hi> began in <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> until that great Ravage the <hi>Turks,</hi> as a <hi>Gog Magog,</hi> made in the World. In Anſwer hereunto,</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> I cannot underſtand how the <hi>Apoſtle</hi>'s expreſs Words of the <hi>Son's delivering up of the Kingdom to God, even the Father,</hi> can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded <hi>of changing a Kingdom of Acquiſition for a Kingdom of Fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> much leſs, how the <hi>Son's</hi> being <hi>Himſelf ſubject,</hi> can be interpreted into ſuch <hi>a Kingdom of Fruition.</hi> It is very plain, the <hi>Son,</hi> who <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers up,</hi> and who is <hi>ſubject,</hi> muſt be the <hi>Son of Man,</hi> who <hi>Receiv'd the Kingdom from the Hand of the Ancient of Days;</hi> For the <hi>Eternal Word</hi> can neither <hi>Receive a Kingdom,</hi> nor <hi>Deliver it up;</hi> Nor would God be more <hi>All in All,</hi> ſo much as to <hi>Oeconomy,</hi> or <hi>Diſpenſation,</hi> for the <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Words Delivery up of a Kingdom to Him,</hi> who is <hi>One with Him.</hi> The <hi>Kingdom</hi> therefore the <hi>Eternal Word</hi> ever had, the <hi>Father</hi> ever had <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly</hi> with Him: If he ſhould <hi>deliver up a Kingdom to the Father,</hi> he would ſtill have it equally with the <hi>Father,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>He,</hi> as the <hi>Eternal Word,</hi> are <hi>One.</hi> There can be no <hi>Receiving,</hi> nor <hi>Delivering up of a Kingdom</hi> betwixt the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Eternal Word:</hi> There can be no ſo much as Repreſentation of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Father,</hi> more or leſs <hi>All in All,</hi> for any <hi>Kingdom,</hi> the <hi>Eternal Word</hi> hath, or <hi>Delivers up of a Kingdom:</hi> The <hi>Kingdom</hi> therefore <hi>delivered up,</hi> that God may be <hi>All in All,</hi> muſt be the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of the <hi>Son of Man,</hi> which as in <hi>Oeconomy,</hi> or <hi>Repreſentation,</hi> is made ſo ſupreme, though indeed to the <hi>Glory of God the Father;</hi> that the <hi>Glory of God</hi> ſeems not to ſtand
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105089:18"/> Alone in <hi>Glory,</hi> but is pleas'd to Allow Full Glory to, and not to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine the <hi>Kingdom of the Humane Nature of Chriſt,</hi> or of the <hi>Man Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>2</label> There is no poſſible Fitting Any Part of Time, that hath yet been, to the Deſcription Given of the <hi>Thouſand Years,</hi> by the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> Revel. 20. But it muſt needs be yet to come, for this Great and moſt Apparent Reaſon: There hath been no Time yet, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Sathan</hi> could be ſaid to be ſo <hi>Bound,</hi> as not to deceive the <hi>Nations</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more; What Time hath there yet been, in which, beſides all Unholy Practices, he hath not Deceiv'd with <hi>Paganiſm,</hi> with <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metaniſm,</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtianiſm?</hi> Theſe <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be proper and peculiar to a <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> yet to come; and that therefore muſt be to the <hi>Kingdom</hi> deſign'd by Chriſt in this <hi>Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>3</label> The parallel State of the <hi>Will of God</hi> done in the <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and in the <hi>New Earth,</hi> as in the <hi>Kingdom of Eternity,</hi> can have no place in this <hi>Prayer,</hi> becauſe it can indeed have no place at all in that <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal State.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="arguments">
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>1</label> Becauſe the Apoſtle ſtiles the <hi>Time of the Delivery up of the Kingdom,</hi> moſt Signally and Eminently, <hi>The End;</hi> And he diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhes it from that <hi>End</hi> when <hi>Chriſt ſhall come;</hi> with which alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curs the <hi>Reſurrection of His,</hi> his <hi>Reign,</hi> and ſo <hi>Kingdom,</hi> till <hi>Death,</hi> the <hi>Laſt Enemy ſhall be ſubdued;</hi> and then the <hi>Kingdom</hi> is <hi>Delivered up.</hi> See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then <hi>the End</hi> it ſelf is after the <hi>Coming of Chriſt,</hi> and after the <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,</hi> the <hi>End</hi> it ſelf muſt be an <hi>End</hi> to that Laſt State; For the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Riſing of his Saints,</hi> is an <hi>End</hi> to this World, and to the State of it; ſo it cannot be the End of this State, but of that After-State of the <hi>Reign</hi> of Chriſt, and whatever conſiſts with that: And that we ſhall find to be the State of the <hi>New Heaven</hi> and of the <hi>New Earth.</hi> For,</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>2</label> The <hi>New Heaven</hi> and <hi>New Earth,</hi> muſt needs be the <hi>World to come, whereof,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle, we ſpeak;</hi> which is put into <hi>ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to Chriſt;</hi> and it is put into <hi>ſubjection</hi> to Him at his <hi>coming,</hi> when He <hi>Reigns,</hi> and hath <hi>All Things put under Him.</hi> If then there ſo comes an <hi>End,</hi> when this <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſhall be <hi>deliver'd up,</hi> by the Great Ruler of it, <hi>Chriſt;</hi> what Reaſon is there to believe, that That <hi>World</hi> it ſelf is then to take <hi>End</hi> at and with that <hi>End?</hi> It is certain, it muſt have <hi>End,</hi> or be <hi>deliver'd up;</hi> For the <hi>Son</hi> ſhall be <hi>ſubject.</hi> It can be his <hi>World</hi> therefore no longer; his <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> no longer.</p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:105089:18"/>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Arg. </seg>3</label> If then the State of God's Kingdom, even the <hi>Father,</hi> ſhall be ſuch, that it will bear no ſuch <hi>Heaven</hi> nor <hi>Earth;</hi> then it is certain, They muſt have <hi>End</hi> when <hi>All</hi> is <hi>deliver'd up.</hi> But <hi>God</hi> being <hi>All in All,</hi> No <hi>New Heaven,</hi> nor <hi>New Earth</hi> can be born; for either They muſt Enjoy God, or be Enjoyed by God, and by his Saints. Their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are ſuch, that they cannot enjoy God, being not Creatures of Underſtanding or Will: To be therefore, and not to enjoy God, takes off from God being <hi>All in All:</hi> For then would there be Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of an Eternal Duration; even when <hi>God is All;</hi> and They in no Capacity to enjoy him. If it ſhould be ſaid, They do enjoy him in their way; I Anſwer, That is High enough for an <hi>Oeconomical State,</hi> but not for this of <hi>Eternity.</hi> If it be ſaid, That God may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy them, and his Saints may enjoy them, and praiſe him for them, and they Declare his Glory. I Anſwer, This alſo is Allowable to the <hi>Oeconomical,</hi> but not to the <hi>Eternal State;</hi> God is the only Enjoya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in that State to himſelf, and to his Saints; and He Enjoys his Saints only in the Communication of Himſelf to Them: No leſs than This can be underſtood by <hi>God</hi> being <hi>All in All;</hi> He muſt be <hi>The Alone to be Enjoyed;</hi> and He muſt be <hi>Enjoyed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>4</label> There is but One Place of Scripture that gives Account of Things after the <hi>Thouſand Years Kingdom</hi> of Chriſt, and that is, <hi>Revel.</hi> 20. It plainly gives Account of the State after that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> becauſe it gives an Account of Things after the <hi>Expiration of the Thouſand Years,</hi> when <hi>Sathan is Looſed.</hi> And the <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> are ſaid to be the <hi>Reign of Chriſt</hi> with his <hi>Saints.</hi> So it muſt be the <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Years Kingdrm of Chriſt.</hi> Now the utmoſt End of that State is a Great <hi>White Throne,</hi> and <hi>One ſate upon it,</hi> from whoſe <hi>Face Heaven and Earth</hi> fled away, and there was not <hi>Place Found for them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now from hence ſeveral Arguments Ariſe, Aſſuring us, There are no <hi>Heaven and Earth,</hi> except the <hi>Heaven of Divine Preſence,</hi> after the utmoſt <hi>End</hi> of All.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. There appears an <hi>Emblematical</hi> Introduction to the Utter Bla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and Annihilation of All Being, but God and his Saints, on one ſide, and the <hi>Lake of the Second Death,</hi> with its <hi>Dead,</hi> on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Becauſe the <hi>Lake</hi> receives All the <hi>Dead,</hi> with <hi>Death</hi> it ſelf, we are Aſſured, it is that very End, when the <hi>Kingdom</hi> is <hi>deliver'd up,</hi> and the <hi>Son becomes Subject,</hi> All being <hi>ſubdued to him;</hi> For here the <hi>Laſt Enemy, Death, is ſubdued;</hi> and then is the <hi>End.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:105089:19"/> 3. When this <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth Fled away,</hi> There was <hi>no Place Found For them;</hi> When any one dies, it is ſaid, <hi>Their place knows them no more;</hi> Their <hi>place</hi> remains, but it knows them no more; Another comes in their place; Or, as it is ſaid in <hi>Job, Out of their Earth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grows.</hi> So when the <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> that <hi>now are,</hi> are burnt up, another <hi>Heaven and Earth</hi> ſhall come in their room: But when this <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> Fly away, there is <hi>no place</hi> for them, not ſo much as <hi>place</hi> where they may be; and ſo not where any other may come.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The <hi>Heaven and Earth</hi> that now are, <hi>are Treaſur'd up for fire,</hi> and are to be for the <hi>perdition of ungodly men;</hi> and ſo in other Scriptures. But theſe fly from the ſole <hi>Preſence of Him</hi> that <hi>ſits on the white Throne.</hi> Theſe Two Deſcriptions are very differing.</p>
                  <p>But if All Theſe Things could be Accommodated, and it be ſaid, There are <hi>New Heavens,</hi> and a <hi>New Earth</hi> that ſucceed, <hi>c.</hi> 21. thoſe which <hi>fly away,</hi> c. 20. I further Argue:</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>4</label> The <hi>Heavens and Earth</hi> that <hi>fly away,</hi> c. 20. are no other, nor can be any other than the very <hi>New Heavens,</hi> and <hi>New Earth</hi> that <hi>John ſaw,</hi> c. 21. And though to draw a Veil on <hi>Prophecy,</hi> They are ſet, as it were, in a Succeſſion to the <hi>Heaven and Earth</hi> that <hi>Fled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way;</hi> yet there are ſeveral Great and Undeniable Arguments, That the <hi>Flying away</hi> of the <hi>Heaven and Earth</hi> ſpoken of, <hi>c.</hi> 31. muſt be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> State, and therefore muſt be of the <hi>New Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens</hi> and <hi>New Earth,</hi> that were created <hi>New,</hi> together with the <hi>New Jeruſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the <hi>New Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth John</hi> ſaw, are ſo cloſe Tied with the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> as not to be ſeparated: For after the mention of them it is immediately ſubjoyn'd, <hi>I John ſaw the New Jeruſalem,</hi> that made her ſelf Ready, as <hi>a Bride Adorned for her Husband,</hi> cap. 19. <hi>Come down,</hi> cap. 21. And again, after the ſeeing both the <hi>New Heavens</hi> and the <hi>New Jeruſalem;</hi> He <hi>that ſate on the Tbrone,</hi> ſaid, <hi>Behold, I create All New.</hi> So there is a Locking in the <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and the <hi>New Earth,</hi> even on purpoſe with the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> that they may not be Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided.</p>
                  <p>But the <hi>Flying away of Heaven and Earth from him that ſate on the white Throne,</hi> muſt needs be after the <hi>New Jeruſalem;</hi> For it is after the <hi>Holy City,</hi> and the <hi>Beloved City;</hi> which was no other than the <hi>Bride,</hi> the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> that was therefore <hi>Beloved,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Bride;</hi> and therefore <hi>Holy,</hi> becauſe <hi>Arrayed</hi> in <hi>Linen White and Clean,</hi> which is the <hi>Righteouſneſs of the Saints.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:105089:19"/>
                  <p> Now this <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> muſt be together with the <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> alſo; for at the end of the <hi>Thouſand Years, Satan</hi> was <hi>Let Looſe,</hi> to make the Attempt on the <hi>Holy,</hi> and <hi>Beloved City,</hi> by <hi>deceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Nations</hi> into that Attempt: Now <hi>Satans</hi> being <hi>let Looſe</hi> is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid to be, when the <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> were <hi>expired;</hi> ſo the <hi>City</hi> muſt needs be during the <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> in Peace and Safety, and Attempted at the end <hi>of</hi> the <hi>Thouſand Years;</hi> when <hi>Fire Comming down to deſtroy the Enemies,</hi> and <hi>Satan</hi> not being <hi>Sealed</hi> up only, but caſt into the <hi>Lake,</hi> after this Attempt, immediately Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>White Throne,</hi> and <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth, flying</hi> from the <hi>Face</hi> of <hi>Him</hi> that <hi>Sat upon it.</hi> So then the <hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> that <hi>Fled away</hi> muſt be the <hi>New-Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> that were together in the <hi>Holy City,</hi> during the <hi>Thouſand Years.</hi> And yet hath not this <hi>Kingdom</hi> End, when the <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> End, becauſe <hi>Chriſt delivers</hi> up the <hi>Saints</hi> into the Enjoyment of <hi>God,</hi> the Principal Part of this <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> but yet much more ſtrictly, and properly, the <hi>Kingdom</hi> is <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered</hi> up, Becauſe what was more Immediately mannaged by Chriſt in the <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> in a Viſible and Conſpicuous Glory, is now mannaged by the <hi>Divine Nature,</hi> conveying his Love by the <hi>Eternal Word,</hi> through the <hi>Human Nature</hi> in <hi>Grace</hi> to his <hi>Saints,</hi> and in <hi>Wrath</hi> to thoſe in the <hi>Lake.</hi> For the <hi>Kingdom</hi> delivered up, is the <hi>Power delivered up,</hi> and it is explained by the <hi>Son being Subject,</hi> and by <hi>God</hi> even the <hi>Father,</hi> therein oppoſed to the <hi>Son,</hi> being <hi>All in All;</hi> All things elſe Being then Subdued, and the Glory ſhining from the <hi>Father</hi> by the <hi>Eternal Word,</hi> Vibrated by <hi>the Eternal Spirit,</hi> through the <hi>Human Nature;</hi> For ſo Aſſures us our <hi>Lords</hi> whole Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, <hi>John</hi> 17. 21. to the End.</p>
                  <p>And with this whole State of things, upon cloſe Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, will be found to Agree all the <hi>Oeconomies</hi> of <hi>Scripture;</hi> and otherwiſe none of them will be found to Agree.</p>
                  <p>So that if it ſhould be ſaid, why ſhould not this <hi>Prayer</hi> be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the preſent State of <hi>the Kingdom,</hi> as High as we can attain in it, and then of the Abſolute, Perfect, and Supreme <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of Eternity? The Anſwer is very plain: He who is the only <hi>Wiſe God,</hi> hath found the <hi>Oeconomy</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt neceſſary,</hi> both as a Mirror of his own <hi>Wiſdom and Glory,</hi> in Relation to his Creation, as <hi>Reſtored</hi> by the <hi>Redemption of Chriſt;</hi> and alſo as a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of his <hi>Saints, by Chriſt in the Glory, and Holineſs of Human Nature,</hi> for that Union with himſelf, in the Abſolutely <hi>Divine King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Eternity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In which That Laſt Act of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as in <hi>our Nature, ſeeking</hi> not <hi>his own Will, nor Glory, but the Glory of the Father;</hi> He does not only in, and by himſelf perform, as that Higheſt Act of Obedience,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105089:20"/> and ſelf Reſignation; but he United all his <hi>Saints</hi> with him in that Act; that however the State of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> might ſeem more proportioned to the <hi>Human Nature,</hi> as of <hi>Spirits in Bodies, Chriſt the Head for his whole Body of Saints the Church,</hi> and they in and by him Chooſe and are moſt gladly <hi>Delivered</hi> up into that whole State, to have <hi>Body</hi> as much (as can ſtand with Remaining Higheſt Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualiz'd <hi>Bodies;</hi> and Diſtinct Beings) ſwallowed up of <hi>God all Spirit,</hi> and <hi>Created</hi> ſwallowed up of <hi>Increated;</hi> and is that Laſt and moſt perfect Act of Chriſts <hi>Declaring</hi> to <hi>All,</hi> the <hi>Name</hi> of the <hi>Father</hi> and wherein He <hi>will declare it;</hi> that the <hi>Love, wherewith the Father Loved Chriſt may be in them, and He in them,</hi> John 17. <hi>ult.</hi> All which is in cluded in this <hi>Prayer</hi> for the <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
               <p>I have now ſo far, as I can underſtand, ſetled the Principal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and find the true Elevation of this <hi>Prayer,</hi> as the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom,</hi> and Vindicated it from all objections. I now come to Adjuſt each part of this Prayer hereunto, which Conſiſts of a <hi>Prefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Addreſs,</hi> and a <hi>Doxological Concluſion,</hi> and as they are Generally Accounted, <hi>Six,</hi> but as I Account <hi>Seven Petitions,</hi> Anſwerable to the many <hi>Sevens</hi> in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> Leading to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the reaſon, why I Account <hi>Seven,</hi> what others Account but ſix, is, Thoſe Two; <hi>Lead us not into Temptation, But deliver us from Evil,</hi> very naturally fall into <hi>Two Petitions,</hi> and expreſs Two di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct very High things; though Both fall into one State; and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, but do ſo, even that State of this <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> And the <hi>but</hi> is a <hi>but</hi> of Diſcretion, and Diſtinction of things. And yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thoſe Two diſtinct things can neither of them be, but United in time, and in that <hi>Bleſſed State,</hi> wherein either of them ſhall be, They are ſo Conjoyned; and the <hi>but</hi> does not only Diſcern, but Tye them together.</p>
               <div type="prefatory_address">
                  <p>I Come therefore to the <hi>Prefatory Addreſs,</hi> which conſiſts of Two things; The Compellation uſed to God, <hi>Father, and our Father;</hi> A Compellation Importing <hi>Tranſendent Greatneſs, and Goodneſs;</hi> and the further Magnification of him by his Reſidence, which is <hi>Heaven, who are in Heaven:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Preface, <hi>Our Father].</hi> I deny not any of the Senſes, <hi>Holy Men of God</hi> have given of this Appellation, but exalt it to 'its Heighth; and the Heighth is, when God gives the <hi>Inheritance;</hi> then he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in full <hi>Paternity and Fatherhood;</hi> and this is at the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> the <hi>Redemption of our Bodies;</hi> For as he is the <hi>God,</hi> ſo he is the <hi>Father, not of the Dead, but of the Living;</hi> and at this Time, as he is not <hi>Aſhamed</hi> to be called the <hi>God,</hi> ſo he will not be <hi>Aſhamed</hi> to be called the <hi>Father of his Servants;</hi> For then He will bring the <hi>Inheritance</hi> and the <hi>Adoption</hi> together, and ſhew, how One is <hi>Provided</hi> for the Other<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:105089:20"/>
                  <p> And this muſt needs be ſo; There muſt be ſuch an <hi>Adoption</hi> by, and in the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> and ſuch an <hi>Inheritance:</hi> For, as our Lord ſays, <hi>They All Live</hi> to <hi>Him, whoſe God He is:</hi> He cannot elſe be their God. So then that they may <hi>Live</hi> to Him, and He be their God, They muſt <hi>Live;</hi> elſe how can <hi>They Live to Him,</hi> and he be <hi>their God</hi> and <hi>their Father?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now ſeeing <hi>God</hi> is the <hi>God of all his Servants,</hi> not only as <hi>Spirits,</hi> but as <hi>Spirits in Bodies:</hi> They muſt thtrefore <hi>All Live to him,</hi> as <hi>Spirits in Bodies;</hi> and if for ſome Time They are <hi>Spirits</hi> out of <hi>Bodies,</hi> and thoſe Spirits are Pledges of the Future State of Life; yet it can be but for a Time, though it may be to the <hi>Servants of God,</hi> who liv'd far off from that <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> a very long time, according to our Meaſure of Time; yet nothing compar'd with the <hi>Thouſand Years Kingdom of Christ Deliver'd up into an Eternity of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion with God and the Father.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Seeing then, I ſay again, <hi>God</hi> is the God of his <hi>Servants,</hi> as Spirits in Bodies, and the State oppoſite to it, is call'd <hi>Hades, Death,</hi> and the <hi>Grave;</hi> or at the higheſt, an <hi>Inviſible State,</hi> though in his wiſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, for ſo conſiderable a Space, He is ſatisfied by his Saints, as Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits living to him; yet there muſt needs be a <hi>Reſurrection<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> that in Full ſenſe his Servants may <hi>Live to Him,</hi> and He be <hi>known</hi> to be <hi>Their God</hi> and <hi>Father;</hi> For the Children of God are then <hi>known</hi> to be the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, and He their Father, when they ſhall be and appear the Children of the <hi>Reſurrection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is therefore ſaid, at the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> as the Juſt time of all theſe things fulfill'd; <hi>He that overcometh ſhall inherit All Things; And I will be to him a God, and He ſhall be to me a Son;</hi> Then the <hi>Abba Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> that we now cry as Children, ſhall in that Fulneſs of the Inheritance, be pronounc'd in Full and Manly Sounds and Accents. This muſt be the <hi>Adoption</hi> then. If the <hi>Adoption,</hi> it muſt be alſo the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> or <hi>Redemplion of our Bodies.</hi> For the <hi>Adoption</hi> and the <hi>Redemption</hi> of our <hi>Bodies,</hi> are by the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> made one and the ſame. Accordingly, the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> hath a <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> and is an Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance.</p>
                  <p>But further, to make this out, whenever the Adoption or Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of the Children of God ſhall be, there ſhall be a Reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the whole Creation: For the <hi>Creation</hi> it ſelf ſhall then be <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered</hi> into the <hi>Glorious Liberty of the Children of God;</hi> When there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this <hi>World</hi> to <hi>come</hi> is, it ſhall be <hi>put in ſubjection to Chriſt</hi> Alone: Then ſhall be his Kingdom therefore; For theſe things reciprocate: Then ſhall be the <hi>Adoption;</hi> and when the <hi>Adoption</hi> is, This <hi>VVorld to come</hi> of the <hi>Reſtitution</hi> ſhall be. So the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Chriſt, and the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution,</hi> muſt needs be together with the <hi>Adoption,</hi> or the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> or the <hi>Redemption of our Bodies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:105089:21"/>
                  <p> Let us then lay All together; The <hi>Prayer,</hi> that our <hi>Lord taught, Teaches</hi> us to <hi>pray, Our Father.</hi> The Higheſt ſenſe of <hi>God</hi> being <hi>Our Father</hi> is at the <hi>Adoption</hi> or Manifeſtation of the <hi>Sons of God</hi> in the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> or <hi>Redemption</hi> of our Bodies; Together with this is the <hi>Reſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Creation</hi> in the <hi>World of the ſecond Adam,</hi> that is, <hi>the World to come,</hi> of which God in Chriſt is the Father; even of that New Heaven, and New Earth, as He is now ſtyl'd the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Heaven, and Earth; All theſe are in the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> and <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt: This Prayer of our Lord</hi> comprehends the Largeſt, and Reaches the higheſt ſenſe of All Things of <hi>Prayer.</hi> The very <hi>Calling</hi> of <hi>God</hi> therefore <hi>Father,</hi> and <hi>Our Father,</hi> muſt needs reach the State of the <hi>Adoption,</hi> or <hi>Manifeſtation of the Kingdom of God,</hi> which is the State of the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> or <hi>Redemption of our Bodies;</hi> which is the State of the <hi>Reſtitution of All Things;</hi> which is the State of the <hi>World to Come;</hi> which is the State of the <hi>New Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> and of the <hi>Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> which <hi>Kingdom</hi> the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> is; and accordingly, It hath a <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> and a <hi>New Creation</hi> Appertaining to it; which is the <hi>Reſtitution</hi> of <hi>All Things;</hi> ſo that this <hi>Prayer.</hi> muſt even from this Prefatory Addreſs be the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let us now conſider the further Magnification of God by his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence in <hi>Heaven,</hi> that we may obſerve; whether That have any Manuduction of our Thoughts towards the <hi>Kingdom: Our Father which art in Heaven,</hi> or in the <hi>Heavens:</hi> Theſe words are a Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of God, as by his ſupreme Reſidence in the <hi>Heavens,</hi> or in the <hi>Heaven of Heavens.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now to pray to him, who <hi>Dwelleth in the Heavens,</hi> that his <hi>Name may be Sanctified,</hi> as in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and on <hi>Earth,</hi> and <hi>his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom Come, as in Heaven, and on Earth;</hi> and <hi>his Will Done, as in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and on Earth;</hi> what is it, but to Beſeech <hi>Him to Bow the Heavens, to Rend the Heavens,</hi> and to <hi>Come Down;</hi> and to Eſtabliſh as in a Lower <hi>Heaven,</hi> a parallel State, as in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and on <hi>Earth.</hi> It is to ſay to <hi>God,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid; <hi>The Heaven of Heavens cannot contain Thee. Come down</hi> therefore into the Lower <hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> and Eſtabliſh a State as in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and on <hi>Earth;</hi> And becauſe, This cannot be in the preſent <hi>Old</hi> lower <hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> Therefore to pray for ſuch a State, as in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and on <hi>Earth,</hi> is to pray for the <hi>New Heaven,</hi> and the <hi>New Earth;</hi> or the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> that ſhall <hi>Come Down</hi> from <hi>Our Lord out of Heaven.</hi> And when this is, The <hi>Heavens that now are,</hi> ſhall be <hi>Rent</hi> indeed, as an <hi>old Garment;</hi> and ſhall with the vehemency of that <hi>Flame melt,</hi> and <hi>Come Down;</hi> And They ſhall be according to this his <hi>Promiſe, New Heavens,</hi> and a <hi>New Earth,</hi> wherein <hi>Righteouſneſs ſhall Dwell;</hi> and ſo his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:105089:21"/> 
                     <hi>Name</hi> ſhould be <hi>Sanctified,</hi> his <hi>Kingdom come</hi> and <hi>His will be done,</hi> as in <hi>Heaven</hi> and in <hi>Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And in <hi>our Father,</hi> not only the <hi>Father,</hi> but the <hi>Eternal Word,</hi> who is <hi>One</hi> with the <hi>Father,</hi> is <hi>Prayed</hi> unto; So that, in a more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Sence of the <hi>Prayer,</hi> we beſeech his <hi>Comming down</hi> in <hi>our Nature;</hi> For the <hi>Heavens Receive</hi> and ſo <hi>Contain Him,</hi> but till the <hi>Times</hi> of the <hi>Re-En-Livening,</hi> and <hi>Reſtitution</hi> of <hi>All Things;</hi> the <hi>Re-En-Livening</hi> them, <hi>as by a Reſurrection,</hi> and New Vigor of the whole <hi>Creation.</hi> Then they ſhall no longer <hi>Receive</hi> or <hi>Contain Him,</hi> but He ſhall De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend, even that <hi>Jeſus now Preached, God will ſend Down from the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,</hi> that now <hi>Receive Him. Acts</hi> 3. 20. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And thus there is nothing more ſuitable to <hi>Scripture,</hi> then to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>Heaven,</hi> when he is to Manifeſt Himſelf as <hi>Comming down from Heaven,</hi> and out of <hi>Heaven.</hi> Thus God <hi>Dwelling</hi> with the <hi>Humhle and Contrite Heart</hi> is prefaced with his <hi>Dwelling</hi> in the <hi>High,</hi> and <hi>Holy Place,</hi> and <hi>Inhabiting Eternity,</hi> and with the <hi>Heaven,</hi> being His <hi>Throne,</hi> and the <hi>Earth</hi> His <hi>Foot-Stool;</hi> and together with this Deſcription of the Grandieur of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Heaven,</hi> is joyned the <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of New Heavens, and a New Earth,</hi> c. 65, c. 66. to ſhew, how Great the Power of Him, that <hi>Dwelleth in the Heavens</hi> is; And the <hi>Dwelling of God and of Chriſt in the Heavens</hi> now, is no Barr to His <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle</hi> being with <hi>Men in the Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> but the Infinite Power therein Imployed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> produces it in its own Time: At the <hi>New Jeruſalem, it is Proclaimed</hi> therefore out of <hi>Heaven, with a Loud Voice;</hi> The <hi>Taberacle of God is with Men, and he will Dwell among them;</hi> Not they with Him, as in the <hi>Heaven of Heavens;</hi> but <hi>He</hi> with <hi>them,</hi> as in the <hi>New Heaven and New Earth.</hi> The <hi>Voice</hi> is from <hi>Heaven,</hi> and the <hi>New Jeruſalem comes down from God out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thus we ſee, how fitly the Addreſs to God, <hi>as our Father;</hi> and <hi>as our Father, who is in Heaven;</hi> agree with the Scriptures Relating to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="petition">
                  <p>I Come therefore to the <hi>Firſt Petition,</hi> and to Obſerve how agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able it is to the <hi>Elevation</hi> of the <hi>Prayer,</hi> as it is the <hi>Prayer of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi> The Words of this <hi>Firſt Petition,</hi> are theſe great ones; <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed or Sanctified be thy Name.</hi> And it is to be Remarked, that they ſuſtain the Place of the <hi>Firſt Petition</hi> of ſo Great a <hi>Prayer;</hi> and Theſe Conſiſt of Two Parts, <hi>viz.</hi> the Grand Object in the Eye, as I may ſo ſpeak, of the Petition, and that is, the <hi>Name of God;</hi> and That which is <hi>Prayed,</hi> or Deſired concerning it; that it may be <hi>Sanctified;</hi> and further the Form or Manner of the <hi>Petition</hi> is greatly to be Conſidered; It is not declared, how, or by whom,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:105089:22"/> the Name is to be <hi>Sanctified,</hi> but abſolutely, that it ſhould be <hi>Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi> till we come to that Common Modification of theſe Three <hi>Petitions, as in Heaven and upon Earth;</hi> as hath been ſet out.</p>
                  <p>Let us then Enquire for the Higheſt Senſes of the <hi>Name of God,</hi> and of the <hi>Sanctification of His Name;</hi> for it is certain, <hi>this Prayer taught by Chriſt</hi> Reaches thoſe Higheſt Senſes, and thoſe Higheſt Senſes muſt Iſſue themſelves, when ever the <hi>Petition</hi> is Anſwered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a State, <hi>as in Heaven,</hi> and <hi>upon Earth.</hi> All which Laid to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, will Abſolutely evince, and make Good, that no Lower State, than that of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> can be the Anſwer of this <hi>Prayer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If we then <hi>Firſt</hi> Reſearch the <hi>Name of God,</hi> it can be no other in its Higheſt Sence, but his <hi>Nature</hi> in its Higheſt Manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: For His <hi>Name</hi> is, <hi>I am, that I am;</hi> that is, His <hi>Being</hi> is His <hi>Name,</hi> and His <hi>Name</hi> is His <hi>Being.</hi> When God therefore ſays to the <hi>Iſraelites, he</hi> was not known unto their Fathers, by his <hi>Name Jehovah;</hi> It ſignifies, <hi>he</hi> was not known unto them by thoſe <hi>Eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Manifeſtations</hi> of <hi>himſelf, he</hi> was now about to make <hi>himſelf</hi> known to themſelves the <hi>Children</hi> of thoſe <hi>Fathers</hi> by, before <hi>Egypt</hi> and the <hi>Cananites,</hi> and in thoſe Glorious Appearances from <hi>Heaven,</hi> at <hi>his Giving of the Land,</hi> and in the <hi>Tabernacle of Teſtimony;</hi> And Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, where ever, there are Extraordinary Appearances of <hi>Divine Power, and Glory, and Wondrous Works,</hi> there <hi>his Name</hi> is ſaid to <hi>be near;</hi> as many <hi>Scriptures</hi> do ſhew. When <hi>God</hi> gave <hi>Moſes</hi> a ſight of <hi>his Glory; he</hi> is ſaid to <hi>Proclaim his Name,</hi> Exod. 33, c. 34. Now there is no Manifeſtation or Divine Diſpenſation what ever, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Divine Glory ſo Appear'd as in and by our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> in whom <hi>his Name</hi> is ſaid to <hi>be,</hi> and who is ſaid to come in <hi>his Name,</hi> and to declare <hi>his Name;</hi> So there is no Manifeſtation of our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ſo great, as that of <hi>his Kingdom,</hi> when the <hi>Lord ſhall be One in all the Earth,</hi> and <hi>his Name One;</hi> and that <hi>One Name is in Chriſt,</hi> to whom <hi>God hath given a Name above every Name,</hi> that is <hi>Named</hi> in <hi>Heaven</hi> or <hi>Earth;</hi> And all ſhall <hi>confeſs Him to be Lord, to the Glory of God the Father:</hi> Becauſe the <hi>Name of God the Father is Eſſentially</hi> in <hi>him,</hi> as <hi>he</hi> is the <hi>Eternal Word,</hi> and in <hi>him</hi> by way of Higheſt Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation, as <hi>he</hi> is the <hi>Son of Man,</hi> or the <hi>Eternal Word in Human Nature.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Seeing then, It can no way be denied, but that every <hi>Word</hi> of this <hi>Prayer</hi> is to be underſtood in the Higheſt Sence; The <hi>Name of God,</hi> muſt be underſtood in the higheſt Sence, both as to the Manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>his Eſſential, Eternal, Increated Glory;</hi> And That is by the <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Word;</hi> And as to <hi>his</hi> Manifeſtation of <hi>himſelf</hi> in a Created Glory,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:105089:22"/> and 'its higheſt Elevation; That is in the <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>only Begotten Son of God,</hi> beheld in the heighth of <hi>his Glory,</hi> and of <hi>his Kingdom:</hi> And thus we ſee in Regard of the <hi>Name of God, this Prayer muſt</hi> be the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let us now Conſider the Thing that is Deſired touching this <hi>Name of God;</hi> And that is, That it may be <hi>Sanctified,</hi> and Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely <hi>Sanctified. Sanctified be thy Name,</hi> ſo expreſſed, as to ſignifie an Abſolute <hi>Sanctification.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That we may then underſtand the <hi>Sanctifying</hi> of <hi>Gods Name; Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs</hi> it ſelf is to be ſought out in the true Notion of it; now <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs</hi> is that ſo Supream <hi>Atribute of God,</hi> that the <hi>Seraphims Reſt not Day and Night,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy, is the Lord of Hoſts The ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Earth</hi> is his Glory. That is, it properly is ſo, and ought to be ſo: So this is ſaid by way of higheſt Exaltati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the <hi>Song of Moſes, the Servant of God; Glorious in Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now the Eſſential Notion God gives us of <hi>Holineſs</hi> in his <hi>Word</hi> is; <hi>Separation to God</hi> is <hi>Holineſs to Jehovah.</hi> The Contrary to this <hi>Holineſs</hi> is <hi>Commonneſs</hi> to other Uſes. The <hi>Holineſs of God</hi> is then his Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Separation to himſelf in the perfection of his own Being, and Glory; the Receiving into Union with which his own Saints, and Servants; Angels, and Men, is their <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Glory:</hi> and this he doth by no other than himſelf, by the Eternal <hi>Word,</hi> in our <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and by his <hi>Spirit</hi> in and through him.</p>
                  <p>If this then be the Notion of the <hi>Eſſential Holineſs of God; Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of God, or of</hi> his <hi>Name</hi> can be no other than the <hi>Manifeſtation</hi> of God, as thus <hi>Infinitely Holy:</hi> For there can be no Addition, to the <hi>Holineſs,</hi> ſeeing it is <hi>Infinite;</hi> Men are therefore ſaid to <hi>Sanctify</hi> God, when they declare, and Speak of, and Treat with God, as <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely Holy;</hi> So God is ſaid to <hi>Sanctify</hi> himſelf when He Lays Obligations on Creatures to See him, and Speak of him, as ſo <hi>Holy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now it is Certain none can <hi>Sanctify</hi> God, as himſelf; As his own <hi>Purity, Power, Wiſdom, Truth, Goodneſs is Seen, Acknowedg'd, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored</hi> in his Great <hi>Works,</hi> and <hi>Word;</hi> So the more Immediate the Appearance is, the Greater is the <hi>Sanctification.</hi> The Works of Immediate <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Preſence Sanctify God</hi> more than his General <hi>Works;</hi> as <hi>Moſes Sings to him; Glorious in Holineſs, Fearful in Praiſes, doing Wonders;</hi> When God had Appeared ſo Immediately at the <hi>Red Sea:</hi> Never was God ſo <hi>Sanctified</hi> as by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> whom to that ſo great End He <hi>Sanctified,</hi> is <hi>Sealed, and Sent into the World,</hi> to <hi>Glorify</hi> him by ſhewing and Setting out his own <hi>Holineſs,</hi> and declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his <hi>Name.</hi> No way therefore can God be ſo <hi>Sanctified,</hi> as in
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:105089:23"/> that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> wherein <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Lamb, Chriſt,</hi> will have his <hi>Throne,</hi> and his <hi>Tabernatle ſhall be with men;</hi> Then ſhall God be known to be the <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy,</hi> and the <hi>Fullneſs of the Earth his Glory:</hi> For when <hi>Eſay ſaw this Glory</hi> of Chriſt, Then was this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ohn</hi> 12.</note> to his <hi>Holineſs.</hi> And as it was then by <hi>Serophs,</hi> ſo when the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Chriſt is, ſhall it be by all his Saints, as in the <hi>New Heaven,</hi> ſo on the <hi>New Earth;</hi> and his <hi>Servants ſhall ſee his Face,</hi> and <hi>his Name ſhall be in their Foreheads:</hi> And ſo They in their Sphere are in a perpetual <hi>Sanctification of the Name of God,</hi> as with a Plate on their Foreheads, inſcribed with <hi>Holineſs to Jehovah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Seeing then. as hath been already Argued, and it can no way be denied; This <hi>Prayer</hi> Aſcends to the very Heighth of Things, that are to be <hi>prayed</hi> for, and to the higheſt Senſes, the Words, it uſes, can be expounded into; and that there is ſuch a <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Kingdom,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Name of God</hi> ſhall be thus <hi>Sanctified</hi> to the Higheſt by Saints, by Chriſt, who is Himſelf, even in ſo immediate a Kingdom: Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>This Prayer,</hi> at its higheſt Elevation, muſt be a <hi>Prayer</hi> for the State of that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and that <hi>Sanctification of the Name of God.</hi> And ſeeing it muſt be a St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te, as in a Parallelliſm, and as in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>upon Earib;</hi> as hath been Argued from the <hi>Will of God, Donè as in Heaven,</hi> and <hi>upon Earth;</hi> The <hi>Glory of God,</hi> in the <hi>Holineſs of his Name.</hi> muſt ſhine. as in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>upon Earth;</hi> that is, from the <hi>New Heaven</hi> upon the <hi>New Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="petition">
                  <p>I come now to the <hi>Second Petition, Thy Kingdom come.</hi> And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be taken in the ſtrict Senſe of the Words, or in the Connexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the <hi>Petitions</hi> before and after it, it will be every way evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, That this <hi>Prayer</hi> muſt be the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For when we pray, That the <hi>Kingdom of God may come,</hi> what <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> can it be that ſhould come? The <hi>Kingdom</hi> of God's Univerſal <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Dominion</hi> cannot be pray'd for, that it ſhould, becauſe it is alway, it hath been alway, and it cannot but be for ever: The <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Goſpel</hi> it might be, till the Univerſal <hi>Preaching</hi> of it by the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and Firſt Miniſters of the <hi>New Teſtament:</hi> But then the Coming of it was Accompliſhed, except as there ſhall be a more Full and Glorious Coming at the more Univerſal <hi>Preaching</hi> of it, as this <hi>Prayer</hi> muſt needs import: Or elſe to pray, That the <hi>Kingdom may come,</hi> as it is the <hi>Kingdom of the Gospel,</hi> muſt be, as to pray, that <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah</hi> might <hi>come,</hi> who is already <hi>come;</hi> And That would be a Secret Denial, That <hi>Chriſt is come in the Fleſh,</hi> and that This is the True <hi>Gospel,</hi> or <hi>Grace of God wherein we ſtand.</hi> If therefore it be the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the <hi>Gospel,</hi> that is (as it is indeed) here to be underſtood; It muſt needs be, That as the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> is to have an <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Glorious</hi>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:105089:23"/> 
                     <hi>Kingdom;</hi> ſo there ſhall be yet a much more <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> and <hi>Effectual preaching of the Gospel,</hi> even the <hi>Everlaſting Gospel,</hi> Declaring, and Introducing that <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There is, I acknowledge, yet remaining, a <hi>Kingdom of Glory in Eternity,</hi> introduc'd by the <hi>Day of Judgment,</hi> according to the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Notion, that might be intended in this <hi>Prayer.</hi> And though this <hi>Kingdom</hi> could not properly be ſaid to come, in regard of Place, ſeeing it is to be in the <hi>Higheſt Heaven,</hi> where it already is; yet that the Time of it might <hi>come,</hi> might be <hi>prayed;</hi> and that in the mean Time, the <hi>Will of God,</hi> might in Degree, and in Sincerity be <hi>Done on Earth, as in Heaven.</hi> But becauſe, as hath been already, and ſhall ſtill be Argued: There is a <hi>Glorious Kingdom</hi> before that, and that ſtands in a Parallel, betwixt the <hi>New Heaven</hi> and the <hi>New Earth;</hi> and that prepares for, and Iſſues into that Greateſt <hi>Kingdom of Eternity,</hi> and is indeed One with it in all Subſtantials; It muſt needs be moſt Directly in the Eye of this <hi>Prayer,</hi> which reaches the higheſt ſenſe, that the Words can poſſibly be ſuppoſed to contain.</p>
                  <p>Seeing then the <hi>Gospel</hi> in the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal preaching;</hi> in that It is to bring forth the Great, and moſt Illuſtrious <hi>Kingdom of God,</hi> and of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is call'd the <hi>Kingdom of God;</hi> and that <hi>Our Lord</hi> continually call'd it ſo in that Time of his Miniſtry, wherein he gave this <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er;</hi> and wherein He Teaches to <hi>pray, Thy Kingdom come; This King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> muſt needs be underſtood to be the Higheſt State of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> moſt <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſally</hi> and moſt <hi>Efficaciouſly preach'd</hi> ſo, that it ſhall indeed moſt conſpicuouſly and illuſtriouſly bring forth that <hi>Kingdom in its Glory.</hi> And that is the <hi>Kingdom</hi> here <hi>prayed</hi> for: And it is a <hi>Kingdom</hi> that ſhall never <hi>end,</hi> and therefore is <hi>One Kingdom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> with the <hi>Eternal Kingdom of God,</hi> into which it is <hi>Delivered up.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From All which it follows, The <hi>Preaching of the Goſpel</hi> is not that Kingdom in the meer <hi>Adminiſtration,</hi> or <hi>Preaching</hi> of it, but as it is to produce the <hi>Kingdom of God,</hi> and of <hi>Christ</hi> in its <hi>Glory.</hi> For Chriſt Left the <hi>Gospel in preaching,</hi> when <hi>He went into a Far Countrey,</hi> to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a Kingdom,</hi> and <hi>to Return</hi> with it, when that <hi>Goſpel</hi> ſhould have its full Effect; and he ſhews, That though the <hi>Preaching of the Goſpel</hi> did immediately <hi>Appear,</hi> yet the <hi>Kingdom</hi> did not <hi>immediately Appear;</hi> there was a Dawn of it in that <hi>Preaching,</hi> which is therefore in a General Way, call'd, the <hi>Kingdom of God.</hi> But it was not to bring forth the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> till a Second, more Univerſal and Effectual <hi>Publication, Luke</hi> 19. compar'd with <hi>Revel.</hi> 14.</p>
                  <p>And thus far I have Argued upon a ſimple Conſideration of the Words in Themſelves: But if we look upon them, as involv'd
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:105089:24"/> with the Foregoing and Following <hi>Petitions,</hi> the Enforcement is much ſtronger; For the Connexion may be Three manner of ways underſtood; and in which ſoever of thoſe ways it be underſtood, the Argument will be very forcible.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Let theſe Three <hi>Petitions</hi> ſtand equally as <hi>Petitions;</hi> And if it be a Rule of <hi>Prayer,</hi> for the Enlargement of the <hi>Glory of God,</hi> that his <hi>Glory</hi> ſhould be the <hi>Fullneſs of the Earth,</hi> or as in <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>upon Earth;</hi> Then there is the Force of a <hi>Petition Taught</hi> by Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly, according to <hi>Faith,</hi> according to <hi>Promiſe,</hi> according to the <hi>Will of God,</hi> and under the <hi>Mediation of Chriſt;</hi> and therefore That muſt be Anſwer'd; For there is the ſame <hi>Rule of Proportion,</hi> that if we ought to deſire, the <hi>Will of God may be done,</hi> and <hi>His Name ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, as in Heaven and upon Earth,</hi> we ought alſo to <hi>Pray,</hi> His <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom may come, as in Heaven,</hi> and <hi>upon Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Take the <hi>Petitions</hi> in Connexion; And if that <hi>Petition, Thy Will be done as in Heaven and on Earth,</hi> be <hi>Heard;</hi> it cannot be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, the <hi>Kingdom of God muſt be, as in Heaven and on Earth;</hi> For <hi>his Will done is his Kingdom;</hi> and ſo proportionably, <hi>His Name muſt be ſanctified:</hi> When one is, the other cannot but be: If any one is not, the other cannot, either of Them be.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Indeed, the <hi>Kingdom</hi> placed in the middle, is as the Great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument by which the other Two are effected, the Center about which they turn; That <hi>his Name may be ſanctified,</hi> and his <hi>Will done,</hi> as in <hi>Heaven</hi> and on <hi>Earth, His Kingdom muſt come,</hi> as in <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>on Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For what Reaſon can be given, ſeeing it is ſo highly pleaſing and acceptable to God, and ſo due from all his <hi>Creatures;</hi> if it be but in the Nature of the Thing poſſible; that his <hi>Name ſhould be ſanctified,</hi> and <hi>his Will done, as in Heaven, and on Earth;</hi> that it ſhould not in ſo long a Time, either beſore, or eſpecially ſince this <hi>Prayer taught by our Lord,</hi> have come to paſs; but that in his wife Diſpoſe and Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, the Time of his Glorious and Illuſtrious <hi>Kingdom, as in Heaven, and on Earth,</hi> was not yet come.</p>
                  <p>When therefore the <hi>Myſtery of God</hi> ſhall be <hi>finiſh'd</hi> in the <hi>Days of the Seventh Angel,</hi> and He ſhall <hi>Sound;</hi> it ſhall be <hi>proclaim'd,</hi> that the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of this World are beeome the Kingdoms of the Lord, and of his Chriſt;</hi> That he hath taken <hi>to him his Great Power, and Reigns,</hi> when there ſhall be the <hi>Voice of many VVaters, and of mighty Thunderings;</hi> ſaying, <hi>The Lord God Omnipotent Reigns;</hi> Then ſhall be the <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Appearing of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> And it ſhall be a <hi>Kingdom,</hi> as in <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>on Earth,</hi> a <hi>Kingdom of God, and of the Lamb,</hi> Revel. 19.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="petition">
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:105089:24"/>
                  <p> I come therefore to the Third Petition, <hi>Thy Will be done, as in Heaven,</hi> and upon <hi>Earth;</hi> For ſo are the Words exactly tranſlated: And it ſeems not unworthy Notice, That when in the Addreſs to God, we ſay, <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven;</hi> The Word in the <hi>Greek</hi> is in the Plural Number, <hi>who art in the Heavens.</hi> But when we <hi>pray, Thy Will be done, as in Heaven, and on Earth;</hi> the word <hi>Heaven</hi> is in the ſingular Number, and ſo in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> c. 21. a ſingle <hi>New Heaven John ſaw.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now theſe words are generally underſtood, as if they had been thus Form'd; <hi>Thy Will be done on Earth,</hi> according to the <hi>Exemplar</hi> of its being <hi>done in Heaven;</hi> but in both <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>Luke</hi> they are fram'd by way of <hi>parallel, Let thy Will be done, as in Heaven,</hi> and <hi>upon Earth.</hi> So that in ſtricteſt holding to the words, the <hi>Prayer</hi> is for a <hi>parallel</hi> State, as <hi>in Heaven and upon Earth.</hi> I dare not deny, but if there were not Another Admirable Senſe given us by Scripture con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them, That Senſe of the <hi>Exemplarity</hi> of the <hi>Will of God</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>done on Earth</hi> as <hi>in Heaven,</hi> were very clear and good: But when this Contexture is ſuch, as to Favour Another Senſe moſt, <hi>viz.</hi> of the <hi>Parallelliſm;</hi> and that <hi>Scripture</hi> offers ſuch a <hi>Parallelliſm</hi> to us, Undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly the <hi>Paralleliſm</hi> is rather to be choſen.</p>
                  <p>When therefore, as I have already Argued, this <hi>Prayer</hi> is ſo Founded, that this <hi>Petition</hi> ſhalI certainly be Anſwer'd; And that it muſt be Anſwered in a State on ſome Earth, and that it cannot be otherwiſe Anſwered; and that there is ſo great Countenance of a <hi>Parallelliſm, as in Heaven and upon Earth;</hi> we have nothing more ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary now to do, than to ſearch Scripture for the full ſettling of this <hi>Paralelliſm.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By Three Gradations therefore we may take this <hi>Paralel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſm.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. By conſidering thoſe <hi>Scriptures</hi> that Repreſent <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> in ſuch a <hi>Parallel;</hi> The <hi>Apoſtle Peter</hi> ſays, <hi>VVe, according to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, look for New Heavens, and a New Earth, wherein dwelleth Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> where the <hi>Parallel lies</hi> in the <hi>Heaven and Earth</hi> expreſly nam'd; in both being <hi>New,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs dwelling in both.,</hi> Ep. 2. c. 3. 13.</p>
                  <p>Again, the Apoſtle, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 10. ſpeaking of that very Time of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in its <hi>Glorious Appearance,</hi> when he ſhall appear the <hi>Second Time, without Sin, unto Salvation;</hi> He calls it, the <hi>Oeconomy, the Fullneſs</hi> of <hi>Time.</hi> Now at this Time, ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> God would Recollect All, as into <hi>One Head in Chriſt,</hi> even <hi>in Chriſt; All things in Heaven and Earth.</hi> Here are <hi>All</hi> things in <hi>Heaven and Earth.</hi> Here are <hi>All Things in Heaven and in Earth</hi> in a <hi>parallel in Chriſt, even in Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:105089:25"/>
                  <p> In a <hi>Scripture</hi> of a very like Conſtitution with this, <hi>Col.</hi> 1: 20. the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaks of God <hi>Reconciling All Things in Heaven and Earth by him, even by him.</hi> Here again are <hi>All Things in Heaven and Earth in a parallel; Reconcil'd by him to God,</hi> even by him: As if the Apoſtle in both places had ſaid, Take notice, I ſay it Twice over, <hi>In him, In him; By him, By him, are All Things in Heaven and Earth Gathered under one Head, and Reconcil'd.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Laſtly,</hi> In a <hi>Pſalm Prophetick</hi> of the Laſt Turning the <hi>Captivity of the people of God,</hi> as in a <hi>paralelliſm</hi> betwixt <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>Truth ſhall spring out of the Earth, and Righteouſneſs ſhall Look down from Heaven,</hi> Pſal. 85. 11.</p>
                  <p>How now can Things be more fix'd and ſettled for the <hi>Doing the VVill of God, as in Heaven, and on Earth,</hi> than that there ſhould be a <hi>New Heaven and a New Earth,</hi> wherein <hi>Righteouſneſs ſhall dwell?</hi> That <hi>All Things in Heaven and Earth</hi> ſhould be <hi>Reconcil'd by Christ to God?</hi> and that <hi>Truth ſhould ſpring out of the Earth,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs look down from Heaven?</hi> When things are thus, it cannot be otherwiſe then, but that, what hath never yet been in this <hi>Old Earth,</hi> but in Chriſt Alone, ſhould be, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Will of God ſhould be done as in Heaven, and upon Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The <hi>Scripture</hi> gives Account of the <hi>Dead in Chriſt,</hi> or of Thoſe who <hi>Sleep by Jeſus,</hi> that <hi>God will bring them with him;</hi> and as ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, They ſhall be with Chriſt in the <hi>Air, viz.</hi> of the <hi>New Heaven:</hi> The <hi>Living Saints</hi> ſhall after the 1000 <hi>Years Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> be <hi>caught up</hi> to that moſt <hi>General Aſſembly,</hi> and <hi>Church of the Firſt Born, All Saints together meeting Chriſt,</hi> when <hi>he Delivers up the Kingdom:</hi> So then during the 1000 <hi>Years Kingdom,</hi> there ſhall be <hi>Saints with Chriſt in Bodies incorruptible,</hi> that <hi>cannot die,</hi> being the <hi>Children of God, and of the Reſurrection;</hi> and <hi>Saints in Paradiſiac Bodies,</hi> chang'd; So as that They ſhall not <hi>dye;</hi> One in the <hi>New Heaven,</hi> the Other on the <hi>New Earth:</hi> Now as by the One, <hi>the VVill of God ſhall be done in Heaven;</hi> by the other, as in a <hi>parallel, upon Earth; As in Heaven, and upon Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. As in the New Heaven, there ſhall be a Reſtitution of the <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,</hi> that the Heavens ſhall be Clean, and the Stars Pure; and the Higheſt Order, and Beauty in All; and no Enmity or Smiting from thence upon Any Thing on Earth; and all thoſe Hoſts and Powers of the Air, <hi>Spiritual Wickedneſſes in Heavenly Places,</hi> Diſlodged, and ſeal'd up in their <hi>Abyſs,</hi> making Room for better Inhabitants; So the Earth ſhall be ſo fruitful of All that is Excellent, that inſtead of the <hi>Briars</hi> and <hi>Thorns,</hi> ſhall come up the <hi>Fir Tree</hi> and the <hi>Myrtle Tree;</hi> And they ſhall be to the <hi>Lord a Sign,</hi> and a <hi>Memorial, that ſhall not be cut off.</hi> And at the ſame Time, the mutual Enmities of the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:105089:25"/> Creatures, moſt Contrary to the Gracious Deſignment of the <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> ſhall be utterly Extinguiſhed, and a wonderful <hi>Reconciliation</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Them; So that the <hi>Lyon, and the Lamb ſhall lye down together;</hi> There ſhall be an <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Tameneſs,</hi> and <hi>Quiet. There ſhall be no Hurting nor Deſtroying in all tbe Holy Mountain of the Lord; For Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg ſhall cover the Earth, as the Watèr does the Sea;</hi> A State, which we All know, hath never been yet; But to <hi>Reconcile Event</hi> and <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> together, Men have been forced to <hi>Evaporate</hi> and <hi>Attenuate Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy</hi> into <hi>Allegory.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now according to this our <hi>Saviour</hi> Compoſes this <hi>Prayer;</hi> And <hi>Holineſs to the Lord,</hi> the moſt <hi>Comprehenſive Expreſſion</hi> of the <hi>Will of God</hi> is moſt <hi>Specific</hi> to theſe Two <hi>States;</hi> For as above, <hi>All</hi> is moſt Pure, Clear, and Undefiled; So below, <hi>Holineſs to the Lord</hi> is on the <hi>Equippings of the Horſes,</hi> upon the <hi>Bowls,</hi> and <hi>Pots</hi> in the <hi>Lords Houſe, Which ſhall be as Bowls</hi> before the <hi>Altar,</hi> as of a <hi>Holineſs,</hi> that is of nearer Approach to <hi>God:</hi> And all the <hi>Pots</hi> and <hi>Bowls</hi> in <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> ſhall be <hi>Holineſs to the Lord,</hi> which in <hi>Prophetic</hi> Language is the very ſame with <hi>Thy Will be done as in Heaven, and upon Earth;</hi> when All the <hi>Saints</hi> are <hi>Prieſts</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Reign a</hi> 1000 <hi>Years. Zeoh.</hi> 14. 20.</p>
                  <p>All which comes Home to all that has been ſaid; That This <hi>Prayer,</hi> and the <hi>Expoſition</hi> of it at the true Height is, as of the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom;</hi> And we <hi>pray</hi> that the <hi>Will of God may be done;</hi> that is, that there may be <hi>Holineſs to the Lord,</hi> as in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>on Earth,</hi> in that State of <hi>Chriſts Kingdom;</hi> the <hi>New Heaven,</hi> or the <hi>Jeruſalem Above,</hi> and the <hi>New Earth,</hi> or the <hi>Jeruſalem Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="petition">
                  <p>I go forward now to the <hi>Fourth Petition. Give us this day, our daily Bread.</hi> And it may ſeem, <hi>This Petition</hi> can no way conſiſt with that High Sence of this <hi>Prayer,</hi> that hath been undertaken to be given of it; But at leaſt here the <hi>Prayer</hi> muſt Flat into a <hi>Prayer</hi> ſuited only to the Preſent State. For what, may we ſay, can be plainer, that no Higher is Intended, than the preſen State? when we <hi>pray,</hi> that this <hi>Bread</hi> may be given us <hi>To Day, or This Day;</hi> That it may be <hi>Given according to the Day:</hi> and when it is called <hi>our Bread,</hi> and hereunto is to be <hi>Accommodated</hi> the word, we Tranſlate <hi>Daily;</hi> All This Layed together, makes it ſeem Impoſſible to extend the Sence of this <hi>Bread</hi> beyond the neceſſary <hi>Bread</hi> of this preſent Life, with any Agreeableneſs to the <hi>Words of the Petition.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But againſt all this I ſhall Levy theſe <hi>Four Arguments,</hi> that there is a much Higher Intention, than the preſent <hi>Bread</hi> of <hi>Natural Life,</hi>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:105089:26"/> Couched under this <hi>Petition.</hi> But I <hi>Firſt</hi> premiſe I do by no means deny, but moſt Fully, and Freely Acknowledge; There is a Plain and Manifeſt Intention of <hi>Supplicating God, in this Petition,</hi> for the preſent neceſſities of Life; that they may be Supplied to us accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Food,</hi> that is <hi>Convenient for us;</hi> and in order to our Support for the <hi>Seeking the Eternal Kingdom of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Bread</hi> that <hi>endures</hi> to <hi>Everlaſting Life;</hi> This <hi>our Father knows that we have need of;</hi> So that I do not in the leaſt Impeach any Part of thoſe Exellent, and Profitable Diſcourſes, that have been made upon this <hi>Petition,</hi> in Relation to our depenedncy upon <hi>Providence</hi> for the neceſſaries of Life; or that <hi>Moderation,</hi> and <hi>Contentment,</hi> in what is neceſſary for <hi>the day, without taking Care for To morrow;</hi> Which our <hi>Lord</hi> Annexes to this very <hi>Petition,</hi> after this very <hi>Prayer</hi> there Given.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 6</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>But upon all this, it muſt be Conſidered, and underſtood; that as <hi>our Lord</hi> in declaring <hi>Himſelf the Bread of Life,</hi> and the <hi>Bread from Heaven,</hi> ſerved <hi>Himſelf</hi> of the General <hi>Notion</hi> we have of <hi>Bread,</hi> and of the Uſefulneſs of it to <hi>Life</hi> to convey into our thoughts, and to Raiſe our Hearts to that much more Excellent <hi>Bread;</hi> So under the <hi>Petition for our dayly Bread,</hi> He did intend to lift up our Hearts in <hi>Prayer</hi> for a much Higher Thing; And as in that Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the <hi>Bread of Life,</hi> He did not pull down our value, and eſteem of <hi>Natural Bread</hi> but allowed it; So in the <hi>Petition for a much Higher Bread,</hi> He did not Diſannul <hi>Prayer</hi> for the <hi>Bread of the Day,</hi> but made it the Vehicle of a much Higher <hi>Supplication:</hi> And thoſe very <hi>Words our Bread, and to Day,</hi> and what is <hi>According to the Day,</hi> which ſeem moſt to ſtay our <hi>Thoughts</hi> in the <hi>Bread of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> are alſo moſt Appoſite Conveyances of <hi>our Lords</hi> Great Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
                  <div type="arguments">
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>1</label> 
                        <hi>Our Lord,</hi> Entertains a Large, and Great <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Himſelf,</hi> as the <hi>Bread of Life;</hi> Concerning the <hi>Bread,</hi> that <hi>came down from Heaven;</hi> And that <hi>endures to Everlaſting Life;</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 6.</note> 
                        <hi>Eating His Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>Drinking His Blood;</hi> And that elſe <hi>we have no Life in us,</hi> but that <hi>whoſoever ſo Eateth,</hi> and <hi>Drinketh, Dwelleth in Christ, and Chriſt in him;</hi> and as the <hi>Living Father hath ſent Him, and He Lives by the Father;</hi> So he that <hi>ſo Eateth and Drinketh ſhall Live by Him,</hi> and <hi>He will Raiſe him up at the Laſt day: Our Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares an Eating and Drinking at His Table in His Kingdom;</hi> He hath by His <hi>Servant John</hi> ſett out the <hi>Life of</hi> that <hi>Kingdom</hi> Suſtain'd by a <hi>Tree of Life,</hi> and by a <hi>River Clear, as Chriſtal, Flowing with the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Life;</hi> He hath Appointed that Great <hi>Ordinance of the Lords Supper, till He Comes,</hi> as a <hi>Symbol</hi> of that <hi>Bread,</hi> and <hi>Water of Life</hi>
                        <pb n="43" facs="tcp:105089:26"/> in <hi>His Kingdom.</hi> Can it then be, that in ſo Great an <hi>Inſtitution of Prayer, Comprehenſive</hi> (as I have ſaid) of all the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> and <hi>Word of the Kingdom,</hi> ſo far as it can Fall into <hi>Prayer;</hi> That a <hi>Petition for Bread</hi> ſhould miſs that Supream <hi>Bread</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> ſomuch <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed</hi> in His Word, So promiſed in <hi>His Kingdom,</hi> ſo Repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the <hi>Supper of His Kingdom?</hi> We may be Aſſured, It cannot be; And that therefore this <hi>Bread</hi> muſt be of a Higher Importance than <hi>Natural Bread.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>2</label> Eſpecially <hi>Our Lord</hi> ſets a ſevere Brand in the Expoſition, or diſcourſe after, as upon the Heads of this <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er;</hi> upon too Earneſt Care, and <hi>Seeking, (viz.</hi> by <hi>Prayer,</hi> as <hi>one</hi> way;) <hi>What we ſhall Eat, and Drinck,</hi> &amp;c. and Recommends to <hi>our</hi> Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal <hi>Deſires,</hi> and <hi>Prayers,</hi> the <hi>Kingdom of God,</hi> and the <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it,</hi> as what ſhould be in <hi>our Eye;</hi> And aſſures us that <hi>our Father Knoweth the need we have of Other Things,</hi> and will give them in Courſe, as a <hi>Surpluſage</hi> to thoſe Greater Things: Not that we are <hi>Forbidden to Pray for them</hi> at all, but that they ſhould be the <hi>Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt</hi> of <hi>our Prayers;</hi> And therefore They cannot be the Principal of ſuch a <hi>Petition</hi> as This is: <hi>Our Lord</hi> alſo ſeverely <hi>Reproves</hi> thoſe who <hi>Sought Him,</hi> becauſe they <hi>Eat</hi> even <hi>of His Miraculous Loaves,</hi> and were <hi>Filled;</hi> and directs them <hi>Better, then to Labour for the Meat that Periſheth,</hi> ſetting before them, as was ſaid, <hi>that which Endureth to Eternal Life.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>How then can it be, that this <hi>Bread,</hi> that <hi>periſheth</hi> ſhould take up One, though it be but One <hi>Petition</hi> in this <hi>Prayer,</hi> and it not have a Higher Sence, and Meaning, in a Higher Spirit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Bread,</hi> then <hi>our daily Natural Bread?</hi> Certainly it cannot Be.</p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>3</label> Our <hi>Lord</hi> made choice of ſuch a <hi>Word,</hi> in the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; wherein <hi>He</hi> gave this <hi>Prayer, viz.</hi> that which <hi>Two Inſpired Writers</hi> Uniformly give <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, which moſt <hi>nearly, nextly,</hi> and <hi>naturally</hi> ſignifies, <hi>Super-Eſſential,</hi> or <hi>Super-Subſtantial;</hi> and it <hi>Poſes</hi> and even <hi>Crucifies</hi> Learned Men, when they cannot Acquieſc in that Sence. The very Enquiry therefore after the Sence of a <hi>Word</hi> no where elſe uſed, and the ſo Ready Offer of <hi>Super-Eſſentiality, Super-Subſtantiality</hi> muſt needs perſwade us; Our <hi>Lord</hi> intended the <hi>Bread</hi> that <hi>came down from Heaven,</hi> Eſpecially by this <hi>Super-Eſſential Bread.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">Argum. </seg>4</label> Thoſe Expreſſions, <hi>Our Bread, Bread for to Day,</hi> or that <hi>is according to the Day;</hi> and <hi>daily, or ſucceſſive Bread, from Day</hi>
                        <pb n="44" facs="tcp:105089:27"/> 
                        <hi>to Day,</hi> as ſome underſtand that <hi>Word</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, altho they carry <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of</hi> great <hi>Moderation</hi> to all things in this World, a diligence in calling, and Juſtice, in <hi>Eating our own Bread;</hi> yet they Offer us a much Higher Sence in that <hi>Super-Eſſential Bread,</hi> as that which is much more truely <hi>our own Bread;</hi> That <hi>better part</hi> then <hi>much ſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> about the <hi>Bread</hi> of this World, which ſhall <hi>never be taken from us,</hi> but <hi>Endures to Everlaſting Life.</hi> This is indeed <hi>our own Bread.</hi> And it is indeed <hi>Bread</hi> of a certain Succeſſion, and Sufficiency, as certain, as <hi>Duration</hi> it ſelf; <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Yeſterday</hi> and to <hi>Day,</hi> without a <hi>Tomorrw,</hi> the <hi>Same</hi> for <hi>Ever. Bread of every Day,</hi> Sufficient to it, and of a <hi>certain Succeſſion</hi> in Fulleſt, Trueſt Sence; What They Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly, Carnally <hi>Prayed</hi> for; <hi>Lord evermore give us this Bread;</hi> It is <hi>Evermore given,</hi> it is unto <hi>Eternal Life; He that Eats of it ſhall never Die,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And together with it is given to the Saints, <hi>The Living, The Remaining Saints on the New Earth,</hi> a Sufficiency of all outward En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments, <hi>according to the Day,</hi> without any <hi>Labour or Toyl,</hi> diſtracting their Enjoyment of <hi>God,</hi> and in a certain Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without any <hi>Care,</hi> or <hi>Solicitude,</hi> or taking Thought for <hi>To mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But how can the State of this World Quietly ſubmit to a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency upon <hi>Providence,</hi> according to the <hi>Prayer;</hi> or find the Juſt Temper betwixt that <hi>Providence</hi> for <hi>To morrow,</hi> we look upon as our Duty and the Care, and Immoderate Thoughts for <hi>To morrow</hi> our <hi>Lord</hi> forbids? This World is too Poor, and Indigent, and the Courſe of things too Broken, and Diſorderly to Truſt till <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrow</hi> without Anxieties; Except we had a better <hi>Faith</hi> than the very moſt of <hi>Saints</hi> have here: Nor can this <hi>Bread</hi> be called <hi>Epiouſious, Super-Subſtantial,</hi> or <hi>Eſſential,</hi> or ſo much, as in a kindly Natural Courſe of Succeſſion, without ſomething Parallel to the <hi>Sweat of the Brow:</hi> Or ſo much as <hi>Ours:</hi> Since beſides all other Reaſons, that may be given, which make it too apt to be the <hi>Mammon of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>urighteouſneſs,</hi> It is very often, that while <hi>it is in our Mouth,</hi> the Body, for which it is, and <hi>it Periſh together.</hi> So that this <hi>Petition</hi> in its Juſt <hi>Elevation</hi> of Sence can never be Anſwered, but in the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> which aſſures us; <hi>It is the Prayer of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi> Although it is indeed our Duty, and it ought to be our conſtant <hi>Prayer,</hi> to come as near as we can to the State herein Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported.</p>
                     <p>But we are too much <hi>Gentiles</hi> in this Regard, not only caring Inordinately, but Inordinately Enjoying the World, more than can Conſiſt with the delay <hi>of the Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>His Patience</hi> for it; And as it were to ſhew we are yet in the <hi>Gentiles Times,</hi> our
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:105089:27"/> very Word to expreſs <hi>Splendor of Condition,</hi> and <hi>Affluence,</hi> is taken from Them, even that Word we Rate our ſelves ſo much by: <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile</hi> is taken from the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> By which I intend not to diminiſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing from True Honour, Worth or Accompliſhment, Diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Families, or Perſons; but make a Full Allowance of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> and <hi>Reverence,</hi> to whomſoever <hi>due.</hi> But I cannot but obſerve how <hi>Ominous</hi> a Word we uſe to expreſs theſe Things.</p>
                     <p>But to ſum up All concerning this <hi>Petition:</hi> Seeing the Word we tranſlate <hi>Daily;</hi> hath not ſo much as any Air, Sound, or Breath of <hi>Daily</hi> in it; and that the faireſt Senſe is <hi>Super-Eſſential, Super-Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial,</hi> and that Jeſus Chriſt is Alone that <hi>Bread,</hi> even <hi>that Living Bread,</hi> on which <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> are continually Repaſted; and in Regard of which, <hi>Manna</hi> the <hi>Type</hi> was call'd <hi>Angels Food,</hi> and for which They now ſtoop down to the <hi>Churches Table;</hi> What Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is there to underſtand this <hi>Petition</hi> in its higheſt Elevation, to be for the <hi>Table of the Kingdom,</hi> and the <hi>Bread</hi> ſo <hi>convenient to Immortal Beings?</hi> which the <hi>Innumerable Company of Angels,</hi> together with the <hi>Saints</hi> in the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> eat of, as <hi>of the Tree of Life in the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe of God; and drink of, as of the Chryſtal River Running through the Holy City;</hi> even the <hi>Fruit of his Redemption,</hi> which is indeed in the Beginnings of it participated here below; but is then as a <hi>Paſſover fullfill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d,</hi> and that <hi>Fruit of the Vine drunk New,</hi> in that ſo exalted Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of the Great <hi>Marriage-Supper of the Lamb in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And of this Enjoyment the Saints below have their juſt propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo that they ſhall never <hi>die; The Leaves of the Tree of Life are for the Healing of them,</hi> and the Fruit for ſufficient <hi>Food,</hi> and <hi>They drink of the Water of Life freely,</hi> Running down from the <hi>Holy City,</hi> and <hi>Sanctuary;</hi> So that though they have not an Abſolute <hi>Incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibility,</hi> till they are <hi>caught up,</hi> and put on <hi>Incorruption and Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity;</hi> Yet their <hi>Corruptible,</hi> and <hi>Mortal,</hi> ſhall never <hi>ſee Death,</hi> or <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption:</hi> And as to all Things of the Preſent State, there is by the Divine Benediction, and no Curſe entring, <hi>ſufficient Food,</hi> and <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Clothing;</hi> That is, All that is neceſſary by a Spontaneous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, without their Toyl, or ſo much as Thought for it, <hi>God provides.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And thus in this very <hi>Petition,</hi> Chriſt hath <hi>Spann'd Heaven and Earth with his Hand,</hi> and made it correſpendent to the <hi>Sanctifying the Name of God,</hi> and <hi>doing his Will in his Kingdom</hi> being <hi>come;</hi> and to let us into the Senſe of it, hath choſen a Word of an Extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Key, and that can be no way interpreted to Satisfaction, but into this high Senſe of <hi>Super-Eſſential, Super-Subſtantial.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="petition">
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:105089:28"/>
                  <p> I proceed now to the <hi>Fifth Petition, Forgive us our Trespaſſes, as we forgive Them, that trespaſs againſt us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now This <hi>Petition</hi> alſo, as hath been before obſerved, is a <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition,</hi> that ſhall be heard, as all the <hi>other Petitions</hi> of this <hi>Prayer,</hi> to <hi>Perfection.</hi> It is moſt True, and undoubted, That it carries an high Obligation to mutual <hi>Forgiveneſs,</hi> even now, among all the <hi>Diſciples of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Worſhippers</hi> of him, according to this <hi>Prayer,</hi> he hath <hi>Taught.</hi> But This doth not exclude the higher Predictive Senſe, that is included in the Elevation of this <hi>Petition;</hi> eſpecially becauſe we find ſo low a State of Things, if we meaſure, according to it, whether we conſider the Comfortable Senſe, that the Saints of Chriſt have of their <hi>Sins</hi> being <hi>pardoned by God;</hi> or the Degrees of mutual <hi>Pardon,</hi> Chriſtians are Able to extend one towards another in this Preſent State.</p>
                  <p>There are Three Things therefore, that I will propoſe to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe upon it.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That this <hi>Petition</hi> imports a State of the Higheſt and Fulleſt <hi>Forgiveneſs</hi> of the <hi>Saints of Chriſt,</hi> one towards another; even ſo high, that our <hi>Lord</hi> propoſes it, as the very Standard of the <hi>Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God;</hi> not that it is indeed ſo, but contrary-wiſe; The <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of God</hi> is certainly the <hi>Original Exemplar</hi> of <hi>Pardon,</hi> and the Grand Efficient of it, as it is in his Saints, One to Another.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This <hi>Petition</hi> therefore Declares a <hi>Forgiveneſs,</hi> and <hi>Pardon</hi> from God, to the Higheſt of all our Notions and Sentiments of <hi>Pardon,</hi> that either we can deſire from, or yield one to another; which is one main Reaſon of our Saviour's Teaching us the Deſire of <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs</hi> from <hi>God,</hi> as we <hi>Forgive;</hi> That is, to the <hi>Heighth</hi> and <hi>Depth,</hi> to the <hi>Breadth and Length</hi> of all our Conceptions of <hi>Pardon;</hi> and alſo, as we learn from <hi>Scripture,</hi> much <hi>above,</hi> and <hi>beyond what we can know, ask or think.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. When we compare this <hi>Prayer</hi> with <hi>Scripture,</hi> in its whole Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, which (as I have ſaid) is the True Expoſition of it; and with the Height of <hi>Prophetical Scripture,</hi> in this Point of <hi>Reconciliation;</hi> we find, It ſhall be of <hi>All Things in H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aven and Earth,</hi> or of the <hi>Creatures</hi> among themſelves, or of the <hi>whole Creation,</hi> in all the Parts of it, one with another.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. I begin with the Firſt, wherein <hi>our Lord</hi> appears to have Given us as a Key, a private Key, That this is the <hi>Prayer of his Kingdom;</hi> viz. That he <hi>Teaches us to pray,</hi> that we may be <hi>forgiven,</hi> even as <hi>we</hi>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:105089:28"/> 
                     <hi>Forgive;</hi> or, as it is ſaid in <hi>Luke, For we alſo forgive.</hi> I do not at all doubt, as I have already declared on All Accounts and ſo on this but that our Lord did hereby <hi>Teach</hi> the Great Duty of Mutual <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs;</hi> and that the Expoſitory Diſcourſes upon this <hi>Petition,</hi> are of Great Weight and Moment, and of mighty preſſing Obligation to all ſuch Mutual <hi>Forgiveneſs.</hi> But I do only endeavour to ſhew, They do not reach the Heighth of this <hi>Petition;</hi> And therefore on Two Grounds I would diſcourſe this, as the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom, upon this Petition.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. That the very mention of <hi>Forgiveneſs</hi> one of another, does im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port an high State of our Mutual <hi>Forgiveneſs:</hi> For the <hi>Petition</hi> does intend not only a <hi>Prayer,</hi> that God would <hi>forgive,</hi> as we <hi>forgive;</hi> but alſo a <hi>Prayer,</hi> that we may <hi>forgive,</hi> ſo as we deſire to be <hi>forgiven of God.</hi> For a Duty ſo much above <hi>Fleſh and Blood,</hi> and alſo ſo contrary to <hi>Fleſh and Blood,</hi> how can we preſume upon in our own ſtrength; without Prayer for it, in the very mention of it included: For elſe the Words wauld be, as if we Vyed with God in the Magnanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Pardon,</hi> and deſir'd him to take Pattern by us, and to <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rgive us;</hi> For we are able to <hi>forgive thoſe who are indebted to us.</hi> Whereas we know, and Scripture ſo makes plain to us: <hi>God is He to whom none is like, in pardoning Iniquity, Tranſgreſſion and Sin.</hi> And indeed none can Forgive at all, but God principally and primarily; becauſe every <hi>Sin againſt Men,</hi> is firſt <hi>againſt Him,</hi> and a <hi>Victation of his Order and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> of the World: And therefore <hi>David,</hi> when he had ſinned ſubordinately againſt the Honour of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi>'s <hi>Bed,</hi> and againſt his <hi>Life,</hi> yet confeſſes, <hi>Againſt Thee, Againſt Thee only have I ſinned:</hi> Not as many would take it, eztolling his Kingly Power and Supremacy, but <hi>acknowledging God's Original Right over All Things,</hi> and that Sin is ſo <hi>againſt Him,</hi> that he hath a Supreme Right of <hi>pardoning,</hi> without the <hi>Conſent</hi> of the <hi>offended Creature;</hi> although it be both the Duty of the <hi>Offending to Ask,</hi> and of the <hi>offended Creature to Grant that Pardon;</hi> And that is, becauſe both the <hi>Offending</hi> and the <hi>Offended</hi> are his.</p>
                  <p>But not inſiſting upon our <hi>forgiving,</hi> as being intended by way of <hi>Petition,</hi> but only as a <hi>Condition of, and Qualification for Divine Pardon:</hi> Yet ſeeing <hi>Gods forgiveneſs</hi> of us, we deſire, ſhould be to the heighth; There muſt be a Time, when our <hi>forgiving one another</hi> ſhall be at ſuch a <hi>Heighth,</hi> that it may be the Glory of that State; that <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs of one another,</hi> and alſo <hi>Forgiveneſs from God</hi> to us; may be at a heighth; becauſe this Prayer does in every thing, imply the higheſt Senſes, and therefore muſt have an Anſwer to a heighth: So on all Accounts there muſt be a Time of God's <hi>forgiving us,</hi> and our <hi>forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of one another,</hi> at the heighth; and the Latter muſt be ſuch, that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:105089:29"/> it may declare, and diſplay the Glory of the Former; or elſe <hi>This Prayer</hi> does not Attain its End.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Indeed <hi>Our Forgivneſs</hi> of one Another is now ſo low, that if it ſhould be the Meaſure in any Sence of <hi>Gods Forgiving us;</hi> the Beſt, and the moſt Charitable would want a plenary <hi>Pardon,</hi> if ſo Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured out to Them; I ſhould <hi>deſire</hi> in the Behalf of Thoſe, who <hi>Forgive</hi> moſt Clearly, They ſhould yet be in a Higher Meaſure <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given of God,</hi> then They <hi>Forgive.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The beſt Men have too great Tinctures of the Sence of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury of others againſt them, Remaining upon their Spirits; and eſpecially according to the Comprehenſive Word here Choſen by <hi>Chriſt; Debts;</hi> that is; either what we call ſtrictly <hi>Debts,</hi> or are Reall, and Subſtantial <hi>Wrongs;</hi> Who comes up to <hi>Forgive,</hi> as They deſire to be <hi>Forgiven of God?</hi> That All ſhould be <hi>Blotted out</hi> and <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given,</hi> as if it had <hi>never been;</hi> And that it is ſo Perfectly Taken away by <hi>Forgiveneſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> that tho it be <hi>Sought for,</hi> it cannot be <hi>Found:</hi> And not only ſo, but the Offending, and Indebted Perſon Received into Eſpecial Favour: According to the State of Things now, even to thoſe we Account Good Men, this <hi>Petition</hi> were rather an <hi>Imprecation,</hi> than a <hi>Petition.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If we ſhould endeavour to Qualify the <hi>Petition,</hi> as It ſeems to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend <hi>Gods Forgiveneſs</hi> upon ours, with the Sence; in our Degree, and with Sincerity, tho not to <hi>Perfection;</hi> Even as we are Commanded to be <hi>Merciful, as God is Merciful;</hi> I do Acknowledg It may give ſome Satisfaction, as to the <hi>Time being,</hi> and till that great <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>All Things,</hi> even that of <hi>Reſtitution;</hi> Or elſe <hi>we were All</hi> moſt <hi>Miſerable.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But ſeeing there is a State much Higher both of our <hi>Pardon</hi> from <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Forgiveneſs</hi> to one another; And that I have ſo often Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, and it cannot but be yeilded; That this <hi>Prayer,</hi> that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> hath <hi>Taught,</hi> muſt Reach to the very Heighth of Things in every Part of it; And it is to be Expounded according to the <hi>whole Word of God.</hi> Let us therefore inquire by the Second Particular for that much Higher State of <hi>Gods Forgiveneſs,</hi> and of the <hi>Saints Forgiveneſs one of anothor,</hi> wherein theſe Things ſhall be Convertible, and Turn Round upon one another; we <hi>ſhall Forgive one another</hi> to that <hi>Perfection,</hi> that <hi>Gods Forgiveneſs,</hi> Reſerving to it only the difference between a <hi>Finite,</hi> and an <hi>Infinite Forgiver,</hi> and Reſerving to <hi>Gods Forgiveneſs</hi> alſo the <hi>Exemplarineſs,</hi> and alſo the <hi>Efficiency</hi> of our <hi>Forgiving;</hi> and <hi>Gods Forgiveneſs</hi> ſhall be according to the <hi>Forgiveneſs,</hi> the <hi>full Forgiveneſs of the Saints, Forgiveneſs one of another;</hi> That is, the G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ory and perfection of <hi>Gods Forgiveneſs</hi> ſhall be ſeen in our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of <hi>Forgiveing one another,</hi> as in this Mirror and Reflection;
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:105089:29"/> And therefore the <hi>Petition</hi> is ſo Framed on purpoſe to Leade us to that State of the <hi>Kingdom.</hi> For that very End the Lower, and the Leſſer Thing, the Copy, and the Reflection is given, as the Meaſure of the Higher, and the Greater, and the Original; For if that be ſo Glorious as to be made, as it were, the Exemplar, and Original, how much more Glorious is that Exemplar and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal it ſelf? And that the Reflection and Mirror of <hi>Gods Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, viz.</hi> our <hi>Forgivneſs of one another is</hi> ſo Dark now; It aſſuers, there ſhall, and muſt be a Time, that the Original ſhall be more Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in the Manifeſtation of it ſelf, that the Mirror and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection may be more Glorious; And becauſe it ſhall be ſo Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, therefore the <hi>Manifeſtation</hi> of the <hi>Original</hi> ſhall be more Glorious alſo <hi>Firſt;</hi> All which I will Repreſent in theſe Two Particulars.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The State of the <hi>Saints,</hi> ſhall be a State of the moſt perfect Purity, from all Remaining <hi>Stains</hi> of Sin, in Regard of the Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Divine Pardon and Forgiveneſs;</hi> Then to the Height of all Underſtanding Their <hi>Sins ſhall be Blotted out,</hi> when theſe Times of <hi>New Life, and Reſtitution ſhall come from the Preſence of the Lord;</hi> and They ſhall be Preſented before the <hi>Eyes of His Glory without Fault, Spot, or Wrinkle or any ſuch thing; Their Robes being waſhed White in the Blood of the Lamb,</hi> and being Arrayed in Linen <hi>White,</hi> and <hi>Clean,</hi> and <hi>Cloathed in Change of Raiment,</hi> all which expreſs the <hi>Righteouſneſs of the Saints:</hi> That State therefore Commenſurate here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto is inwardly full of all <hi>Joy</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> in <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly of all <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Happineſs:</hi> when the <hi>effects</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> ſhall be <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Aſſurance for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. That this may be; There cannot be any thing upon the <hi>Breaſts</hi> of <hi>Saints</hi> Remaining, one towards another, that ſhall Recall or give any Remembrances of their former Tranſgreſſions, or Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Reſentments, one towards another; For this muſt need be a Shade and Cloud upon that Glorious and Happy State, altogether both Unbeſeeming, and Unſuitable to it.</p>
                  <p>For the <hi>Infinite Riches of Grace</hi> in the <hi>Pardon of Sin,</hi> through the <hi>Blood and Redemption of Chriſt</hi> ſo fully ſet out in Glory Operates, both as an <hi>Exemplar</hi> to which the <hi>Saints</hi> are Conformed in Relation to one another; and by way of Sweeteſt Efficient Attempering them in Higheſt <hi>Love</hi> to and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> one with another; and that Sence they have of the Full, Abſolute <hi>Forgiveneſs, Love</hi> to, and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> one with another, is an Inward Pledg and Experiment of the <hi>Power of Forgiveneſs in God</hi> and of the High Nature of it; So that the <hi>Sainte</hi> have Knowledg of Divine <hi>Forgiveneſs</hi> in themſelves by their
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:105089:30"/> own <hi>Forgiveneſs,</hi> One of Another; And therefore Chriſt was pleaſed ſo to put it, <hi>Forgive us, as we Forgive.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. As a further Luſtre of that State; As the <hi>Angels</hi> ſhall be Full of <hi>Love,</hi> and the <hi>Amneſty</hi> and <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Supream Grace</hi> ſhall take all our Former ſins out of their Remembrances; So the very Enmity of the <hi>Creatures,</hi> towards us, and among themſelves, of the <hi>Wolf</hi> and of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> of the <hi>Lyon</hi> and of the <hi>Kid,</hi> of the <hi>Child,</hi> and of the <hi>Aſp,</hi> ſhall be Reconciled; and the <hi>Antipathies</hi> and <hi>Offenſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of their Natures and all <hi>Obnoxiouſneſs</hi> Cancell'd; And <hi>Duſt</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone ſhall be the <hi>Serpents</hi> Meat. For as the <hi>God of Peace and Order,</hi> will <hi>Reconcile All Things in Heaven,</hi> and <hi>Earth by Christ, even by Chriſt to Himſelf;</hi> So will He <hi>Reconcile</hi> them All one to another; Yea the very <hi>Elements,</hi> and moſt Inſenſible <hi>Creatures,</hi> the <hi>Heavens ſhall Hear the Earth,</hi> and the <hi>Earth all, that is upon it;</hi> and the <hi>Stones of the Field</hi> ſhall be in the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and <hi>League of Amity,</hi> that ſhall not be Violated, Infringed, or Diſſolved; And all this we <hi>Pray</hi> for in the Higheſt Sence of this <hi>Prayer;</hi> which muſt needs therefore be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe theſe are the Higheſt Expreſſions of <hi>Scripture,</hi> concerning this <hi>Forgiveneſi</hi> ſo Univerſal; And therefore they muſt be within the <hi>Prayer,</hi> the Great <hi>Mediator</hi> hath Taught; And therefore It muſt needs be the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom,</hi> when there ſhall be no <hi>Hurting, nor Deſtroying</hi> in all the <hi>Holy Mountain of God;</hi> For <hi>Knowledg of God</hi> and of <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall <hi>Cover the Earth, as the Waters do the Sea.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="petition">
                  <p>Let us now move on to the <hi>Sixth Petition; Lead us not into Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation:</hi> And here again I Premiſe, I Derogate nothing from the <hi>Holy, Wiſe, Serious,</hi> and <hi>Spiritual</hi> Diſcourſes upon the General Sence of the <hi>Words, Lead us not into Temptation.</hi> But ſeeing the Fundamental Rule I have laid Down int he Expounding this <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> is, that it takes in the Whole Sence of <hi>Scripture,</hi> ſo far as it can Fall into <hi>Prayer,</hi> and eſpecially the Higheſt Sence of it; whatever we can find to be the Higheſt Sence of <hi>Scripture</hi> Concerning Freedom from <hi>Temptation,</hi> muſt needs be alſo the Higheſt Sence of this <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now the Higheſt Freedom from <hi>Temptation,</hi> the <hi>Scripture</hi> declares to us, muſt lie in the Conſidering the things wherein the <hi>Power of Temptation</hi> ſtands, and finding the Door, as I may ſo Speak, ſhut upon them all; That we cannot <hi>Enter into Temptation,</hi> and ſo not be Led into it. And there are theſe Four things Conſpiring in <hi>Temptation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:105089:30"/> 1. There is that, either Weakneſs, Unconfirmedneſs, and Lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility, that was in <hi>Adam</hi> before his <hi>Fall;</hi> or that Inward Luſt in Depraved, Corrupted <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> of which a <hi>Man is drawn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> and <hi>enticed,</hi> when <hi>He is Tempted.</hi> And without one of Theſe, no <hi>Temptation</hi> can take, but as Chriſt ſpeaks, <hi>The Prince of this World comes,</hi> and hath <hi>nothing in me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. There is that <hi>Pabulum,</hi> the Food and Fewel of <hi>Temptation,</hi> by way of Object; and that is, <hi>All that is in the World, the Luſt of the Fleſh, the Luſt of the Eye, and the Pride of Life.</hi> This State of the World made <hi>Subject to Vanity,</hi> and in <hi>Bondage to Corruption</hi> is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, and prepar'd to draw out the Luſt of <hi>Man's Fleſh</hi> in <hi>Senſuality;</hi> the <hi>Luſt of the Eye</hi> in coveting the Appearance of Riches, Splendor or Glory; or the inward <hi>Pride,</hi> and ſwelling of Conceit and Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, that ariſes from any of theſe things, come into our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment and Poſſeſſion; without which <hi>Humane Temptation</hi> would be ineffectual.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. There is the mighty Agent and Efficient of <hi>Temptation,</hi> the <hi>Devil,</hi> and <hi>Sathan,</hi> the <hi>Old Serpent, the Lyar from the Beginning,</hi> who is therefore call'd <hi>The Tempter;</hi> without whom the higheſt Notion of <hi>Temptation</hi> would ceaſe; and All <hi>Sin</hi> would be only that Ebulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Riſing up of <hi>Luſt</hi> within, which the <hi>Apoſtle James, ſpeaking</hi> More Generally, and Improperly, calls <hi>Temptation;</hi> And together with him, are to be accounted <hi>All Wicked Men, his Seed:</hi> And even Good Men Acted by him, are called <hi>Sathan,</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> by Chriſt, when he ſpake, as it were, from him.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. There is the <hi>Supreme, Holy, Righteous Judge, Governour and Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruler of Temptation,</hi> who <hi>cannot be Tempted of Evil,</hi> neither <hi>Tempteth he any Man;</hi> Yet He is ſaid to <hi>Lead into Temptation,</hi> when He permits us to <hi>enter into Temptation;</hi> And if he Leaves us in it, we Fall, and plunge down into it: But when he ſupports us in it, we overcome and bear up aloft and above it: And this Temptation he ſuffered at firſt upon Man, before <hi>Confirmation by the Second Adam;</hi> and then he ſuffered it to Ruſh out in Greateſt Abundance, and Prevalency, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Great Diſloyalty and <hi>Diſobedience of his Sin.</hi> Thus God ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prevents, or over-rules through Infinite Grace in the <hi>Second A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> that we either enter not into it, or <hi>fall not in it;</hi> and he at laſt puts an end to that permiſſive <hi>Leading into Temptation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For when there ſhall be the higheſt and fulleſt Anſwer of this <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, Lead us not into Temptation;</hi> there ſhall be ſo high a Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Saints in Holineſs, that <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>Lamb</hi> ſhall be their <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Temple,</hi> their <hi>Tree</hi> and <hi>Water of Life,</hi> that they ſhall <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> and <hi>Thirſt</hi> after any thing elſe no more; but the <hi>Lamb</hi> ſhall be <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Leading them</hi> to the <hi>Green Paſtures,</hi> and to the <hi>Fountains of Living</hi>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:105089:31"/> 
                     <hi>Water.</hi> What then can <hi>Temptation</hi> find in them, which always ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes from <hi>Luſt,</hi> or Deſire of ſomething that God hath not Thought Good for us? As <hi>His Servants</hi> therefore <hi>we ſerve Him,</hi> having <hi>His Name in our Foreheads,</hi> Prieſts in the <hi>Robes waſhed in his Blood,</hi> and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his <hi>Face always;</hi> and nothing that <hi>Defiles,</hi> and <hi>makes a Lye, can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> How then can there be any <hi>Leading into Temptation?</hi> And as this is the State of the <hi>New Jeruſalem abovè,</hi> ſo is that <hi>below,</hi> as to all Aſcertaining Influences; However, there is, as to the <hi>Saints below,</hi> not an <hi>Abſolute Incorruption,</hi> or <hi>Immortality;</hi> yet ſo, that whatever doth <hi>Live, ſhall Live, and they ſhall not Die;</hi> For they are <hi>Chang'd and Heal'd</hi> by the <hi>Leaves of the Tree of Life,</hi> and <hi>walk in the Light of the</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem <hi>above,</hi> and <hi>drink of the Water of Life freely,</hi> above Temptation.</p>
                  <p>And then the <hi>Reſtored Creation</hi> ſhall be no more in <hi>Bondage to Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,</hi> or to <hi>Luſt,</hi> under which it hath ſo long <hi>Travail'd</hi> and <hi>Groan'd,</hi> as under an intollerable <hi>Burthen;</hi> for then it being <hi>deliver'd</hi> into the <hi>Manifeſtation</hi> of the <hi>Glorious Liberty of the Children of God, Righteouſneſs</hi> Alone ſhall <hi>dwell in</hi> it, and make uſe of it Alone. It ſhall yield no Motion of Deſire, nor to any ſuch Motion, but of the <hi>Glory of God.</hi> It ſhall offer nothing, it ſhall receive nothing of the <hi>Luſt of the Fleſh,</hi> the <hi>Luſt of the Eye,</hi> or <hi>the Pride of Life.</hi> There ſhall be no more <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting Adultery with the Love of this World:</hi> There ſhall be only a moſt Holy and Pure Uſe of all the Creatures: So that in this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard alſo, there ſhall be no <hi>Leading into Temptation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That <hi>Great Negotiator,</hi> and <hi>Super-Intendent of Temptation, Sathan,</hi> ſhall be <hi>Seal'd up,</hi> and <hi>Chain'd,</hi> that he ſhall <hi>deceive the Nations no more,</hi> for a 1000 years; and when they are <hi>expir'd,</hi> he hath the Freedom but of one fruitleſs, unſucceſsful Effort, and that but for a <hi>ſmall moment,</hi> and he is <hi>thrown</hi> for ever <hi>into the Lake,</hi> to <hi>Deceive no more for ever</hi> And <hi>Evil Men are conſumed out of the Earth,</hi> who joyn with <hi>Sathan</hi> in <hi>Tempting;</hi> And <hi>Sinners are no more,</hi> but in ſuch a State of <hi>Death and Horror,</hi> as not to <hi>Tempt,</hi> but to be only an <hi>Abhorring of All Fleſh.</hi> And Good Men being in ſuch a State, that they cannot be <hi>Tempted of Evil,</hi> ſo neither can they <hi>Tempt any.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Laſtly,</hi> All this proceeds from the <hi>Infinite Grace of God,</hi> and of <hi>the Lamh,</hi> who having their <hi>Tabernacle with Men,</hi> God ſhall Gather his Servants with <hi>Everlaſting Loving Kindneſs,</hi> ſhall <hi>Gather into One Head,</hi> and ſhall <hi>Reconcile All Things to Himſelf by Him,</hi> even <hi>by Him;</hi> and <hi>in</hi> and <hi>by Him</hi> they ſtand <hi>Reconcil'd,</hi> and for ever Confirm'd in a <hi>Reconciled State;</hi> ſo that <hi>Temptation</hi> ſhall no more be permitted by Him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="petition">
                  <p>And this I look upon to be the Expoſition of this Great <hi>Petition,</hi> at its higheſt Elevation. And ſo let us come to the Laſt <hi>Petition, But deliver us from all Evil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:105089:31"/>
                  <p> This <hi>Petition, Deliver us from Evil,</hi> is by the <hi>Conjunction,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or <hi>But;</hi> a <hi>Particle,</hi> that joyns as a <hi>Conjunction,</hi> and yet diſtinguiſhes as a <hi>Diſcretive,</hi> ſo <hi>Lincked</hi> with the Former; <hi>Lead us not into Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> that it hath been Generally looked upon, as but One <hi>Petition:</hi> But both in Regard of the Relation of the <hi>Septenary</hi> Number to the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> And in Regard of the Diſ-union of that Diſ-cretive <hi>Particle</hi> I look upon them as <hi>Two.</hi> And as they are ſo joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and diſtinguiſhed, we may be guided by the very Obſervation to the Sence.</p>
                  <p>For the General Notion of <hi>Temptation</hi> looks <hi>Two</hi> Ways; It looks to the Enticement, and Allurements of <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> or the things we deſire; which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> calls <hi>Luſt;</hi> And on the other ſide, It looks to the Evil of <hi>Perſecution,</hi> and all kinds of the <hi>Fiery Tryal,</hi> or <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction,</hi> or what ever in General of Evil we Fear, and fly from; So the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> calls <hi>Manifold Temptations; My Brethren, count it all joy, when ye fall into divers Temptations. And Bleſſed is the Man, that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth Temptation; And God is Faithful, and will not ſuffer you</hi> to <hi>be Tempted above what you are Able to Bear,</hi> meaning of Affliction, <hi>but</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jam.</hi> 1. 2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>will with the Temptation make you a way of Eſcape.</hi> Thus on the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Evil, and Fear coming upon them, at the Time of <hi>His Suffering; Our Lord warns His Apoſtles to Watch, and Pray;</hi> That they may not <hi>Enter into Temptation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now our <hi>Lord</hi> having taken care in the Firſt of theſe <hi>Two Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> of what Concerns the <hi>Smoother,</hi> and more <hi>Oyly</hi> part of <hi>Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> that we ſhould not be <hi>Led into it;</hi> In this Latter <hi>Petition</hi> He takes Care againſt the <hi>Rougher,</hi> and more <hi>Formidable</hi> Part, that Affrights us, and Scares from that Duty, and Station, wherein we ought to ſtand Faſt, that we might avoid ſuch, or ſuch Evils; or by Reaſon of which we are diſpirited, and <hi>Faint in our minds;</hi> or that by any Impreſſion diſſits or diſadvantages, in holding a Cloſe Communion with God, or abates the <hi>Honour,</hi> or <hi>Glory</hi> of our Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to Him, Becauſe we want what is neceſſary, for the moſt <hi>Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious</hi> management or it. For we know, that low State of Things, that abundant of Evil by way of Punniſhment, or Affliction, that is in the world, however It may be more Acceptable to God to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover Sincerity, and other Graces; Yet it Clouds and Darkens the <hi>Splendor of Religion,</hi> and it is not the State, the <hi>Holy, Wiſe,</hi> and <hi>Good Creator</hi> deſigned things at <hi>Firſt</hi> for; Nor that They ſhould ſo continue, though for a Time His Srength may be thus <hi>Manifeſted in our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that though, I ſhall not in the Leaſt, Queſtion, but that the <hi>Petition</hi> may Import deliverance from the <hi>Evil of Temptation,</hi> while we are in the Preſent State; yet that the Heighth, and <hi>Elevation</hi> of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:105089:32"/> it Intends the Deliverance of the Servants of Chriſt, from all the Diſadvantages upon any Account whatſoever, they Receive, or may Receive from All, or any of the various Kinds, or Forms of Natural <hi>Evils;</hi> of thoſe <hi>Evils</hi> which we call the <hi>Evil</hi> of <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> and of <hi>Affliction</hi> in the World; which are ſo from the want of ſuch a plentifull; and Happy State, that might more Encourage and Raiſe our <hi>Spirits,</hi> and the Honour of the <hi>Kingdom of God in this World;</hi> and that upon theſe <hi>Two</hi> Accounts.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Becauſe it cannot agree with the <hi>Holineſs, Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God,</hi> and the <hi>Glory</hi> of His own <hi>Perfection,</hi> and <hi>Happineſs,</hi> that there ſhould laſt always ſuch a Dark ſhade upon the Great <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick</hi> of Things, ſuch a <hi>Diſorder and Confuſion</hi> in His <hi>Creation</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> of the World, as we now ſee, But that All ſhould come into a State of Perfect <hi>Light, Peace, Order,</hi> and <hi>Happineſs,</hi> as that wherein Himſelf, the only <hi>Wiſe,</hi> and <hi>Happy Potentate</hi> Dwells.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Becauſe the Deſcription of the Laſt State of Things is ſuch, as does declare ſuch a <hi>Deliverance from the whole Power of Evil,</hi> viz. of <hi>Affliction</hi> or <hi>Puniſhment;</hi> Both as in the want of <hi>Good,</hi> and the preſſure of <hi>Evil;</hi> and this we find both in the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and more Fully and together in the <hi>Revelation;</hi> For <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 4. <hi>God ſhall wipe away all Tears from the Eyes of His Servants, and there ſhall be no more Death, neither Sorrow, nor Crying, neither ſhall there be any more pain;</hi> For <hi>all the former Things are paſt away.</hi> And <hi>Chap.</hi> 22. 3. <hi>There ſhall be no more Curſe; And there is a City of Gold and Pearl;</hi> and <hi>the Glory of God and the Lamb</hi> are its ſo <hi>Supream Lights,</hi> that there ſhall be No need of the <hi>Sun;</hi> and the <hi>Tree of Life</hi> with its <hi>Twelve</hi> Kinds of Fruit are in <hi>the Middeſt of it,</hi> and <hi>the River of the Water of Life, Clear as Chriſtal</hi> Run through it; and <hi>the Throne of God,</hi> and <hi>of the Lamb,</hi> are the never Failing <hi>Splendor of it:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now ſeeing there is ſuch a State, as this in the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> how can we think it Poſſible, ſo <hi>great a Petition of ſo great a Prayer</hi> ſhould leave it out, that is ſo Admirably prepared to Expreſs it? as this <hi>Deliver us from Evil,</hi> or from <hi>the Evil,</hi> viz. from the Whole Nature of <hi>Evil,</hi> of the <hi>Evil of Miſery, and of Affliction,</hi> and that <hi>Low, Poor, Indigent</hi> State; wherein we can ſet out nothing <hi>Splendidly</hi> for our <hi>God,</hi> and in our way of Service, and Honour to Him in His Worſhip or in Obedience to His Commands, and Conformity to <hi>Himſelf;</hi> but we are Enſnared with Fears, Amazed with Terrors, Diſcouraged by Want, kept down with Preſſures; This is the <hi>Evil</hi> in this <hi>Petition, Our Lord Teaches us to Pray for Deliverance</hi> from, <hi>as that Black, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal, and Terrible ſide of Temptation.</hi> Which is the <hi>Curſe,</hi> that ſhall be <hi>no more</hi> in <hi>His Kingdom.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:105089:32"/>
               <p> There now remains only the Conſideration of <hi>our Lord's Manner</hi> of Summing up of <hi>this Prayer,</hi> which is ſo done, that it Appears with a Threefold Aſpect.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It looks back upon the whole <hi>Prayer,</hi> by way of Recollective Argument, and Enforcement of it in every part, as it is the <hi>Prayer</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It particularly indents and entwines it ſelf with the Laſt <hi>Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Deliver us from Evil,</hi> as the moſt ſenſible, to us now, Character of the <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Under the cloſe Conveyance of the Argument, enforcing to the hearing of the whole, and every part, and <hi>Petition of this Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er;</hi> it falls into the Great <hi>Doxology</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> which however it is always due to God, yet is in its higheſt Senſe, and Elevation the <hi>Doxology</hi> proper to the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and which argues this <hi>Prayer</hi> to be the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Argument looking back upon the whole <hi>Prayer</hi> may be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood theſe Three ways:</p>
               <p n="1">1. All theſe <hi>Petitions</hi> are thus Argued to be well Founded upon greateſt Equity, Truth, and Righteouſneſs, in Two Regards.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Such High Deſires, and <hi>Petitions</hi> were moſt Abominable and Sacrilegious, if They were not Offered and Addreſſed to Him, whoſe is the <hi>Power,</hi> and the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and the <hi>Glory.</hi> For All the Things deſired in this <hi>Prayer,</hi> He Alone is worthy to be prayed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to for them, whoſe is the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and the <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>the Glory,</hi> even <hi>for ever and ever.</hi> And it were to make a <hi>God</hi> of him, who is <hi>no God,</hi> to offer them by way of <hi>Prayer</hi> to Any other; to <hi>Make a Falſe God,</hi> and to cloath him with the <hi>Majeſty and Greatneſs</hi> that is None of His, but is peculiar to Him, who is <hi>God Alone,</hi> and there is <hi>None be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Him;</hi> There is not any <hi>Other;</hi> and ſo it is a ſtrong Bar to <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints,</hi> for any of the Things laid up in this <hi>Prayer,</hi> which are indeed All things, that according to the Word of God fall into <hi>Prayer.</hi> To offer them to any other, is both Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge and Idolatry; and therefore it is ſo to <hi>pray</hi> Religiouſly to Any other, becauſe all <hi>Holy Prayer</hi> is Treaſur'd in them. And they were alſo moſt Fooliſh, Vain, and to no purpoſe, to be offer'd to any other, even as if they were offered to a Fly, or a Glod of Earth, in compariſon; who are ſo far from being Able to Grant ſuch Things, that they cannot in the leaſt underſtand Them. No more in the main, is any <hi>Power</hi> Able, below His, whoſe is the <hi>Kingdom,</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:105089:33"/> 
                  <hi>the Power, and the Glory,</hi> to bring forth theſe <hi>Petitions</hi> in their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In regard, that He, whoſe is the <hi>Kingdom, the Power, and the Glory,</hi> will <hi>Take to Himſelf his Great Power,</hi> and <hi>Reign;</hi> Theſe <hi>Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> are well Grounded, and well Addreſs'd to him. For ſeeing the Things are ſo high, that though the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and the <hi>Power,</hi> and the <hi>Glory,</hi> are always God's, yet Theſe <hi>Petitions</hi> have not yet been Anſwered, nor theſe Great Things come into Effect: The <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions</hi> would not be well Grounded, if there were not a Time, He would thus <hi>Take to himſelf his Great Power,</hi> and <hi>Reign.</hi> For if the World continued never ſo long, and that the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> were in all the Right of them, Gods; yet theſe Things <hi>Pray'd for,</hi> would, for all that, never be fullfill'd. So that they muſt have been either laid lower, or have been in vain.</p>
               <p>As therefore (as <hi>Scripture</hi> hath fully declar'd) there is a Time God will Take to Himſelf his Great Power, and Reign; ſo theſe very Petitions are fram'd to ſuch an Altitude, to ſuch a Supreme Pitch; And becauſe they cloſe with this as an Argument, That God's is the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and the <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> and that for <hi>Ever and Ever;</hi> They become a certain Aſſurance, That theſe Petitions are well Grounded, and well Addreſs'd; and that though they do not Appear ſo yet, in Regard of their being Fullfill'd; yet that they ſhall Appear ſo at the Time of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and of <hi>God's taking to Himſelf the Power,</hi> and the <hi>Glory;</hi> And that certainly there ſhall be ſuch a Time, wherein the <hi>Kingdom of God</hi> ſhall be, and All Theſe Things Fullfill'd in it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As Theſe Things cannot be, till the <hi>Kingdom</hi> be; ſo on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, the <hi>Kingdom</hi> cannot be, till theſe Things are. A <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and a <hi>Power,</hi> and a <hi>Glory,</hi> God always hath. But this <hi>Kingdom</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Appear, nor the <hi>Power,</hi> and the <hi>Glory</hi> be ſeen to be God's, till his <hi>Name be Sanctified,</hi> his <hi>Will done, as in Heaven,</hi> and <hi>upon Earth;</hi> Till he ſhews his Grace to his Servants, in giving them the <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantial Bread, according to the Day,</hi> or in a <hi>Perpetuity:</hi> Till he <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciles</hi> All to <hi>Himſelf, in Heaven and Earth, by Him,</hi> even <hi>by Him;</hi> and till he ſets wholly free <hi>from Temptation,</hi> and <hi>Delivers from Evil</hi> all the Subjects of <hi>his Kingdom.</hi> And All theſe are the <hi>Coming of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Therefore by the way of ſo Cloſe a Conjunction, and Union of theſe Two, our Saviour declares this <hi>Prayer</hi> to be the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom;</hi> And that as the <hi>Kingdom</hi> is the Great Senſe, Mind and Spirit of this <hi>Prayer;</hi> ſo that it can never be aright <hi>prayed,</hi> nor is <hi>heard,</hi> ſo as to be Anſwer'd. till this <hi>Kingdom come:</hi> So that the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:105089:33"/> ſhall certainly <hi>come,</hi> in Anſwer to this <hi>Prayer,</hi> and in Anſwer to every Petition of it: Every Thing in it ſhall be done, becauſe <hi>God's is the Kingdom, and the Power, and the Glory, for Ever and Ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. This <hi>Doxology</hi> is moſt immediately Linck'd with that Laſt <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, Deliverance from Evil;</hi> to ſhew both the Inconſiſtency of the <hi>Divine Kingdom,</hi> in its <hi>Glory and Coming</hi> with a State of <hi>Evil,</hi> even of the Evil of <hi>Affliction, Pain,</hi> and <hi>Miſery:</hi> So that it is the <hi>Laſt Enemy ſubdued,</hi> by the <hi>Divine Kingdom;</hi> that is, the <hi>Divine Kingdom</hi> Alone can <hi>ſubdue</hi> it, and only when it <hi>Appears,</hi> and not before. But when it Appears, it ſhall be perfectly remov'd. And our Lord takes the Advantage at that very Time, and in that Order, to preſs and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low home the whole by the Argumentative <hi>Doxology, For thine is the Kingdom:</hi> And therefore Thou art Able, and wilt <hi>Deliver from Evil,</hi> by that <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> which is thy <hi>own,</hi> and at the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of thy own <hi>Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Under the <hi>Doxology</hi> conveyed by way of Argument, This is to be Acknowledg'd; That a conſtant <hi>Offering</hi> up to God in a way of <hi>Praiſe,</hi> and <hi>Adoration</hi> this <hi>Confeſſion;</hi> That, <hi>His is the Kingdom,</hi> the <hi>Power,</hi> and the <hi>Glory;</hi> is moſt due to Him from us, in all our <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> and <hi>Supplications</hi> to him. But yet the higheſt Senſe of this <hi>Doxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy</hi> is proper to the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and Argues the <hi>Prayer</hi> to be the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom.</hi> For ſeeing our <hi>Lord</hi> hath put this <hi>Doxology</hi> into our Mouths, That <hi>His is the Kingdom;</hi> and yet at the ſame Time <hi>Teaches</hi> us to <hi>pray, Thy Kingdom come;</hi> It ſignifies plainly and neceſſarily, That it hath not yet ſo come, as to Appear to be <hi>His:</hi> And that <hi>His is the Power;</hi> and yet at the ſame Time <hi>Taught us to pray, Thy Will be done,</hi> as in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>upon Earth;</hi> in the ſame plain manner he ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies, The <hi>Power</hi> does not yet Appear to be his; For wherein is Power ſeen, but in the having the <hi>Will of Him done,</hi> who hath that <hi>Power?</hi> And that <hi>his is the Glory,</hi> and yet at the ſame Time <hi>Teaches us to pray; Sanctified,</hi> or <hi>Glorified by Thy Name;</hi> This ſhews very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly, the <hi>Glory is not His,</hi> as it ſhall be. By All This it Ariſes clearly to our Notice, That <hi>Our Lord</hi> hath, in putting this <hi>Doxology</hi> into our Mouths, put a Prophecy into our Mouths; That the Time is coming, according to the Meaſures Given us in <hi>his Word of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy;</hi> when the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and the <hi>Power,</hi> and the <hi>Glory,</hi> ſhall in full and higheſt Senſe be Aſcrib'd to God; and as at a very <hi>preſent Time</hi> in that fulleſt Senſe; So that this <hi>Doxology</hi> of the <hi>Prayer</hi> Leads us to that, <hi>Revel.</hi> 4. 11. <hi>Thou art worthy, Oh Lord, to Receive Glory, and Honour, and Power; For thou haſt created All Things; and for thy pleaſure they are and were created.</hi> And c. 5. 13. And <hi>every Creature,</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:105089:34"/> 
                  <hi>which is in Heaven, and on the Earth, and under the Earth, and ſuch as are in the Sea, heard I, ſaying, Bleſſing, and Honour, and Glory, and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er be unto him that ſitteth upon the Throne, and unto the Lamb for ever and ever:</hi> c. 11. 17. <hi>We give Thee Thanks, Oh Lord God Almighty, which art, and waſt, and art to come; becauſe thou haſt taken to thee thy Great Power, and haſt Reigned; and the Nations were Angry, as at a thing not done before.</hi> c. 15. 3. <hi>Great and marvellous are thy Works, Lord God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty; Juſt and True are thy ways, Oh King of Saints; Who ſhall not Fear thee, Oh Lord, and Glorifie thy Name? For thou only art Holy; For All Nations ſhall come, and Worſhip before thee; For thy Judgments are made manifeſt. c.</hi> 19. 5. <hi>Hallelujah, Salvation, and Glory, and Honour, and Power unto the Lord our God; For True and Righteous are his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: And a Voice came out of the Throne, Praiſe Our God, All ye his Servants, and ye that Fear Him, both Small and Great. And I heard, as it were, the Voice of a Great Multitude, and as the Voice of many Waters, and as the Voice of mighty Thunderings; ſaying, Hallelujah; For the Lord God Omnipotent Reigneth.</hi> When theſe Great <hi>Doxologies</hi> come into their High, and Lofty, and Solemn Sounds, then ſhall this <hi>Doxology</hi> be both fully underſtood and fullfill'd, and not before; And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ſhews this <hi>Prayer</hi> to be the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Seal of this <hi>Prayer,</hi> both as to the Sincerity and Reality of our own Deſires, and of our Faith and Hope in God's Gracious An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and Giving Effect to our <hi>Prayers,</hi> is common to All <hi>Prayers,</hi> and yet moſt peculiar to this <hi>Prayer,</hi> as the Comprehenſionary <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> of all <hi>Prayers:</hi> And it is <hi>Amen;</hi> which hath the Force not only of <hi>So be It,</hi> as in other <hi>Prayers:</hi> but of <hi>So It is,</hi> or <hi>So It ſhall be;</hi> even in this <hi>Prayer,</hi> Taught by an <hi>Infallible Maſter of Prayer,</hi> who calls himſelf the <hi>Amen:</hi> And ſo was, and is Able to ſet with higheſt Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy the <hi>Amen</hi> to his own <hi>Prayer.</hi> And he will moſt certainly bring All Things to paſs, according to it, even as he is the <hi>Amen,</hi> the <hi>Faithful Witneſs,</hi> the <hi>Beginning,</hi> or mighty <hi>Principle,</hi> as of the Firſt, ſo of the <hi>New Creation of God.</hi> And therefore every <hi>Petition</hi> of it ſhall be Anſwer'd to even every <hi>Iota; Heaven and Earth ſhall paſs,</hi> but not <hi>one Iota of this Prayer ſhall paſs away, till All be fullfilled.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as it thus looks back to the whole <hi>Prayer,</hi> and every <hi>Iota</hi> of it; ſo it particularly reſpects the <hi>Doxology.</hi> We therefore find, as in Harmony with it, in Two Great <hi>Doxologies,</hi> this Word, <hi>Amen,</hi> ſet as in Capital Letters, and in moſt exalted Accents, <hi>Revel.</hi> 5. 14. When <hi>Every Creature in Heaven and Earth</hi> had ſaid, <hi>Bleſſing, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and Glory, and Power, be to Him that ſits on the Throne, and to the Lamb for ever and ever:</hi> The <hi>Four Living Creatures</hi> in the moſt ſolemn manner, <hi>ſaid Amen.</hi> And c. 19. 4. Where there had been a <hi>Voice</hi>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:105089:34"/> 
                  <hi>of much People in Heaven; Saying Allelujah,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The Four and Twenty Elders,</hi> and the <hi>Four Living Creature,</hi> Pronounced again in moſt Sollemn manner, <hi>Amen, Allelujah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And indeed <hi>Amen</hi> is a <hi>Word</hi> moſt Proper, and Peculiar to the <hi>Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> when <hi>All Prophecy,</hi> even the whole <hi>Myſtery</hi> of <hi>God, as He hath Spoken by all the Prophets,</hi> ſhall be <hi>Finiſhed;</hi> and when All <hi>Prayers of Saints</hi> Comprehended in this <hi>Prayer;</hi> which is beyond what we can <hi>Aske,</hi> or <hi>Think;</hi> (but as the <hi>Spirit helping our Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities with Groans,</hi> that are not to be <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ttered, makes Interceſſion for us,)</hi> ſhall be Fully Anſwered, and Fulfilled. So that though <hi>Amen</hi> be a Common Obſignation of all <hi>Prayer;</hi> yet it hath a much higher Sence in this <hi>Prayer,</hi> which Communicates it to All <hi>Prayer</hi> Flowing from, and Returning into it ſelf; and even the higheſt Sence of the <hi>Amen</hi> to this <hi>Prayer</hi> is, as it is the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom,</hi> and is Fulfilled in the <hi>Doxologies of the Kingdom,</hi> and of the <hi>Power,</hi> and of the <hi>Glory,</hi> which that <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſhall Produce: So that even this, however Common <hi>Amen</hi> of All <hi>Prayer,</hi> Expounded into its Full Sence, as ſet to this <hi>Prayer</hi> is alſo a Proof to us; This <hi>Prayer</hi> is the <hi>Prayer</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> a <hi>Prayer</hi> with a <hi>Supream A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> Peculiar to it.</p>
               <div type="objection_and_answer">
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                     </label> If any ſhould ſay, why is it then together with the <hi>Dox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ology</hi> wholy Omitted in the <hi>Goſpel of St. Luke?</hi> and then Eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, when <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, the Meſſiah, the Prince,</hi> Taught His <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> to <hi>Pray,</hi> as <hi>John the Fore-Runner,</hi> Taught his <hi>Diſciples;</hi> and where alſo, if any where, <hi>He</hi> Commands the uſe of it, as a <hi>Form?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> I can underſtand no Reaſon, but according to what hath been already Intimated; That <hi>Our Lord</hi> might ſhew, <hi>He</hi> did in neither Place Intend a Rigid <hi>Form;</hi> and leaſt of All, where it might be moſt Collected from His <hi>Words, He</hi> did Intend a <hi>Form</hi> as in the <hi>Evangeliſt Luke;</hi> yet here the <hi>Prayer</hi> Ariſes leaſt to a <hi>Form,</hi> being without the <hi>Doxology</hi> or the <hi>Amen:</hi> And that therefore we might be engaged upon that Rule of <hi>Praying after the manner of this Prayer,</hi> as it is Expounded to us in the whole <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> And Eſpecially in the <hi>Word,</hi> as it is moſt peculiarly the <hi>Word of the Kingdom;</hi> And particularly according to the <hi>manner</hi> of this <hi>Prayer,</hi> as given before <hi>by our Lord,</hi> according to the <hi>Evangeliſt Matthew;</hi> where we have the <hi>Doxology,</hi> and the <hi>Amen.</hi> And therefore to make Formal Repetition of the <hi>Prayer,</hi> as in <hi>Luke;</hi> without the <hi>Doxology,</hi> and <hi>Amen,</hi> as in <hi>Matthew,</hi> is a Groſs Offence againſt that <hi>Precept</hi> of our <hi>Lords in Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew; Pray after this manner,</hi> Extending to the <hi>Doxology,</hi> and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:105089:35"/> as much as to any part of the <hi>Prayer;</hi> and is by <hi>Conſequence</hi> to be joyned to it in <hi>Luke,</hi> where the Repetition of it is ſo <hi>Given</hi> as to make both One.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="review">
               <p>Let us now make a Review upon the whole <hi>Prayer,</hi> and behold the Order of it, as It is the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom;</hi> And Firſt <hi>Our Father,</hi> Who is now in the <hi>Heavens,</hi> will <hi>Rend,</hi> and <hi>Bow</hi> the <hi>Heavens;</hi> And they ſhall <hi>open to Him,</hi> as He Deſcends in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>only Begotten Son;</hi> and Receives his whole <hi>Adoption,</hi> made <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the Image of his Son</hi> in <hi>His Saints</hi> of the <hi>Firſt Reſurrection;</hi> who put on <hi>Incorruption;</hi> and the <hi>Saints Living Remaining, Changed;</hi> And the <hi>Creatures</hi> alſo <hi>waiting for the Manifeſtation of the Son of God</hi> are <hi>Delivered from the Bondage of Corruption</hi> into the <hi>Glorious Liberty of the Son, of God;</hi> And ſo He Appears the <hi>Father of Heaven and Earth</hi> as the <hi>Father of Chriſt,</hi> of whom the <hi>Whole Family of Heaven and Earth</hi> is Called; So the <hi>Whole Creation is Filled with His Glory,</hi> which is the <hi>Sanctification,</hi> or <hi>Glorification</hi> of <hi>His Name,</hi> by <hi>Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Immediately, even together with this Appearance of <hi>His Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> comes in the Univerſal <hi>Holineſs of Jehovah,</hi> Written on the <hi>Forheads of His Servants, Serving Him;</hi> which is His <hi>Will done,</hi> by His <hi>Saints</hi> in the <hi>New Heaven</hi> above, and the <hi>New Earth</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; and His Enemies Crouching Down at the <hi>Foot-Stool of His Feet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereupon follows the <hi>Marriage Supper of the Lamb;</hi> and the <hi>Eating,</hi> and <hi>Drinking,</hi> at <hi>His Table in His Kingdom;</hi> that is; the Full <hi>Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Bread of Life,</hi> the <hi>Super-Subſtantial Bread,</hi> in a Conſtant Uninterrupted <hi>Yeſterday,</hi> and <hi>to Day, the ſame For ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At this <hi>Supper,</hi> as ſo Great a <hi>Feſtival</hi> for it, There is an Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal <hi>Reconciliation of God by Chriſt,</hi> and of all the <hi>Saints,</hi> one with another; and of the whole <hi>Reſtored Creation,</hi> even thoſe <hi>Parts,</hi> which ſeem'd moſt at Enmity; which is the Univerſal <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs, as we are Forgiven;</hi> and a Perfect State of <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> in the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> that there can be no <hi>New Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> under our <hi>Great Melchiſedeck, King of Righteouſneſs, King of Peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the <hi>Serpent,</hi> and his <hi>Seed</hi> at the <hi>Foot-Stool of Chriſt, Eat Duſt,</hi> and cannot, ſo much, as Repaſt upon <hi>Temptation;</hi> For there ſhall be none; And at the ſame Time, the whole <hi>Curſe</hi> is Remooved; So that <hi>Sorrow and Sihgthing Flee away,</hi> and are <hi>Remembred no more,</hi> nor <hi>come into Mind.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:105089:35"/>
               <p> This Univerſal State of <hi>Glory</hi> Flows from the Univerſal <hi>Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and <hi>Kingdom of God,</hi> and therefore, it is <hi>Thundered out with E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Hallelujahs;</hi> The <hi>Lord God; Omnipotent Reigns;</hi> Reſounded, and Seal'd with a never Ending <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Our Lord</hi> hath given <hi>this All Comprehenſive Prayer</hi> from, and According to the very Firſt Beginning of His <hi>Kingdom</hi> in the <hi>Preaching,</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of His <hi>Goſpel,</hi> all along upon the Hearts of His Servants; unto, and untill His <hi>Kingdom</hi> in it's <hi>Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this Purpoſe <hi>He</hi> hath with a <hi>Divine Wiſdome</hi> drawn the <hi>Whole Counſel of God</hi> in <hi>His Word</hi> within it; So that to <hi>Pray after this manner</hi> is to <hi>Pray</hi> according to the whole Scope of <hi>Scripture,</hi> Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly Referred to every <hi>Petition;</hi> But Eſpecially with an Eye to the <hi>Glorious,</hi> and <hi>Illuſtrious Appearance</hi> of <hi>His Kingdom,</hi> Concerning which I would Appeal to All; whether theſe things are not the <hi>Highest Flights</hi> of <hi>Prayer,</hi> and moſt worthy to be the <hi>Higheſt Sence</hi> of the <hi>Prayer, Our Lord Taught.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The very <hi>Form</hi> is no further preſcribed, but that our Rule for the Frame of our <hi>Prayers</hi> ſhould from hence be underſtood; That we ought not to Compoſe <hi>Our Prayers</hi> to a Superſtitious <hi>much Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> or to <hi>Repetition</hi> for <hi>Repetitions or much ſpeaking ſake,</hi> nor with the Artifices of Feigned, and yet Blind Devotion according to Innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable Formalities.</p>
               <p>The Servants of God <hi>Praying</hi> according to this <hi>Whole Counſel of God in His Word, Pray</hi> into, and within this <hi>Prayer;</hi> For their <hi>Prayers</hi> are, as it were, Drawn within this <hi>Element of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er;</hi> And when they ſo <hi>Pray,</hi> they do indeed ſay, <hi>Our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Interceſſion of Chriſt</hi> Overſhaddows, Receives, and Preſerves all <hi>Prayers</hi> according to <hi>His Word,</hi> as if they Fell into the very <hi>Words</hi> of this <hi>Prayer;</hi> ſo that they are all within <hi>Gods Gracious Acceptance,</hi> and <hi>Remembrance,</hi> even as this very <hi>Prayer of Christ,</hi> which in Subſtance they are; and ſhall have beſides the Preſent a <hi>Full Anſwer</hi> in the <hi>Glorious Kingdom of Jeſus Christ;</hi> and they are all Bound up within that Great <hi>Interceſſory Prayer</hi> of <hi>Chriſt, John</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>But becauſe of the Various States of the <hi>Church,</hi> and of the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Chriſt,</hi> the Various Degrees of <hi>Light,</hi> and Opportunities of <hi>Knowledg;</hi> Their <hi>Prayers</hi> have been of a very different Elevati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Raiſedneſs of <hi>Apprehenſion,</hi> Faith and deſire with Relation to the <hi>Councel of God</hi> in his <hi>Word for Prayer,</hi> according to this <hi>Prayer;</hi> There are Three Expedients of <hi>Divine Grace,</hi> as <hi>Helps</hi> in this Great Concernment.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:105089:36"/> 1. There is ſuch an Unexpreſſible Concatenation, or Lincking all Parts of the <hi>Divine Kingdom;</hi> that what ever <hi>Saint of Chriſt</hi> is ſincerly poſſeſſed with any one Principle of it, and Prays accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to it, It Allies <hi>Him</hi> to the <hi>Whole;</hi> and it ſhall Lead <hi>Him</hi> into <hi>All,</hi> ſo far as is neceſſary to <hi>His Meaſure, His Stature in Christ;</hi> and it ſhall Unite <hi>His Prayer,</hi> with this <hi>Prayer of Christ,</hi> according to <hi>His Degree of Prayer</hi> in it; For even in <hi>Prayer</hi> one <hi>Saint differs from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Saint in Glory:</hi> Yet this ought not to ſtraiten, or Abate, but even to Excite the Weakeſt Saint, and to Encourage him to Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour an Attainment of the <hi>Full Aſſurance of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding in the Myſtery of God, and of the Father, and of Chriſt, and in Prayer;</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the whole <hi>VVord of God,</hi> with as Particular a Reſpect, as may be to this <hi>Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe the <hi>Church of Chriſt</hi> hath not as yet, in any Age Riſen, but very Little to the Heighth of this <hi>Prayer</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> And Few <hi>Saints</hi> in Compariſon Attaind it; <hi>The Spirit of God</hi> hath <hi>Helped them</hi> with <hi>Inward Grones,</hi> which they could not Articulate, or Utter; And ſo Proportionably in all the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely Neceſſary Points of This <hi>Prayer</hi> according to the <hi>VVord of God,</hi> wherein their Knowledg hath been Low, or Want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Interceſſion of Christ</hi> Receives the <hi>Prayers of</hi> All, who Sincerely <hi>Pray</hi> within this <hi>Prayer;</hi> And the <hi>Interceſſion of the Spirit</hi> Joyned with it makes their <hi>Prayer</hi> Effectual; Though They are not Enlarged in the <hi>Spiritual <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> of this <hi>Prayer</hi> in its <hi>Heighth,</hi> and <hi>Depth,</hi> in its <hi>Breadth,</hi> and <hi>Length.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. God is pleaſed to Underſtan His <hi>Children</hi> in their Weak <hi>Cries, Abba Father;</hi> and in their Loweſt Underſtanding of His <hi>VVord</hi> in this <hi>Prayer;</hi> and to know the Mind of His <hi>Spirit making Interceſſion according to His VVill;</hi> And He knows how to <hi>Give them the Beſt Things</hi> above any <hi>Earthly Parents,</hi> even the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> which they <hi>Ask, Seek, and Knock</hi> for, above their own Underſtanding; For He <hi>Interprets</hi> His own <hi>Spirit</hi> by a Word of theirs into its High Sences; So that they having the <hi>firſt Fruits</hi> of the <hi>Spirit Groan for</hi> that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and the Large Effuſions of that Spirit init; And ſo <hi>cry to Him Night and Day,</hi> and <hi>God hears them ſpeedily,</hi> that is in the very <hi>proper Times of the Kingdom of Chriſt;</hi> And that <hi>Kingdom comes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus this <hi>Prayer</hi> otherwiſe very hard to be Underſtood in its deſign, even by a Thinking, Conſidering <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> is one of the moſt Stupendious Mirrors of the <hi>VViſdom</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and with <hi>open Face</hi> ſhews the <hi>Glory of Christ;</hi> though as yet, but in a Glaſs; till in the <hi>Kingdom we ſee All, Face to Face.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="inferences">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:105089:36"/>
               <p> Let now ſome brief Inferential Reflections conclude the whole.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Infer. </seg>1</label> How profound, and hidden is the Judgment of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> World, which ſo contrary to the Literal and Expreſs Intendment of <hi>our Lord in this Prayer,</hi> againſt <hi>Heatheniſh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitions</hi> in <hi>Prayer,</hi> ſhould even Burleſque it; not only by <hi>vain Repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> but by offering to God, as in Sacrifice, theſe <hi>Repetitions,</hi> by Tale, and by Number of <hi>Beads?</hi> And All this in a ſtrange <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage,</hi> as if they hop'd to be heard for their <hi>much ſpeaking,</hi> and their <hi>meer ſpeaking. Well ſaid the Divine Spirit by our Lord; As the Heathen do:</hi> For they proclaim aloud, They are the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that Tread the <hi>Outward Court of the Chriſtian Prafeſſion under Foot,</hi> and have done ſo for near theſe 1260. <hi>Years.</hi> now within Five at an End, <hi>Revel.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Infer. </seg>2</label> Too near Them do the Ignorant and Carnal <hi>Proteſtants</hi> approach; <hi>Proteſtants</hi> they call Themſelves; who yet <hi>knowing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Scriptures,</hi> of the <hi>Power of God,</hi> or of <hi>his Wiſdom,</hi> in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to this <hi>Prayer,</hi> hope yet to be accepted by Formal <hi>Repetitions</hi> of it: Theſe, however they Name themſelves, are but in <hi>the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Court,</hi> where thoſe very <hi>Gentiles</hi> are, laſt ſpoken of; and which is <hi>Trodden under Foot</hi> by <hi>thoſe Gentiles.</hi> And though theſe <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> as they are in a General Courſe of Charity, Call'd; do not <hi>Tread under Foot</hi> that <hi>Court,</hi> in the Groſs <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> manner, the Other do; yet they are in no better a State, than to be in the <hi>Outward Court</hi> or the <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of Chriſtianity, ſo <hi>Trodden under Foot by Gentiles;</hi> which is a very dangerous State.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Infer. </seg>3</label> Seeing this <hi>Prayer</hi> is ſuch an Admirable Foundation of <hi>Prayer,</hi> both as to Matter and Form, which the <hi>Supreme Maſter-Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> hath <hi>Laid; Let every one take heed, how he builds upon it in Prayer;</hi> For if he <hi>lay</hi> upon it <hi>Gold, Silver, Precious Stones;</hi> that is, truly <hi>Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, Scriptural Prayer</hi> and <hi>Praiſes;</hi> his <hi>Building</hi> ſhall <hi>endure.</hi> But if <hi>Hay, Stubble, Wood,</hi> either as to Matter, or <hi>Form,</hi> or <hi>Repetition of this Prayer</hi> it ſelf; He himſelf, if he hold the <hi>Foundation of Prayer,</hi> as it is laid in this <hi>Prayer, He himſelf ſhall be ſaved,</hi> but ſo as <hi>by Fire;</hi> For <hi>His Work</hi> will be <hi>Loſt; The Day will burn it up,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Infer. </seg>4</label> It is very Admirable, how Chriſt hath <hi>put a VVord,</hi> a <hi>Prayer,</hi> even into the <hi>Mouth of Balaam,</hi> and thoſe that <hi>Hold his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine;</hi> even big with their own Doom, and with that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> which will ſhatter their Foundation, and <hi>ſmite their Corners.</hi> This is the <hi>Prayer of the Church,</hi> the <hi>Chaſte Bride,</hi> which ſays,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:105089:37"/> 
                  <hi>Come;</hi> but the <hi>Falſe Adulterous Church, the Whore,</hi> and her <hi>Children, ſhall find it,</hi> as <hi>the Jealouſie-Water,</hi> to the <hi>proſtituted VVife;</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conveyed, as in a <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> ſhall make the <hi>Belly to ſwell,</hi> and the <hi>Thigh to Rot;</hi> That is, All ſuch ſhall be utterly <hi>conſum'd,</hi> and become <hi>a Curſe in the Earth,</hi> by this very <hi>Prayer,</hi> Numb. 5. 21.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Infer. </seg>5</label> This Great Duty of <hi>Prayer</hi> muſt be ſo underſtood, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd, and ſpiritually managed by ſuch ſaving Knowledge, ſincere Faith and Repentance; that all our <hi>Prayers</hi> may fall within this Great <hi>Prayer;</hi> and ſo within the <hi>Interceſſion</hi> of the Great <hi>Mediator,</hi> whoſe <hi>Prayer</hi> it is; within the <hi>Interceſſion</hi> of the <hi>Spirit within us,</hi> and ſo within the Acceptance of God, as a <hi>Father</hi> Giving the <hi>Beſt Things,</hi> his <hi>Spirit,</hi> his <hi>Kingdom,</hi> to them that <hi>Ask him;</hi> who, when They <hi>Pray,</hi> do truly ſay, <hi>Abba Father,</hi> or <hi>Our Father.</hi> Elſe this <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> will be as Dangerous as the <hi>Gospel,</hi> when it is a <hi>Dead Savour,</hi> and ſo <hi>unto Death;</hi> and as the <hi>Lord's Supper, Eaten and Drunk unworthily,</hi> which is an <hi>Eating</hi> and <hi>Drinking unto Judgment.</hi> So this <hi>Prayer</hi> will <hi>turn unto Sin</hi> unto us, and be a <hi>Sacrifice of Abomination,</hi> having not its due Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance with God, nor ſanctifying Effect upon our Hearts.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Infer. </seg>6</label> This <hi>Prayer</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is ſo <hi>wonderfully made,</hi> that it ought to be underſtood, to be prayed by the <hi>whole VVord of God</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightning it; which is the beſt Comment, or Expoſition upon it; And the <hi>Spirit of the VVord of God</hi> is the <hi>Spirit of this Prayer.</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to which <hi>Word of God,</hi> if we do <hi>pray,</hi> our <hi>Prayers</hi> ſlide into it, as the <hi>Rivers into the Sea,</hi> and find ſecret and inſenſible Paths into it. Although we do not uſe the <hi>Form,</hi> yet when we <hi>pray</hi> according to the <hi>Word of God,</hi> we ſhall ſay, <hi>Our Father,</hi> &amp;c. And if we uſe the <hi>Form</hi> never ſo often, if we have not the <hi>Spirit of this Prayer,</hi> the <hi>Word of God mixed with Faith in the Heart;</hi> It becomes as an Empty Ineffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacious <hi>Form</hi> firſt, and then a <hi>Condemnation out of our own Mouths.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Infer. </seg>7</label> This teaches us the True Way and Method of magnify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this <hi>Prayer;</hi> not by multiplied <hi>Repetitions,</hi> ſo contrary to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Deſign of it; not by a Great Appearance of Devotion in the <hi>ſaying</hi> of it, as the moſt <hi>Abſolute</hi> and <hi>Comprehenſive Form of Words,</hi> as Men Love to ſpeak. An Intellectual Derivation from it, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating the <hi>whole Word of God</hi> to it is the Trueſt Honour of it. And if we have ſo Deriv'd from it, and Related to it in our <hi>Prayers;</hi> the Concluſion of our <hi>Prayers,</hi> by a bare <hi>Repetition,</hi> cannot equal that Foregoing uſe of it; but is even unneceſſary, if not <hi>ſuperfluous</hi> and <hi>ſuperſtitious;</hi> except enlarged Underſtanding, Zeal, and inflamed Affection inſpire that Repetition.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:105089:37"/>
               <p> For I would Appeal to Any Man of Reaſon, and Wiſdom; When he hath offered to Men the Exercitation of that Wiſdom, and Reaſon, God hath Given to him, by Diſcourſe, or Writing; Which, he thinks, does the Greateſt Honour to it? He who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandingly Digeſts, and Diſcourſes out of that, which he hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd, and makes ſubſtantial References thereunto, and draws the Senſe of it into his own proper Diſcourſes or Writings, though with little or no <hi>Repetition?</hi> or he that makes, what he hath ſaid, a <hi>Form,</hi> without Rational enlargement upon it? It is eaſie to know, which he would prefer; Even ſo it is eaſie to judge, who is moſt Acceptable to our <hi>Great, Wiſe, Holy,</hi> and <hi>Spiritual Maſter,</hi> in this <hi>Prayer;</hi> He that Complements his <hi>Prayer</hi> by many Interlineations of bare Repetition of the <hi>Form;</hi> or he, who in an Abundance of <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual VViſdom</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, prays</hi> according to his whole Goſpel, compriz'd in that <hi>Prayer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Infer. </seg>8</label> Hereby we come to underſtand, what Place <hi>Prayer</hi> may yet have, although <hi>Our Lord</hi> tells us, <hi>Our Heavenly Father knows what Things we have need of, before we ask him;</hi> For it might ſeem in ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that All <hi>Prayer,</hi> yea, even the ſingle uſe of this <hi>Prayer,</hi> were taken away, and cut off by this undoubted Principle; that our Father knows before-hand; yea<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and hath alſo determined before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, what to give us; as he hath alſo taught us in this <hi>Prayer, what to Ask.</hi> What a Formality then may All <hi>Prayer,</hi> or even this <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> ſeem to be, when it is offered to him, who can neither be inform'd nor chang'd? Not inform'd; For he knows both our State and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, our Wants, and Natural Cravings, before we have dreſs'd them up in the Formality of <hi>Prayers;</hi> And he cannot be chang'd, becauſe he hath alſo Reſolv'd, what is moſt convenient to our State, with Relation to that Supreme End, his <hi>own Glory,</hi> before we <hi>Ask Him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But when we conſider the <hi>VVord of God,</hi> as the Great Treaſury of his <hi>Counſels,</hi> concerning every particular Perſon, and their Caſe; and concerning his <hi>Church and Kingdom</hi> in General; and that Chriſt's Drawing theſe into <hi>Prayer</hi> muſt needs be the Great Rule of <hi>Prayer.</hi> We may then underſtand the Reaſon of this <hi>Prayer of our Lord;</hi> Becauſe we know not how, with certainty, to draw out, and with a Juſt Ballance, to weigh out the Grand Principles and Meaſures of Prayers and Deſires; Our Lord hath given us this Beam in this <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er:</hi> And becauſe He knew, Thoſe very Principles of Prayer can Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their True, and Full Anſwer only in his <hi>Kingdom;</hi> He hath therefore made his <hi>Kingdom</hi> the Load-Star of it. Thus All Things are made conformable to the <hi>VVill of God</hi> in this <hi>Our Lord's Prayer,</hi> as the <hi>Prayer of the Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:105089:38"/>
               <p> But ſtill It may be ſaid, why any <hi>Prayer</hi> at All? God knows All theſe Things before, and hath Reſolved them, They being All His own <hi>Counſels:</hi> So He needs neither to be Informed, nor Moov'd; or if for any Reaſon, Things ought to be humbly Repreſented to <hi>God,</hi> what need any other Prayer but this Prayer only, <hi>Taught by our Lord Jeſus Christ?</hi> who thus certainly knew the <hi>Mind of God,</hi> and hath put that <hi>Mind</hi> into ſuch Words, as will be moſt Accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p>The Anſwer is; <hi>Prayer</hi> in the great Wiſdom, and Goodneſs of God is Ordaind a Tye of <hi>Communion,</hi> and Gracious Indearments betwixt our God and us; That we by His Word Inſtructed, in the <hi>Counſells of Grace, of Mercy, of Holineſs, and Wiſdom, for the Eternal Glory of his Church,</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> in General; and of our ſelves in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; and in all outward Things ſo far, as are Neceſſary here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; and Influenced by His <hi>Spirit,</hi> and Excited by our particular Neceſſities, might with Earneſtneſs Remonſtrate His own <hi>Counſels;</hi> our Hearts and Affections being every way prepared, and diſpoſed thereunto: And God Graciouſly giving, and bringing things to paſs, as at our Defires and Petitions, Oh, how great is the Indear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? As <hi>David</hi> ſays, <hi>I will Love the Lord, becauſe he hath Heard my Supplication, He Inclined to me, and heard my Cry,</hi> and upon this Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, <hi>I will call upon Him, as long, as I Live.</hi> And becauſe <hi>Prayer</hi> is according to <hi>His own Counſels,</hi> and thus prepared to the indearing our Hearts to God; Therefore he Stiles <hi>Himſelf a God hearing Prayers, that to him all Fleſh may come; And He is nigh to them, that call upon him, that call upon Him in Truth. He will fullfill the Deſire of them that Fear Him, He</hi> alſo will hear their City, and ſave them: And they that thus <hi>Hope in His Mercy,</hi> more then in all Created <hi>Leggs, He</hi> takes <hi>Pleaſure</hi> in, as thoſe that will be moſt Moov'd to <hi>Fear and Love Him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it may be ſtill Urged. Either the giving of this <hi>Prayer</hi> may Excuſe our Looking into the <hi>VVord,</hi> and we may be moſt ſecure in <hi>praying this Prayer</hi> only, as moſt certainly according to the <hi>VVord;</hi> or this <hi>Prayer</hi> can do us no Service; For ſtill our buſineſs is to Look into all the <hi>VVord of God,</hi> and then how are we helped by this <hi>Prayer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To this, the Anſwer Lies in Two Things, giving account of the Reaſon of this <hi>Prayer</hi> Taught by Chriſt; notwithſtanding it is our Duty, to Look into the Whole <hi>VVord,</hi> and to <hi>Pray this Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> according to it; with the moſt Enlarged Underſtandings, Affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Expreſſions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. This <hi>Prayer</hi> and the Several <hi>Petitions</hi> of it are as Sea-Marks and Land-Marks, in the vaſt Compaſs and Ocean of the <hi>VVord of God,</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:105089:38"/> Guiding us to the Great Fundamentals of <hi>Prayer,</hi> and ſetting Juſt and Due Bounds to us therein.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It does Eſpecially Winde up our <hi>Hearts,</hi> Thoughts, and Affection in all <hi>Spirituall VViſdome</hi> and <hi>Prudence,</hi> and Intellectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Sence to the <hi>Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> when it is Fully under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; (as I have now made out,) and which is the higheſt Flight of <hi>Prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſeeing, it is only thus, as I have ſhewn, to be uſed; even when it is Repeated; and not by way of meer Form, and Languid <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition;</hi> It ſhews the Neceſſity of the <hi>word of God, dwelling Richly in us in all VViſdom;</hi> that we may without ſuch <hi>Forbidden Repetition;</hi> or Thinking <hi>to be heard for our much Speaking; Continue in Prayer, and Abound therein with Thankſgiving:</hi> And if we make the <hi>Repetition</hi> of this Prayer only to Sum up our Prayers; To do it; when we find our hearts Enflamed, and Running out of Choiſe into theſe Words, with moſt Elarged Underſtandings, and Affections.</p>
               <p>And this is indeed an Admirable <hi>Communion with God</hi> in <hi>Prayer;</hi> and frees it from the Ignorance of a Blind Devotion, and from all the Fopperies of Superſtition, or the poſſible Unreaſonableneſs of Thinking to Inform, or Change God; And it ſhews us, <hi>Prayer is not for God,</hi> as if <hi>He</hi> any way wanted it; But it is for us, to Conform us to God, and to the higheſt Conſpiring with His Will, with His Glory; and to draw up the Faith, Love, Obedience, Reverence, and higheſt Honour of our Spirits upon Him. And ſo we Obſerve the True Ends of our Lords giving this Prayer in our either Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing according to it, out of the whole Word of God, or making a Recital of it; as we find our hearts carried on ſo to Recite it at Some Time, more than Another, and not in a Ritual maner.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Infer. </seg>9</label> Seeing the <hi>Kingdom of God,</hi> and the <hi>Righteouſneſs of it</hi> the <hi>Peace and Glory of Chriſt</hi> is the higheſt <hi>Counſel</hi> of God, for the <hi>Glory of God,</hi> and of <hi>his Saints;</hi> and even for the Glory and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of <hi>His Creation;</hi> Therefore This muſt needs be the higheſt Point of <hi>Prayer,</hi> and therefore this <hi>Prayer,</hi> the Standard and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amplar of <hi>Prayer;</hi> In this then we according to the Nature, and Duty of <hi>Prayer</hi> ſhould Conſpire with the <hi>Counſel of</hi> God, and <hi>Cry, Day, and Night</hi> to <hi>Him</hi> for it; But alaſs, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid, when the <hi>Son of Man Comes, ſhall He find Faith on the Earth?</hi> Even thoſe, who Continually Roll over this <hi>Prayer</hi> by Affected <hi>Repetition,</hi> leaſt pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate, and Enter into the Sence of it; in their Eyes and hearts upon the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> as it is Intended, and deſigned in it; And e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thoſe, who have underſtood, and deſire'd it more, yet have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood it only in the General notions of the <hi>Coming of Chriſt to Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and of the <hi>Reſurrection.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:105089:39"/>
               <p> This hath been the <hi>Slumber of the Apoſtacy</hi> upon the <hi>Chriſtian World;</hi> even upon the <hi>VViſe Virgins;</hi> ſo that the <hi>Comming of Chriſt</hi> will be a Surprize upon them; That is; <hi>His Comming</hi> in another ſort of a Kingdom, then they expected in their <hi>Slumber,</hi> and in the Time of the <hi>Bridegrooms Delay;</hi> Yet notwithſtanding, All that are indeed <hi>VViſe,</hi> who have <hi>Oyl</hi> in their <hi>Veſſels,</hi> and not in their <hi>Lamps</hi> only; that is, <hi>Grace in their Hearts,</hi> not in <hi>Profeſſion only, ſhall go with Chriſt in to the Wedding;</hi> Although in this true Explained Notion of <hi>His Kingdom, He</hi> will not, when <hi>He Cometh, Find Faith on Earth:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it is very Obſervable, that tho this <hi>Prayer</hi> hath not been A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakenedly Underſtood, as is ought to be; Yet by the Secret Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of <hi>Providence,</hi> and <hi>Government of the Church;</hi> Either the <hi>Form of this Prayer</hi> hath ſo Prevaled in the <hi>Church of Chriſt;</hi> Or the Sence of the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt</hi> in the General, and Vertual; or in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and more Expreſs Notions of it according to the <hi>Goſpel of the Kingdom</hi> have ſo derived from, and Fallen into <hi>this Prayer;</hi> that there hath been always a <hi>Generation</hi> of the Sincere <hi>Servants of God, and of Chriſt,</hi> that have Cryed to <hi>Him Day and Night,</hi> for <hi>His King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> and according to this <hi>Praayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Infer. </seg>10</label> However; The <hi>Foundation of God Remaineth Sure:</hi> In this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> The <hi>Promiſes</hi> of <hi>God</hi> are <hi>Yea, and Amen;</hi> And in this <hi>Prayer,</hi> To, the <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> is the Great and True <hi>Amen,</hi> and <hi>Yea</hi> of it ſet: On which Account, as I have ſaid, The <hi>Amen</hi> of this <hi>Prayer</hi> is of an Elevated Note, and in <hi>Harmony</hi> with All the <hi>Promiſes,</hi> that are <hi>Yea,</hi> and <hi>Amen</hi> in <hi>Him;</hi> Therefore, after the declaring <hi>His Coming in the Clouds,</hi> Rev. 1. 17. It is Added, <hi>Yea, Amen;</hi> and after His own <hi>ſaying,</hi> When He had <hi>Teſtified His Coming in His King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> in the Four Chapters before, <hi>Behold I come quickly;</hi> It is Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by His Servants in their <hi>Prayers,</hi> Comprehended in this <hi>Prayer; Amen, Yea, Come Lord Jeſus;</hi> And therefore it is Certain, <hi>He will come to His Servants,</hi> in and according to this <hi>Prayer, Crying to Him Day and Night,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; the Conſtant Notice of <hi>His Kingdom; Speedily, Quickly; Yea,</hi> and <hi>Amen. Amen,</hi> and <hi>Yea; Even So, Even So, Be It:</hi> Let him who is the <hi>Amen,</hi> the <hi>Fatihful Witneſs,</hi> the <hi>Amen</hi> of all the <hi>Promiſes</hi> in <hi>His Kingdom Come</hi> according to the <hi>Amen of</hi> this <hi>Prayer, Comprehending the Prayers of All Saints; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Yea. Revel.</hi> 22. 12. 20.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:105089:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:105089:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
